<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Statutes of the Colledge of Physicians London worthy to be perused by all men, but more especially physicians, lawyers, apothecaries, surgeons, and all such that either do, or shall study, profess, or practise physick.</title>
            <author>Royal College of Physicians of London.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 205 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 116 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57783</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R2123</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R218472</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99830061</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99830061</idno>
            <idno type="VID">34510</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57783)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 34510)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2017:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Statutes of the Colledge of Physicians London worthy to be perused by all men, but more especially physicians, lawyers, apothecaries, surgeons, and all such that either do, or shall study, profess, or practise physick.</title>
                  <author>Royal College of Physicians of London.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 12, 201, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Domini 1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Divisional title page on pg. 1(second series): Statuta collegii medicorum Loninensium. The statutes (or by-laws) of the Colledge of Physicians of London; separate pagination and register; in Latin.</note>
                  <note>With index on pg. 172-175.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original at the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Royal College of Physicians of London --  Rules and practice --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:34510:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE STATUTES OF THE COLLEDGE OF Phyſicians <hi>LONDON: <hi>Worthy to be peruſed by all Men,</hi>
               </hi> But more Eſpecially PHYSICIANS, LAWYERS, APOTHECARIES, SURGEONS, AND All ſuch that either do, or ſhall Study, Profeſs, or Practiſe <hi>PHYSICK.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>ANNO DOMINI</hi> 1693.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:34510:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:34510:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:34510:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:34510:3"/>
            <head>To the PARLIAMENT OF <hi>ENGLAND.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>MOST Renowned Aſſembly, whoſe Vigilancy and Care for the Publick Good, all Ages have ſufficiently experienced, and in whoſe Determination the People of <hi>England,</hi> calmly, content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly, and conſcienciouſly acquieſce; tho the corruptions and perverſions of ill men have frequently ſubverted your moſt Generous Deſigns for the Publick Good, to their own baſe and private Intereſts; among the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of which, it were heartily to be wiſh'd that the moſt Noble and Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Art of <hi>Phyſick</hi> were not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ituted and perverted (by men
<pb facs="tcp:34510:4"/>ſtrictly ſworn to the contrary) to the avarice, pride, and oppreſſion of a few, who not content private<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to enſlave and abuſe men, by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acting Fourſcore or a Hundred Pounds, for an Admiſſion, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Examination; but open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enact By-Laws, contrary to Act of Parliament and the Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Good of Mankind, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding (without any reſpect of their Due and Legal Qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Abilities) particular men from being ſerviceable to the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick; as will plainly appear to thoſe who ſhall attentively examine the following Caſe, and Statutes. The prudent and ſeaſonable redreſs of which Enormities, moſt Worthy Patriots, when time and opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity ſhall preſent, is humbly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to your Determination and Judgement.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:34510:4"/>
            <head>The Baſe, Diſhonourable, and Ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Dealing of the <hi>Colledge</hi> of <hi>Phyſicians, London,</hi> with a Doctor in Phyſick, admitted to that Degree in one of our own <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities;</head>
            <p>WHo in <hi>July, Auguſt,</hi> and <hi>Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember,</hi> in the year 1683, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented himſelf to the Preſident and Cenſors, to be examined; Doctor <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas Coxe</hi> Preſident, <hi>Samuel Collins,</hi> Senior Regiſter, <hi>Walter Charleton, Thomas Allen, Nathaniel Hodges, Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Hulſt,</hi> Cenſors: and was by them examined (<hi>Chap.</hi> 15. <hi>pag.</hi> 112.) three ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral times in Latine, according to the Form of the Statutes (<hi>Chap.</hi> 16. <hi>pag.</hi> 119, 120, 123.) in that Caſe provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; and was approved (<hi>Chap.</hi> 15. <hi>pag.</hi> 111.) and had leave given by the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:34510:5"/>and Cenſors, after Examination (<hi>Chap.</hi> 16. <hi>pag.</hi> 124.) to viſit the Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, and did accordingly viſit all the Fellows, in order to be admitted Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiate (<hi>Chap.</hi> 11. <hi>pag.</hi> 79, 80.) and at the ſame time was requeſted and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired by them, in the behalf of the whole Colledge; and withal comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, how extreamly he ſhould ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidge and highly honour that Society, if he would be pleaſed to ſuſpend his Admiſſion of Licentiate (and which they confeſt they could not deny) till ſuch time as he had quitted his Imployment in Pharmacy, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleated his Degree (being then Batche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour in Phyſick) of Doctor in the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity; and that then, without any farther trouble of viſiting the Fellows, or other Examinations, and for the very ſame Fees, by vertue of thoſe Examinations ſtanding regiſtred in their Books (if they eſcape the fate of being cut out, as ſome other things have been) he might be admitted Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didate, the more honourable ſtation in
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:34510:5"/>their Society, and which he better de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, and they did then propoſe to him Doctor <hi>Liſter</hi>'s Caſe, as a Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent for the ſame thing: On theſe Conſiderations he ſubmitted to and gratified their Requeſt.</p>
            <p>Four years now elapſed, and by their advice, having regularly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleated his Degree of Doctor in Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick (<hi>July</hi> 6. 1687.) performing all Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes required by the Statutes of the Univerſity of <hi>Cambridge</hi> (and as 14, 15 of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. accompliſhing all things for his Form, without any grace) as his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploma to them ſhewn, and the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter in that Univerſity will ſufficiently teſtifie; he applied himſelf to the then Preſident of the Colledge in the year 1687, for his Admiſſion (as formerly directed and promiſed, by the Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and Cenſors, in the behalf of the whole Colledge in the year 1683.) from whom he had a courteous recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and acknowledgement that it was all the Reaſon and Juſtice in the World that he ſhould have his Admiſſion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:34510:6"/>ſaith he, we cannot deny it him; (<hi>Chap.</hi> 15. <hi>p.</hi> 119. <hi>l.</hi> 8.) and then advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him to wait till next Colledge day, and there give his attendance; which he accordingly did, and was then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to another opportunity, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon the Colledge was then ingaged in private buſineſs (<hi>viz.</hi> Making New Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes (<hi>N.</hi> 8, 16.) of Excluſion) and no publick buſineſs would at that time be entred on; he attended again and again, and was ſtill deferred: During theſe delays the private buſineſs is ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, and the New Statutes of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion are made and promulgated in the Theatre, <hi>September</hi> 28. 1687.</p>
            <p>After theſe New Statutes were made, he was adviſed to wait on the Preſident and Cenſors on a private Colledge day, to demand his Admiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and did accordingly; and had for anſwer from them their New Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, which Mr. Regiſter would needs read: To which he anſwered, Theſe Statutes cannot relate to my Caſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made above four years ſince the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:34510:6"/>deſires, requeſts, and directions of this Board, in behalf of the whole Colledge, were made to me to ſuſpend my Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion till I had compleated my De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of Doctor; beſides, I have lately attended ſeveral times on the Colledge for my Admiſſion in <hi>July, Auguſt, Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember</hi> 1687. ſince I was Doctor in Phyſick, and before theſe Statutes were made or promulgated.</p>
            <p>However, ſo it was, that unleſs he would abjure the Company of Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries (as well as he had, by their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and directions, quitted his imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in Pharmacy in the year 1684.) and bring it atteſted under the hand, or by the perſon of a Publick Notary, that he had relinquiſh'd &amp; abjured that Society, he ſhould not be admitted.</p>
            <p>And now, for the further illuſtration of their Honour, Juſtice, and Credit, in this Caſe, I will give you an Advertiſement publiſh'd by the Colledge of Phyſicians <hi>London,</hi> in the Gazette; as alſo what they have an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed to his moſt Sacred Majeſties Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:34510:7"/>and publiſh'd by the conſent of the whole Colledge in 1688.</p>
            <closer>Gazette N. 2325.
<date>Thurſday 1 <hi>March</hi> 1687.</date>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>WHereas there are in and about this City ſeveral Perſons practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Phyſick, who have not yet been exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined and licenſed by the Preſident and Cenſors of the Colledge of Phyſicians, theſe are to require all ſuch perſons forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to repair to the ſaid Preſident and Cenſors, for their Examination and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence to practiſe, that they may hereby prevent their being proſecuted according to the Laws and his Majeſties ſpecial Command.</p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:34510:7"/>
            <head>'A ſhort Account of the Inſtitution and Nature of the Colledge of Phyſicians <hi>London.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">Publiſhed 1688.</head>
            <q>
               <p>THe Colledge of Phyſicians in <hi>London,</hi> being conſtituted of men of generous and liberal Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and inſtituted for publick be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit, out of which no perſon of ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient Capacity and Learning can be excluded, conſiſts of a <hi>Preſident, Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, Candidates, Honorary Fellows,</hi> and <hi>Licentiates.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Fellows</hi> are Doctors of Phyſick choſen out of the <hi>Candidates,</hi> who have been always limited to a certain number (formerly Forty) and are now confined to the number of Four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore, by his preſent Majeſties graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Charter.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:34510:8"/>2. <hi>Candidates</hi> muſt be Doctors in Phyſick, admitted to that Degree in one of our own Univerſities, muſt not be Foreigners, and ought to have practiſed Phyſick four years before they are admitted into that Order.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Honorary Fellows</hi> are ſuch Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors in Phyſick, as by reaſon of their being Foreigners, or having taken their Degree in ſome Univerſity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Seas, are not incorporated into either of ours; or for ſome other reaſon (having not been Candidates) are not of the number of thoſe who have Votes in the Affairs of the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</p>
               <p>The Reader will find no ſuch Rank or Degree inſtituted either in the Old or New Statutes, but was at firſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly and juſtly diſpenſed with about the year 1660, for thoſe who thorow the iniquity of the times, were forced from the Univerſities, and ſo could not orderly take their Degrees at
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:34510:8"/>home; but were compelled to take them abroad in Foreign Univerſities, and were therefore numbred among the <hi>Honoraries</hi> (<hi>Chap.</hi> 12. <hi>p.</hi> 91, 92.) <hi>viz.</hi> the Kings, Queens, and Princes Phyſicians; that ſo they might be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to their Seniority and Standing: but have ſince been continued and perverted to the detriment of our U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſities, and the ſcandal of the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, by admitting all foreign De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, or any elſe (without Examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for money, 80 or 100 <hi>l.</hi>) into an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, which the Statutes have not or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Licentiates,</hi> are ſuch other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons skilled in Phyſick, who by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of their being Foreigners, or their not being admitted Doctors in one of our Univerſities, or for their not being eminently learned, or by reaſon of their too great youth, or ſuch like cauſes, are not capable to be elected into the number of the Candidates, yet may notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding be ſerviceable to the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:34510:9"/>in taking care of the health of the Kings Subjects, at leaſt in ſome particular Diſeaſes.</p>
            </q>
            <p>The Act of Parliament makes no ſuch Diſtinctions, ſave the Eight Elects, but that all ſhall be one Body and Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip; as in <hi>Anno</hi> 14, 15. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>Cap.</hi> 5 ſaith, Have incorporate and made of Us, and of our Company afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, one Body and perpetual Commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty or Fellowſhip of the Faculty of Phyſick, and to have perpetual Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion and Common Seal: And further <hi>Quod nemo in dicta Civitate, aut per ſeptem milliaria in circuitn ejuſdem, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erceat dictam Facultatem, niſi ad hoc per dictum Praeſidentem &amp; Communita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, ſeu Succeſſores eorum, qui pro tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore fuerint, admiſſus ſit per ejuſdem Praeſidentis &amp; Collegii Literas Sigillo ſuo Communi Sigillatas.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Now, of all theſe ſeveral Ranks and Degrees of Practiſers in Phyſick, none of them is confined to any certain num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:34510:9"/>but the Fellows and Candidates; (but not according to the Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament) ſo that the reſt being wholly unlimited, no perſon can be excluded out of the Colledge, or debarred from Practice, but ſuch as are ſo wholly il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>literate and unskilful, that they dare not adventure to ſubmit themſelves to the Examination and Judgement of the Preſident and Cenſors of the Colledge, either as to the goodneſs of their Medicines, or their own skill in all or any part of Phyſick, though the Preſident and Cenſors be men ſtrictly ſworn to do Juſtice to all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons who ſhall preſent themſelves or their Medicines to their Scrutiny and Examination.</p>
               <p>From hence it meniſeſtly follows that the Colledge of Phyſicians is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry far from being a Monopoly, ſince it cannot reject any of the King's Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects who are duly qualified for the Exerciſe of all, or any part of Phyſick.</p>
            </q>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:34510:10"/>
            <p>From all theſe publiſhed Advertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and following Statutes, it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly follows that Doctor <hi>I.B<hi rend="sup">gr.</hi>
               </hi> is and has been legally and duly a Member of the Colledge of Phyſicians <hi>London</hi> for theſe Ten years laſt paſt, although his Name be not printed in their New Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogue of 1693. (which Catalogue, if examined by the Regiſters of our Univerſities, you will find many of thoſe Doctors Names either there not regiſtred, or many that have been im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed on the Univerſities; which will be well worth publiſhing in their next Impreſſion for the publick good and informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;) Or the Colledge guilty of publiſhing to the World moſt notorious falſhoods: and to uſe their own words, is very far from being any other then a perfect Monopoly (<hi>Pag.</hi> 119. exacting large Subſcriptions of our Univerſity men, beſides their pretended Fees, and admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting any for Fourſcore or a Hundred Pounds, without Examination firſt had <hi>Pag.</hi> 116. <hi>l.</hi> 1.) and Confederacy, to ſupport Ignorance (<hi>Pag.</hi> 83. <hi>l.</hi> 16, 20. <hi>P.</hi> 148. <hi>l.</hi> 7. <hi>P.</hi> 151. <hi>l.</hi> 18. <hi>P.</hi> 159. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>P.</hi> 160. <hi>l.</hi> 17. <hi>New Stat.</hi> N. 2, 10. and exclude regularly commenced Doctors in our own U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſities; and the King's Native Subjects, duly qualified for the Exerciſe of all and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry part of Phyſick.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:34510:10"/>
            <head>STATUTA COLLEGII MEDICORUM <hi>LONDINENSI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M.</hi>
            </head>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:34510:11"/>
            <p>QUum Regis Sereniſſimi HEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RICI VIII. Privatà gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tià, &amp; Publicis Parliamenti Decretis ſancitum ſit, ut Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legium Medicorum Londinenſium in decus Regni, &amp; ſalutem Reipublicae ſtabiliatur, Privilegiis muniatur, Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſionibus locupletetur, Electoribus inſigniatur, Praeſide, &amp; Cenſoribus gubernetur, Statutis dirigatur illaque de novo condendi facultate donetur; Conſiliariis adjuvetur, &amp; Literis per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuetur; Conſultiſſimum etiam No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis viſum eſt ut praeſcribamus: Primo qui ſint futuri Electores; quodque eorum ſit Officium, Tum quis ſit futurus Praeſes; quomodo, &amp; a qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus eligendus; quâ Lege obſtrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendus; quodnam ejus Officium, &amp; poteſtas: denique quis locus, atque dignitas: Deinde, quinam ſint fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turi Conſiliarii, quid illis fide datâ ſit praeſtand um quodque eorum ſit
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:34510:12"/>Officium, Locus, &amp; Poteſtas: Qui Cenſores Literarum, Morum, item<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Medicamentorum ſint conſtituen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di; quoque Officio, ex Juramento, illis ſit fungendum. Quodnam ſit Officium Theſaurarii, Regeſtarii, &amp; Bedelli. Poſtremò, quid reliquos deceat in ſui honorem &amp; Collegii decus, &amp; quâ ſponſione teneantur. Si quae Statuta condenda, ſi quae abroganda fuerint, quo id facere opporteat modo. Quae ſit Commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiorum, examinationum, atque ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſionum forma. Quae ſit Offenſae habenda ratio: cum aliis, quae uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſim ad omnes Collegii perſonas &amp; negotia ex aequo ſpectant. Enim verò nihil durabile eſt, quod Rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one, Modo, atque Ordine careat.</p>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:34510:13"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. I.</hi> De Electoribus Creandis.</head>
               <p>STatuimus igitur &amp; Ordinamus ut è Numero Sociorum Octo tantùm Electores creentur, qui gravitate, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teris, moribus, &amp; aetate caeteris praeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geant, Doctoratûſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> gradu inſigniantur, &amp; natione ſint Angli, quorum Offici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um erit ex Authoritate Collegii po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtridiè Divi Michaelis (ſi commodèfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eri poteſt, at verò ſi ob gravia quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam impedimenta id non licebit; tunc alio die ad eam rem magis idoneo modò ſit intra ſeptimanam à tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore Praeſtituto) in celebribus Comi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiis Praeſidem è numero Electorum eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere: ſi anni ſuperioris Praeſes defuncto annuo Officio ſuperfuerit, ſin autem defecerit ille quam primum id com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modè fieri poterit alium ſurrogare, ad plurimum intra dies 20 poſt quam is defecerit. Deficere autem Praeſidem
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:34510:14"/>vel Electorem intelligimus, ſi vel mortuus fuerit, vel è Collegio ſit ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſus, vel cum pannis, ut aiunt, a Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitate diſceſſerit, &amp; per annum inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grum abſuerit, niſi ſit in Miniſterio Principis.</p>
               <p>Si Electorum unus aut plures ita defecerint Electione novâ ſufficiatur alius aut plures in ejus aut eorum locum ex caeteris Sociis qui ejuſdem Nationis, Gradus, Morum, Doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae, atque Ordinis erunt, intra dies 30 aut ſaltem 40; ſed ita ut illis Comitiis ſoli Electores interſint, quò liberior fiat Electio, &amp; morum, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genii, gravitatis ac Doctrinae juſtior examinatio, quas omnes Virtules in Electore vel maxime requirunt Statu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta Regni.</p>
               <p>Qui eligendus eſt, priùs examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitur ab Electoribus prout cautum eſt per Statuta Regni, tum eligatur omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um corum conſenſu; ſi fieri poterit ſin minus per majorem partem, at ſi pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:34510:15"/>fuerint Suffragia per ſeniorem par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem.</p>
               <p>Si autem propter Peſtis ſaevitiam vel aliam ob cauſam Electores abfu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erint ab Urbe, ita ut certus dies ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tui nequeat, tunc licebit Praeſidi quô tempore &amp; loco commodè poterit E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectores convocare.</p>
               <p>Si quis ex numero Electorum Civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem reliquirit &amp; cum familiâ ſuâ in alio aliquo loco ultra ſeptem ab Ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be Milliaria per annum integrum commoratus fuerit, is (niſi ſit Medicus Regius aut aliter Principis Miniſterio detentus) inter Electores locum amit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet, aliuſque per Praeſidem &amp; Electo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res ſurrogabitur: Volumus tamen ut ſuum in Collegio locum &amp; dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatem retineat, ſi intereà temporis Praeſidem de Abſentiae ſuae causâ cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiorem fecerit.</p>
               <p>Dabit ſidem ſe nemini daturum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſum aut ſuffragium ut Praeſes aut Elector creetur niſi ſecundùm formam Statuti &amp; niſi ejus gravitatem, erudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem, mores integros, aetatem de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centem,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:34510:16"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:34510:17"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:34510:18"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:34510:19"/>ſincerum animum in Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gium &amp; Rempublicam &amp; alacritatem ad obeunda Officia cognitam &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectam habuerit.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. II.</hi> De Praſide &amp; ejus Officio.</head>
               <p>QUi Praeſes futurus eſt in annum deſignetur, ſitque è numero Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorum, &amp; quem caeteri Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctores praeſentes, aut omnes aut plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimi pro temporis rei &amp; perſonae rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one idoneum judicaverint idque eò anni tempore fiat, quò jam ante Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutum eſt, cum de Electoribus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geremus poſtridiè nempe Divi Micha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elis ſi commodè fieri poteſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ut ſuprà in Capite de Electoribus creandis.</p>
               <p>Cautum &amp; Statutum eſt ſi paria fuerint Suffragia, ea pars vineat in quà plures ex ſenioribus fuerint, quod ſi hi quo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> pares ſuerint ea praevalebit in quam vetus Praeſes aut eo mortuo
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:34510:20"/>vel abſente Praeſes natus inclinaverit, Praeſidem natum vocamus qui ſenior ex Electoribus fuerit, qui etſi Praeſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis nomen gerat nullam tamen pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatem habeat condendi aut mutandi Statuta, adminiſtrandi vero, fungendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve Praeſidis munere caeteris in rebus ad Collegii negotia pertinentibus, ſit ei plena poteſtas ſecundùm verum ſenſum Statutorum.</p>
               <p>Si Elector aliquis, Praeſidis munns ei delatum recuſaverit, mulctabitur 40 ſolidis niſi fuerit Medicus Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Sponſio ſive Fides à Praeſide data.</head>
                  <p>DAblt fidem fe pro viribus co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturum, ut honor Collegii conſervetur, Statuta ejuſdem ſine fraude obſerventur, omniaque actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum in ſalutem Rei Publicae, &amp; Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtam Collegii utilitatem.</p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:34510:21"/>
                  <p>Fidem a Praeſide novo poſtulabit ſuperioris anni Praeſes ſi adfuerit, aut Conſiliariorum alter, Senior potiſſimum ſi adfuerit, aut his abſentibus Senior ex Electoribus praeſentibus.</p>
                  <p>Qui fidem poſtulabit is porrigat Virtutis Inſignia Pulvinar nempe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noris, Librum, &amp; Caduceum dicat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que, Damus tibi Praeſidis Authorita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem tradimuſque Pulvinar Honoris, Librum Scientiae &amp; Caduceum Gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernationis &amp; Prudentiae ut intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat excellentia tua caeterique Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gae omnes Scientiâ &amp; Prudentiâ Collegium noſtrum firmiter ſtabiliri quamobrem ne id memoriâ tuâ exci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dat in ſolemnioribus Conventibus Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiis funebribus aliiſque temporibus &amp; locis opportunis curabis geſtari ante te per Bedellum, Librum &amp; Cadu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceum in Scientiae &amp; Prudentiae Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num ut quod virtus poſtulat id uſus confirmet.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:34510:22"/>
                  <head>Ratio Deponendi Officium.</head>
                  <p>DEfuncto Praeſidendi Officio, mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus depoſiturus Praeſes finitâ quam velit praefatione dicat. Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no Praeſidendi authoritatem inque tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as manus alterius; viz. Conſiliario<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Senioris potiſſimum aut his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentibus Senioris Electoris praeſentis omnium nomine reſtituo, ut integrum ſit quibus eligendi poteſtas eſt quem velint eligere &amp; ſubſtituere; reddo tibi igitur pulvinar honoris, Librum Scientiae &amp; Caduceum prudentis regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis, praecorque Collegio &amp; vobis omnibus omnia fauſta.</p>
                  <p>Quo facto cui deligata poteſtas eſt proponat eligendum quem ad id Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficium maxime idoneum fore judicave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rint. Eligatur autem eo modo quo ſub initium hujus Capitis ordinatum eſt, &amp; eum qui pro Statutorum ratione Electus eſt clare &amp; nominatim pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuntiet
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:34510:23"/>electum in Praeſidem jubeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ut omnes eum pro Praeſide ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beant, denique fidem ab eo poſtula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit eadem formula qua ſupra dictum eſt.</p>
                  <p>Praeſidis Officium eſto ut Comitia indicat, qua autem ratione poſtea di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cetur cum de Comitiis ſtatuimus, tum ut cauſas Comitiorum proponet, ſingulorum ſententias excipiat, pro ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jori parte diſcernat, factiones &amp; parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um ſtudia excludat.</p>
                  <p>Electores, Conſiliarios, literarum, morum, &amp; medicamentorum Cenſores, cum caeteris, quorum ea res intererit eligat.</p>
                  <p>In Collegis eligendis, aliorum Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fragia primum accipiat, dein ſuum ferat, &amp; pro majori parte deſcernat.</p>
                  <p>Lites inter Collegas dirimat ſed id communi conſilio &amp; ſententia Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorum &amp; Cenſorum ſeorſim adhibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum; eoque modo, quo poſtea in Capite de Conſiliariis dicetur plenius.</p>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:34510:24"/>
                  <p>Curet praeterea, ut Sigillum com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune in Arcâ tutò cuſtodiatur: Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia ipſe obſignabit, in quae reliqui So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cii pro Officio &amp; Statuto conſenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rint.</p>
                  <p>Si qui Libri Collegio donentur, cura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit, ut reponentur, in Bibliothecâ, &amp; exacto anno eorum ratio redda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur novo Praeſidi, oſtendantur<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ei no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minatim ex Indice.</p>
                  <p>Si quis ſit reditus, ſive fructus an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuus ex fundis Collegii, ſi quid do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netur Collegio, ſi quid aliis nomini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus accedat, procuret ut in Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni Arcâ conſervetur cujus ipſe cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vem unam, Conſiliariorum ſinguli itidem unam habeant.</p>
                  <p>Rationem etiam acceptorum &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſorum anni ſuperioris exigat à Theſaurario, caeteriſque Officiariis Collegii, in praeſentia reliquorum E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectorum tunc temporis in Urbe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentium, quos omnes admoneri vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumus, ut putandis rationibus prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtò ſint, ſi modo commodè poterint;
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:34510:25"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:34510:26"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:34510:27"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:34510:28"/>Imprimis autem videat, ut Statuta diligenter obſerventur, &amp; in Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio legantur, vel ab ipſo, vel à Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtario, vel ab alio aliquo prout illi videbitur, eo nimirum modo, quò poſteà in Statutis proviſum &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutum eſt.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. III.</hi> De Pro-Praeſide.</head>
               <p>LIcebit Praeſidi, vel Miniſterio Pincipis, vel magnatis alicujus curâ detento, vel multitudine alio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum negotiorum oppreſſo, Pro-Praeſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem eligere, &amp; ſibi ſubſtituere; is vero Praeſes natus ſit, ſi commode per aetatem, negotia, aut valetudinem fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eri poteſt; ſin minus ex Electoribus aliquis, qui gravitate, recto judicio, experientiâ, diligentiâ, &amp; agendi ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critate polleat, pro Praeſidis volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te &amp; arbitrio.</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:34510:29"/>
               <p>Hujus Officjum erit, ſupplere lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum Praeſidis abſentis in omnibus Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legii negotiis gerendis, &amp; admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrandis, quae commodè per Praeſidem obiri nequeant.</p>
               <p>Sit ei Locus, &amp; Dignitas pro gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>du &amp; ſenioritate, niſi cum Praeſes ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuerit; tum enim Praeſidis locum oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupabit, ſed in Collegio tantùm, loco nimirum Comitiorum ordinario; ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſe autem Praeſidem intelligimus, non modò ſi extra Urbem, &amp; Subur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bia fuerit, ſed etiam, ſi morbo ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quo, aut gravioribus negotiis in Ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be detentus adeſſe nequeat. Sed in his caſibus, volumus, ut abſentiam ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, vel per literas propriâ manu ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptas, vel per Collegii Bedellum notum faciat.</p>
               <p>Duret Officium pro negotio. Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit fidem ſi Electores aequum judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verint, ſe pro virili curaturum ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotia Collegii ſibi commiſſa, &amp; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulò acturum omnia in honorem &amp; u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilitatem Collegii, nihilque facturum, niſi judicio &amp; conſilio Praeſidis, aut
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:34510:30"/>conſiliariorum, eorumque Sociorum, quorum per Statuta intererit.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. IV.</hi> De Conſiliariis.</head>
               <p>POſtridie Divi Michaelis ſi com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modè fieri poteſt, &amp;c. ut ſuprà in Capite de Electoribus creandis, in Comitiis ordinariis, ſtatim à Praeſidis Electione iidem Electores ex ſuo or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine duos qui ad Officium hoc ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nei fuerint in Conſiliarios eligant, aſſentientibus, vel omnibus vel ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jori Electorum Preſentium numero; ſi paria fuerint ſuffragia, ea pars prevalebit, in qua plures fuerint ex Senioribus; ſi hi quoque numero pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res fuerint, tum ea, in quam Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes propenderit.</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:34510:31"/>
               <p>Dabunt fidem ſe probè, &amp; aequè, ut viros bonos decet, ſe poſito om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni affectu, officio ſuo functuros.</p>
               <p>Horum officium eſto, Praeſidi ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in Comitiis majoribus adeſſe; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>undem operâ, &amp; conſilio ubi opus fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erit, juvare, nunquam abeſſe, niſi gravis aliqua cauſa cogat; &amp; ne tunc temporis locus vacet, qui abfuerit ſubſtituet loco ſuo alium Electorem, donec redierit cum conſenſu tamen Praeſidis, aut eo abſente, Pro-Praeſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis.</p>
               <p>Si quae lis aut controverſia de re ambiguâ, aut genuinâ interpretatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne alicujus Statuti, aut hujuſmodi a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquod diſſidium, inter Collegas ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atur, totum id negotium volumus quietè placidèque componi per Praeſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem, Conſiliarios, Cenſores, aut per majorem eorum partem.</p>
               <p>Similiter, ſi inter Praeſidem, &amp; Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legas, controverſia aliqua orta fuerit, rem totam decerni volumus per Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiliarios, &amp; Cenſores, vel per majo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:34510:32"/>illorum partem. At ſi ne ſic quidem componi poteſt, tunc volu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus illis arbitris praedictis, reliquos e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam Electores adjungi; ut horum om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium, vel majoris partis ſuffragiis, tota illa controverſia dirimatur.</p>
               <p>Atque hanc regulam obſervari vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumus, in omnibus Collegarum rixa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionibus decentèr compeſcendis. Hâc nempe ratione futurum ſperamus (quod maximè optandum eſt) ut rix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſa jurgia, ac contentiones evitentur: &amp; fraternus amor, cum ſuavianimorum &amp; voluntatum conſenſu quotidie coa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aleſcat, ac in perpetuum confirmetut.</p>
               <p>Si Conſiliariorum alter aut moria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, aut aliter defecerit antequam annum expleverit, alius intra dies quindecim ſurrogetur.</p>
               <p>Nemo recuſet Officium Conſiliarii ſub poena quadraginta ſolidorum, ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi ſit Medicus Regius.</p>
               <p>Quoties corum conſilium Praeſes rogaverit, paratos ſe praeſtent; ſin minus ſolvant ſinguli tres ſolidos &amp; quatuor denarios, niſi urgens aliqua
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:34510:33"/>cauſa impedierit de qua, cùm proxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mè redierint, Praeſidem certiorem ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. V.</hi> De Cenſoribus.</head>
               <p>POſt Electum Praeſidem, &amp; Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiliarios, mox in iiſdem Comitiis, ſtatuimus &amp; ordinamus ut ſingulis an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis quatuor Viri docti &amp; graves eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantur: ſive ii Electores fuerint, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve Socii: Quos Cenſores Collegii Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinenſis, ſive Gubernatores nominari volumus.</p>
               <p>Horum Electio ſit per Suffragia Praeſidis &amp; totius Societatis aut ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joris partis occultè accepta.</p>
               <p>Horum Officium eſto, de omnibus Medicinam exercentibus cognoſcere, ſive noſtrates fuerint, ſive advenae; per Urbem Suburbia, &amp; intra ſeptem milliaria in ambitu eorundem. Eos examinare, corrigere, gubernare, &amp;
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:34510:34"/>lite (ſi opus ſit) una cum Praeſide &amp; Theſaurario, perſequi: eorum me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendi rationes inquirere, medica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta judicio perſtringere, Pharma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copolarum Officinas ſcrutari, de Phar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macis judicare, vitioſa comburere, aut alio pacto deſtruere: ſi Pharma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copolae obſtiterint, ad Praeſidem &amp; Collegium rem referre: omniaque haec in ſalutem Reipublicae &amp; Collegii honorem agere.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Cenſorum Juramentum.</head>
                  <p>JUrabunt coram Praeſide, Se nemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem in Collegium admittendum decreturos, niſi quem omni ſepoſitô aflectu, judicaverint &amp; literis &amp; mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus idoneum: Nec prece, nec pretio, vel gratiâ, aut quemquam hominem, aut quidquam Medicamentorum ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probaturos; inque caeteris ſuo Officio probè functuros: ſicut eos Deus ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juvet, &amp; ſancta Dei Evangelia.</p>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:34510:35"/>
                  <p>Nullus Socius recuſet Officium Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoris, ſub poenâ quadraginta ſolido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, niſi ſit Medicus Regius.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. VI.</hi> De Comitiorum ratione atque tempore &amp; de Caduceatore ſive Bedello.</head>
               <p>TRiduò antequam futura ſunt Conmitia ſolennia, aut pridie ejus diei, ſi res urgeat; auctoritate Praeſidis monendi ſunt omnes Collegae per Bedellum, aut Praeſidis miniſtrum, ut interſint Comitiis futuris die, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>râ, &amp; locô praeſcriptis.</p>
               <p>Quo ubi ventum eſt, ſedeant ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guli eô ordine quô poſtea dicetur. Comitia vocamus, conventus; ſive ut Rex Henricus in ſuo Diplomate nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:34510:36"/>congregationes Collegarum; &amp; ea Comitia ſolennia, ſive majora le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitima judicamus, quibus ut inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſint, omnes Collegae, in Urbe per Bedellum admonentur: &amp; in quibus duodecim Socii, ad minimùm, adſunt praeter Praeſidem. Modus autem ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitionis talis eſto, Dominus Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes orat Excellentiam veſtram (Doctor eximie) ut Comitiis interſis, menſe, die horâ &amp; loco à Praeſide praeſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis. Subſcribat dein ad hunc modum <hi>A. V. B.</hi> i. e. authoritate veſtrâ Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dellus.</p>
               <p>Sit Bedellus vir probus, detque fidem, ſe fidelitèr &amp; ſedulò inſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turum Praeſidi &amp; Collegio, in omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Collegii negotiis, ſine fuco aut fraude. Promittat inſuper, ſe nec pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiô, nec prece, nec gratiâ, ſecreta Collegii cuiquam vulgaturum.</p>
               <p>Hujus Officium eſto, Schedulas ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitionis ſcribere; Collegas omnes ad Comitia accerſcere in eorum ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventum
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:34510:37"/>omnia parare, munda, polita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que conſervare, à Comitiis non abeſſe: res in Collegii uſum à Praeſide accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas fideliter ferre, &amp; referre; quoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque ſive Medicos; ſive Empiricos, &amp; Impoſtores indagare, eorumque nomina Praeſidi &amp; Cenſoribus indica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re: atque illis, jubente Praeſide aut Cenſoribus, diem indicere; improba Pharmaca comburere, aut aliter de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruere, Convivils, &amp; Funeribus ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſe, Virtutis Inſignia geſtare, &amp; cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tera peragere, quae miniſtro ex Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio incumbunt.</p>
               <p>Bedello ſtipendium duodecim li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brarum à Theſaurario annuatim ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetur.</p>
               <p>Volumus etiam, ut à ſingulis Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didatis &amp; Permiſſis quatuor ſolidi quotannis pro mercede ipſi erogen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur; in omnibus praeterea admiſſioni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, &amp; mulctis quae viginti ſolidos excedunt; &amp; Anatomiis, tres ſolidi &amp; quatuor denarii illi perſolventur.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:34510:38"/>
                  <head>De Collegis admonendis ad Comitia.</head>
                  <p>STatuimus, ut Collegae omnes, qui in Urbe, aut Suburbiis fuerint, ſingulis Comitiis majoribus, ſive or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinariis, ſive extraordinariis interſint; niſi grave aliquod impedimentum ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiterit. Quod ad minores illas Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregationes attinet, quae ſingulis men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibus, aliiſque temporibus habentur; liberum erit caeteris Collegis (praeter ſex illos, quos poſtea in Cap. de Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poribus ordinariis Comitiorum, nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabimus) vel adeſſe, vel abeſſe, pro arbitrio; niſi Praeſidis aut Pro-Praeſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis monitu adeſſe jubeantur.</p>
                  <p>Quod ſi quis praemonitus per Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dellum ipſum, vel per Schedulam ab eô domi ſuae relictam non acceſſerit; ſolvet in uſus Collegii duos ſolidos niſi per valetudinem excuſatus fuerit, aut abſuerit ab Urbe duobus ad mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mùm miliaribus.</p>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:34510:39"/>
                  <p>Qui abfuerit à Comitiis eô die quô Praeſes &amp; Cenſores eligendi ſunt, niſi gravem ob cauſam à Praeſide, aut Pro-Praeſide, aut Conſiliariis, &amp; Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoribus approbandam, ſolvet in uſum Collegii tres ſolidos &amp; quatuor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narios. Imò ſolidum ſolvet, qui ante Auditam tertiam non acceſſerit.</p>
                  <p>Quoniam autem complures legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mè à Praeſide per Bedellum admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti, Comitiis praedictis intereſſe vel negligunt, vel aſpernantur; quo fit ut ſaepe irriti fiant Conventus; reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quique Socii, Praeſidis monitis obtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perantes, fruſtra negotia ſua privata negligunt; propterea ſtatuimus &amp; or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinamus, ut, ſi qùis Socius praedicto modô admonitus, ad ſtata Comitia majora accedere recuſaverit, quater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que hoc pacto continuò deliquerit, nec interea temporis abſentiae ſuae cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam Praeſidi aut Pro-Praeſidi cum Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiliariis &amp; Cenſoribus approbandam reddiderit; alius (quam primum) commodum videbitur Collegio) in ejuſdem locum ſufficiatur.</p>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:34510:40"/>
                  <p>Omnia Statuta in tres partes ſive ſectiones dividantur; prima pars ea omnia comprehendet, quae pertin ent ad Electores, ad Praeſidem, &amp; Pro-Praeſidem, ad Conſiliarios, ad Cenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, ad Comitia, aliaque donec ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ſit ad Caput Nonum, quod tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctat de Officio Theſaurarii.</p>
                  <p>Secunda pars complectetur ea Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuta, quae pertinent ad Theſaurarium, &amp; Regiſtrarium, ad numerum Socio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum &amp; Candidatorum, ad eorundem Examinationes, Electiones, &amp; Admiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiones ad Permiſſorum Ordinem, &amp; Officia; &amp; reliqua, uſque ad Caput Viceſſimum ſecundum quod agit de Statutis Poenalibus ſive Moralibus.</p>
                  <p>Tertia pars continebit Statuta Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalia ſive Moralia, atque ſecundum hanc triplicem Statutorum partitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem perlegantur in Comitiis majori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus omnibus praeterquam die Comi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiorum
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:34510:41"/>divi Michaelis, quo tempore E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectiones Officiariorum inſtituuntur.</p>
                  <p>Lectioni Statutorum interſint Socii, Candidati, &amp; Permiſſi, quotquot ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſe poterunt.</p>
                  <p>Atque haec noſtra Statuta ad praedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum modum perlegentur, vel ab ipſo Praeſideaut Pro-Praeſide (ſi ipſis placue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit) vel à Regiſtrario, ſi adfuerit. At ſi fortè Regiſtrarius, ſive negotiis di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrictus, ſive morbo detentus, ſive aliâ aliquâ gravi causâ impeditus, non adſuerit; tunc pro arbitrio Praeſidis, aut Pro-Praeſidis, alius aliquis è So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciis pro illo tempore deſignetur, qui illam Statutorum partem perlegat.</p>
                  <p>Cautum tamen interea volumus, atque proviſum; ut, ſi graviora quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam negotia illis Comitiis pertractan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da fuerint, Liberum ſit Praeſidi aut Pro-Praeſidi, pro arbitrio hanc Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutorum lectionem, pro tempore, vel penitus omittere, vel ejus partem dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taxat aliquam legere, aut legendam praecipere.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:34510:42"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. VII.</hi> De Temporibus Ordinariis &amp; Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinariis Comitiorum &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquis ad Comitiorum rationem pertinentibus.</head>
               <p>ORdinata ſive Stata Comitia ad quatuor anni Tempora aeque diſtantia celebrenter.</p>
               <p>Prima poſtridiè Divi Michaelis ſi commodè fieri poteſt, &amp;c. ut ſupra dictum eſt.</p>
               <p>Secunda poſtridiè Divi Thomae, ſi commodè, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Tertia poſtridiè Dominicae Palma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſi commodè, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Quarta poſtridiè Nativitatis Divi Johannis Baptiſtae ſi commodè, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Atque haec omnia ſunt ordinaria ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve ſtata Comitia, quae etiam ſolennia &amp; majora licebit appellare.</p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:34510:43"/>
               <p>Ac praeter ſtata iſta ſive ordinaria licebit etiam Praeſidi, alia quoque ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lennia ſive majora Comitia extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naria convocare pro neceſſitate aut dignitate incidentis rei.</p>
               <p>Atque in omnibus iſtis ſolennibus Comitiis, volumus ut duodecim ad minimum Socii adſint praeter Praeſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem aut Pro-Praeſidem.</p>
               <p>At ſi urgens aliqua neceſſitas, ut ſaevitia Peſtis, &amp;c. aut grave aliquod negotium per principis mandatum ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediendum inciderit; idque eo fortè tempore, quo tot Socii in Civitate non adfuerint tunc quidem neceſſitati parendum eſt, talique caſu res tota relinquenda eſt Praeſidis aut Pro-Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidis prudentiae &amp; judicio, ut quot fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erint in Urbe, eos omnes per Bedel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum admonendos curet, ut interſint Comitiis atque in iſtis majoribus Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiis, volumus ut ordinariae fiant E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectiones &amp; Admiſſiones novorum So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciorum, Candidatorum, &amp; Permiſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:34510:44"/>
               <p>Quod verò ad Sociorum, Candidato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, &amp; Permiſſorum, Examinationes attinet eae rectè peragi poſſunt, ſive in majoribus iſtis Comitiis, ſive etiam in aliis minoribus Conventionibus pro Praeſidis aut Pro-Praeſidis arbitrio.</p>
               <p>In omnibus Comitiis, Praeſes, aut Pro-Praeſes, Conventûs cauſam expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat; quid ſinguli ordine dicant ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectet, accipiatque Suffragia: nec quiſquam diſcedat niſi impetratâ pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us veniâ, antequam Praeſes, aut Pro-Praeſes Comitia diſertis hiſce verbis diſſolverit, Solvimus haec Comitia.</p>
               <p>Sunt enim alia Comitia, quae mino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra dicuntur, qualia ſingulis Menſibus, aliiſque temporibus, pro ratione re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum &amp; perſonarum habentur; prout occaſio aliqua ſubitanea poſtulaverit.</p>
               <p>In his, admittendi in Collegium, examinantur; res item Agyrtarum &amp; Impoſtorum omniumque Medicinam malè factitantium, à Praeſide &amp; Cenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus executiuntur, ipſique pro me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rito
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:34510:45"/>puniuntur; aliaque id genus ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotia tractantur.</p>
               <p>In minoribus iſtis Comitiis non re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirimus, ut tot adſint Socii, quot in majoribus &amp; ſolennibus requirun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur; ſuffecerit, ſi in his Dominus Praeſes, quatuor Cenſores, &amp; Regiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius adfuerint.</p>
               <p>Neceſſe autem eſt, ut omnes Cenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res interſint, ſecundum Statuta Regni, modò legitimè admoniti fuerint per Bedellum; quare ne reliqui fruſtra conveniant, abſentem Cenſorem de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem ſolidis mulctandum ſtatuimus; ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi Praeſidem antea de abſentiae ſuae cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sâ certiorem fecerit.</p>
               <p>Summâ in omnibus Comitiis agen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum eſt modeſtiâ ſummâ gravitate, ne qua lis aut convitium oriatur; tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe certè jurgium in privatis congreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, ſed turpiſſimum in publicis: praeſertim inter eos, qui ex bonis di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciplinis honeſtos mores hauſiſſe judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantur.</p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:34510:46"/>
               <p>Proinde nemo proponat aut dicat a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquid publicè in Collegio, niſi Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te aperto, veniâque priús à Praeſide impetratâ: ad quem ſolum Oratio di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigenda eſt.</p>
               <p>Quòd ſi plures ſimul loqui incep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, cedat Junior ſeniori Unuſquiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que breviter, &amp; graviter, ſine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lixâ dicacitate loquatur; &amp; Praeſidis monitu ſileat.</p>
               <p>Neminique liceat loquentem intur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bare, niſi Praeſidi aut Pro-Praeſidi, aut praeſentium Cenſorum ſeniori cujus e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim munus eſto, quemlibet ſui officii admonere.</p>
               <p>Unuſquiſque autem ad rem propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitum ſemel tantùm ſuoque ordine, ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiam dicat; niſi iterum impetratâ à Praeſide veniâ.</p>
               <p>Reliqui Socii attenti ſint, nec pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatis confabulationibus ſuſurris, ſtre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pituve, loquentem, vel auditores in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terturbent, &amp; ſemper ad Praeſidis nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum fiat ſilentium: qui contra fecerit
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:34510:47"/>duobus ſolidis ſtatim ſolvendis ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctetur.</p>
               <p>In rebus dubiis, &amp; magni momen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti, elegantur delegati, pro Praeſidis arbitrio, qui rem undiquaque diſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiant, referantque ad Collegium ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulis Comitiis, poſtquam Praeſes Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventûs cauſam expoſuerit.</p>
               <p>Regiſtrarius quae noviſſimis acta Comitiis clarâ voce recenſeat (ut expunctis ſi quae fuerint emendanda) demum inſcribantur Libro Annalium.</p>
               <p>Suffragia colligenda nemo propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat, niſi Praeſes aut Pro-Praeſes.</p>
               <p>In omnibus Electionibus tacitè &amp; occultè, per piſa aut fabas ferantur Suffragia, in aliis Collegii negotiis, prout viſum fuerit Praeſidi aut Pro-Praeſidi.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:34510:48"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. VIII.</hi> De Statutis Condendis &amp; Abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gandis, &amp; de Mulctis Irro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gandis.</head>
               <p>STatuta pauca ſanciantur, eaque vel Fide datâ vel Mulctâ confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentur.</p>
               <p>Sit Mulcta levis, ſed inevitabilis; minima Mulcta ſit 12 denariorum.</p>
               <p>Ad Statutum aliquod Condendum ſufficient Comitia duo, ſed ad Abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gandum non niſi tria.</p>
               <p>Statuimus &amp; ordinamus ut omnes Mulctae, quae à Praeſide aut Pro-Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, &amp; quatuor Cenſoribus; vel à majore parte Sociorum, quomodocun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que infliguntur, cedant duntaxat in u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum Collegii, non autem in ullius privati emolumentum; exceptis ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men illis pecuniarum ſolutionibus quae per Statuta Collegii Officiariis aliter
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:34510:49"/>conceduntur. Volumuſque ut hae Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctae illico ſolvantur, aut ſaltem datâ hypothecâ, qualem Praeſes expetierit, ſibi caveat de praeſenti paecunia.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. IX.</hi> De Officio Theſaurarii.</head>
               <p>COllegii redditus &amp; Emolumenta quae Annuatim accreſcunt Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio, recipiet, &amp; in cuſtodiâ ſuâ tutò conſervabit, in uſum Collegii.</p>
               <p>Collegii Utenſilia, aliaque neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria, quoties opus fuerit, procurabit.</p>
               <p>Ejuſdemque Bona, Libros, Suppel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectilem, caeteraquae Ornamenta ad de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus illius pertinentia, quantum potue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, tutò &amp; decenter conſervabit.</p>
               <p>Si quid reparandum fuerit in Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gii Ediſiciis, curabit ut id tempeſtivè fiat.</p>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:34510:50"/>
               <p>Lites Collegii &amp; Cauſas Juridicas ipſe unâ cum Praeſide &amp; Cenſoribus proſequetur.</p>
               <p>Collegii Officiariis, ſua cuique Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laria ſive Stipendia, ex Statutis debita, quatuor uſitatis Anni temporibus per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolvet.</p>
               <p>Computi rationem bis quotannis Praeſidi &amp; Electoribus reddet, modò ad hoc poſtulatus &amp; praemonitus fuerit.</p>
               <p>Intra menſem poſt feſtum Divi Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaelis, perfectum computi rationem, pro integro elapſo anno reddet; eo nempe die, quem Praeſes ille aſſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verit.</p>
               <p>Totamque pecuniae ſummam quae tunc temporis ſupererit, caeteraque Collegii Bona, Suppellectilem, Uten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilia, quae in ipſius cuſtodia fuerint, Praeſidi &amp; Electoribus reſtituet.</p>
               <p>Syngraphâ Praeſidi &amp; Societati ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligabitur, eodem die quo admittitur ad Officium, ut Stipendia Collegii Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiariis debita, intra ſeptimanam, poſt plenam computi ſui rationem pro
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:34510:51"/>illo anno redditam, fideliter ſolvat.</p>
               <p>In reparandis Collegii Aedificiis, rebuſque neceſſariis in uſum Collegii coemendis, non impendet ultra qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draginta ſolidos, ſine Praeſidis aut Pro-Praeſidis voluntate, &amp; conſenſu.</p>
               <p>Theſaurario pro Stipendio ſolven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur annuatim ex Collegii redditibus quadraginta ſolidi.</p>
               <p>Statuimus praeterea &amp; ordinamus, ut à ſingulis in Collegii Societatem admiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis, itemque à ſingulis, qui vel in Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didatorum ordinem, vel in permiſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum numerum admittentur, accipiat ſex ſolidos &amp; octo denarios, tempore admiſſionis illorum.</p>
               <p>Dabit Fidem ſe perfuncturum Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio ſuo fideliter ſecundum Statuta, omniaque acturum in honorem &amp; u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilitatem Collegii; &amp; computi ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem fideliter redditurum monitu Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidis.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:34510:52"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. X.</hi> De Regiſtrario.</head>
               <p>OFficium Regiſtrarii hujuſmodi e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſto, ſingulis Collegii Comitiis, ſive majoribus ſive minoribus, legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mè &amp; tempeſtivè admonitus per Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legii Bedellum ſive Praeſidis aut Pro-Praeſidis miniſtrum, ipſemet coram ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit, ſub poenâ decem Solidorum.</p>
               <p>Quicquid ibi actum, ratum, &amp; ſancitum fuerit, conſentientibus Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, &amp; Sociorum praeſentium majori parte (niſi ſit res levioris momenti, &amp; notatu indigna) id omne fideliter adnotet &amp; initio Comitiorum prox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imè ſequentium perlegat, ac poſtea (correctis ſi quae emendanda fuerint) in Librum Annalium Collegii referat.</p>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:34510:53"/>
               <p>Sin autem per valetudinem, aut graviora negotia impeditus fuerit, quò minus adeſſe poſſit; tunc ei lice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit, Socium aliquem pro tempore ſubſtituere, qui &amp; abſentia ejus cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam Praeſidi ſignificet, &amp; locum ipſius diligenter ſuppleat.</p>
               <p>Formulas Literarum ad Collegium vel à Collegio ſcriptarum; &amp; reliqua omnia acta, Libro Annalium inſerat.</p>
               <p>Pro Annuo Stipendio, Regiſtrario quotannis ſolventur ex Collegii reddi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus, Quadraginti ſolidi, eidem per aequales partes, quatuor uſitatis hujus Regni terminis, à Theſaurario annu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merandi.</p>
               <p>A ſingulis, qui vel ad praxin in Medicinâ permittuntur, vel in Candi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datorum Ordinem adſciſcuntur, vel in Sociorum numerum admittuntur; ipſo vel Permiſſionis vel Admiſſionis tempore Regiſtrario ſolventur Sex So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidi &amp; octo denarii, &amp; Quinque inſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Solidi pro illorum Nominum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptione in Librum Annalium.</p>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:34510:54"/>
               <p>Quotieſcunque contigerit, aliquem ex Sententiâ Praeſidis aut Pro-Praeſidis, &amp; Cenſorum, mulctari aliquâ pecuniae ſummâ notabili Collegio perſolvendâ, à ſingulis ita punitis, Tres Solidi &amp; qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuor denarii Regiſtrario ſolventur.</p>
               <p>Si quis, aliquâ pecuniae ſummâ in u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum Collegii ſolvendâ mulctatus, non ſimul &amp; ſemel totum mulctam ſolverit, ſed ſolutionem imperatam, ad dies ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quot diſtulerit, adeòque eam partitim ſolverit; ſingulis iſtis ſolutionibus ſic diviſim factis, Tres Solidi &amp; quatuor denarii Regiſtrario perſolventur; quippe Officium ejus moleſtum onus judicamus.</p>
               <p>Dabit Fidem ſe Officio ſuo debitè perfuncturum, ſecundum Statuta, in honorem &amp; utilitatem Collegii omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aque fideliter Libro Annalium quae fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erint acta, vel in majoribus, vel mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noribus Comitiis ſine fraude inſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:34510:55"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. XI.</hi> De Candidatis.</head>
               <p>STatuimus &amp; ordinamus, Ut nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merus Candidatorum non excedat Duodecim: Volumuſque ut nemo ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittatur in illorum Ordinem, qui non ſit in Medicinâ Doctor, &amp; Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione Britannus, &amp; Medicinam exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuerit per quadriennium.</p>
               <p>Quod ſi Doctoratûs gradum in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terâ aliquâ Academiâ adeptus fuerit; Volumus, Ut antequam admittatur ad examen, Diploma, ſive Literas Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimoniales veras &amp; authenticas illius Academiae proferat, &amp; oſtendat Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legio; &amp; praeterea, ab alterutra no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrarum Academiarum incorporatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis ſuae teſtimonium habeat, &amp; ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducat.</p>
               <p>Volumus praeterea &amp; ordinamus, Ut ſinguli Candidati &amp; Permiſſi an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tequam
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:34510:56"/>admittantur, omnes Collegii So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cios bis, gratiae impetrandae ergo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniant; nimirùm primò ante exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nationem ullam, ſecundò autem finitô examinationum curriculô.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Fides a Candidatis poſtulata.</head>
                  <p>DAbis Fidem, te obſervaturum Statuta Collegii; &amp; pro viribus conaturum, ut honos ejus ſartus te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus conſervetur, nec unquam conſili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um aut familiaritatem inibis cum ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quo qui ſtudet verbô vel factô Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legii ſtatum labefactare; ſed in om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus quae ad honorem &amp; utilitatem Collegii ſpectant, conſiliô, ope, &amp; auxiliô juvabis.</p>
                  <p>Dabis etiam Fidem, te in omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus licitis &amp; honeſtis morigerum fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turum Domino Praeſidi aut Pro-Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidi, &amp; Electoribus, Seniori in Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legio (ſecundum Statuta) locum ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, eundemque honore debito pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequeris.</p>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:34510:57"/>
                  <p>Accedes ad Collegium, ex man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dato Domini Praeſidis aut Pro-Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidis, vel Cenſorum; quoties fueris per Bedellum admonitus &amp; accerſitus.</p>
                  <p>Intereris fingulis Anatomiis, niſi gravi detinearis impedimento, appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bando à Praeſide &amp; Cenſoribus.</p>
                  <p>Nec prece, nec pretio, neque ullâ aliâ causâ, medicamenta quae abortum faciunt, vel venena cujuſvis generis, in pernitiem, aut malum uſum dabis; nec ea quempiam docebis, quem ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicaris velle illis abuti.</p>
                  <p>Neminem qui admiſſus eſt in Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legium, vel ignorantiae, vel maleficii nomine accuſabis, aut publicè contu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meliis afficies.</p>
                  <p>Perſequeris omnibus modis hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtis, indoctos, Empericos, &amp; Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtores, eorumque nomina ad Praeſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem aut Cenſores referes; nec te Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piricis, aliiſque per Collegium non li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiatis familiarem reddes; neque eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Conventiones ad Collegii detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:34510:58"/>vel infamum ullo modo fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentabis.</p>
                  <p>Secreta Collegii nemini extra Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legium divulgabis.</p>
                  <p>Dabis fidem, te neque Literis à Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natibus, nec pretio, nec ullô alio mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do illicitô, Collegii Societatem, am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bire; omniaque in arte Medicâ pro vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus facturum, ad honorem Collegii &amp; Reipublicae utilitatem.</p>
                  <p>Statuimus &amp; ordinamus, Ut Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſi ſive Licentiati, itemque Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didati, Statuta &amp; Decreta noſtra dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genter obſervent, Praeſidi, Electori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, &amp; Cenſoribus morem gerant; Mulctaque, ab iis, ob delicta inflictos promptè, perſolvant.</p>
                  <p>Praeterea non recuſabunt, Medica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta illa ſua, quae Secreta ſive Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cana appellant, ſolentque in ſuâ praxi uſurpare planè &amp; nudè exponere, quoties à Praeſide &amp; Cenſoribus ad id faciendum requiruntur; qui per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinaciter
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:34510:59"/>contrà fecerit, pro arbitrio Praeſidis &amp; Cenſorum poenas lucet.</p>
                  <p>Unuſquiſque Candidatus ſolvet tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore admiſſionis ſuae quatuor libras in uſum Collegii, &amp; decem ſolidos in proprios uſus Praeſidis, Theſaurario verò ſex ſolidos &amp; octo denarios; i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temque Regiſtrario, pro debito Sala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio, ſex ſolidos &amp; octo denarios, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demque inſuper quinque alios ſolidos, pro inſertione Nominis in Librum An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalium; praeterea Bedello Collegii tres ſolidos &amp; quatuor denarios.</p>
                  <p>Quoniam multi huc confluunt quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidiè ad exercendam praxin, è quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum numero complures ſunt, qui an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te debitum tempus ex Academiis ſuis emigrantes, ad tranſmarinas oras voli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, ut in exteris regionibus brevio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri ſpatio, &amp; minori impendio ad Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoratûs gradum perreptent, quam domi in Academiis noſtris aſſequi po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terant.</p>
                  <p>Idcirco ſtatuimus, Ut quicunque vel in Collegii Societatem, vel in Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didatorum
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:34510:60"/>Ordinem, vel in Permiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorum numerum admittetur, ſi Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoratûs gradum apud exteros ſuſcepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: Is admiſſionis tempore, duplo plus ſolvat Collegio, Praeſidi, The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaurario, Regiſtrario, aliiſque Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gii Officiariis, quàm illi ſolvere ſolent, qui in noſtris Academiis Doctores cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antur. Item, quicunque Doctor cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atus fuerit in noſtris Academiis, ſi ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men teſtinantiùs ad gradum illum ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volando, quàm par eſt tempus illi dignitati debitum anticipaverit, id eſt, ſi Doctor fiat prius, quam vel in arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus integros ſeptem annos rexerit, vel tam diu Baccalaures in Medicinâ praeextiterit; is duplo plus ſolvet Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legio, Praeſidi, caeteriſque praedictis Collegii Officiariis, quàm illi ſolent, qui ſecundùm laudabiles leges &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuetudines noſtrarum Academiarum, tempore praefinito, &amp; maturiori cum judicio, ad Doctoratûs gradum aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derunt.</p>
                  <p>Volumus, Ut omnes Candidati, &amp; Permiſſi, à Bedello admoniti, ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:34510:61"/>noſtris Comitiis interſint; ut ſi quos cognoverint illicitè &amp; inſcienter prax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in exercentes, eorum nomina Praefidi, &amp; Cenſoribus ſignificent; tum etiam ut Statutorum praelectionem audiant.</p>
                  <p>Solvant etiam, ſi occaſio fuerit, &amp; neceſſitas Collegii poſtulet, ut Socii; modo ad id requirantur.</p>
                  <p>Exactô anno, Candidati Praeſidem ejus rei moneant, rogentque ut in So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciorum numerum adſciſcantur, ſi modò id commodè fieri poteſt, ſalvis Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gii Statutis.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. XII.</hi> De Sociis.</head>
               <p>STatuimus &amp; ordinamus, Ut nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus Sociorum, non excedat trigin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta; volumuſque ultra hunc certum &amp; determinatum numerum Regis, Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae, &amp; Principis Medicos ordinarios
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:34510:62"/>tanquam Medicos Honorarios Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerari &amp; admitti.</p>
               <p>Volumus praeterea, Ut nemo ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittatur in Collegii Societatem, qui non priùs fuit per annum integrum de Candidatorum numero, aut publicè in aliquâ Britanniae Academiâ Medicinam per triennium perlegerit, aut Doctor Cathedrae, ut aiunt, in aliquâ hujus regni Academiâ prae-extiterit, aut Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius Medicus fuerit ordinarius.</p>
               <p>Singuli Socii tempore admiſſionis ſuae ſolvent Collegio, Praeſidi, The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaurario, Regiſtrario, &amp; Bedello, prout de Candidatis antea Statutum eſt; omnes item ſolutiones duplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunt, conditionibus iis, quae ſupra dictae ſunt.</p>
               <p>Statuimus etiam, Ut omnes Socii tempore admiſſionis, Literas habeant Patentes Sigillo Collegii munitas; &amp; hâc datâ fide obſtringantur.</p>
               <p>ADnitêris pro viribus, ut Status Collegii perpetuetur, Statuta
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:34510:63"/>Collegii obſervabis, Parebis Praeſidi in iis quae ad honorem &amp; perpetuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem Collegii ſpectant.</p>
               <p>Non dabis quae abortum faciant, aut conceptum adimant, vel impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant, nec venena in malum finem; imò verò ea ne docebis quidèm ubi aliqua doli mali ſuſpitio eſt.</p>
               <p>Neminem decernes in Collegium co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>optandum, niſi quem ſepoſito omni affectu, judicaveris ſcientiâ &amp; moribus idoneum.</p>
               <p>Leges diligenter intra annum, quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que primos Libros Galeni, de ſimplici Medicinâ, &amp; omnes de uſu partium.</p>
               <p>Perſequêris omnibus modis honeſtis, indoctos, Empericos &amp; Impoſtores, eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rumque nomina Praeſidi, aut Pro-Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidi, vel Cenſoribus deferes.</p>
               <p>Dabis etiam fidem te Medicinam ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercuiſſe per quadriennium, aut legiſſe publicè in aliquâ Academiâ.</p>
               <p>Item dabis fidem, te Statutum de publicâ corporis humani diffectione,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:34510:64"/>ſummâ diligentiâ, quandocunque à Praeſide aut Pro-Praeſide, admonitus fueris obſervaturum.</p>
               <p>Dices denique verè &amp; bonâ fide, quaenam ſit patria tua.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Literae Admiſſionis.</head>
                  <p>SCiant omnes, Nos J. C. Medicinae Doctorem &amp; Praeſidem Collegii Medicorum Londinenſium, unà cum conſenſu Sociorum ejuſdem, authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate nobis à Domino Rege &amp; Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento conceſsâ, examinaſſe, appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſe &amp; in Collegium noſtrum co-op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſſe doctum &amp; probum virum R. M. Cantuarienſem in Florentiſſimâ Acade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miâ (Cantabrigienſi vel Oxonienſi) Medicinae Doctorem; eique conceſſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe Liberam Facultatem &amp; Licentiam exercendi Scientiam &amp; Artem Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam juxta formam Statutorum ad hoc Editorum largitoſque praeterea uſum ac fructum omnium commoditatum Libertatum, ac Privilegiorum, quae
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:34510:65"/>Collegio noſtro authoritate praedictâ &amp; jam conceſſa ſunt, &amp; in futurum concedenda.</p>
                  <p>In cujus rei fidem &amp; teſtimonium Sigillum noſtrum commune praeſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus apponi fecimus. Datum Londi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni, in Collegio noſtro ſeptimo die Maii Anno Domini 1647.</p>
                  <p>* Si Collegarum quiſpiam ſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligioni, aut Sacerdotio mancipaverit, poſtquam in Collegium co-optatus fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erit ne vocetur ad Collegium, ne videamur ad Medicinae uſum revoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re eum, quem Religio &amp; Lex Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtica à Medicinae functione ablega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit.</p>
                  <p>* Neve honeſtum putemus Clerico, inter caetera, tractare res, morboſque muliebres.</p>
                  <p>* Quod ſi Clericorum aut Religio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorum quiſpiam, admitti cupit in Collegium, aut permitti ad praxin, multo minus aſſumatur, propter eaſdem cauſas.</p>
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:34510:66"/>
                  <p>Si Collegarum quiſpiam ſe ſacerdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio addixerit poſtquam in Collegium co-optatus fuerit, nolumus eum denuò vocari ad Collegium.</p>
                  <p>Quod ſi quiſpiam Clericus aut Sacris initiatus, admitti cupit in Collegium, aut permitti ad praxin multò minùs id illi concedetur.</p>
                  <p>Statuimus &amp; ordinamus, Ut ſi quis criminis alicujus gravioris ac publici reus, aut vitio aliquo inſigni infamis fuerit, ablegetur à Collegio; ne ſi re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineremus talem, videremur aut virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem contemnere, aut eodem morbo laborare; ne autem talis Collega non exiſtens, admittatur in Collegium, &amp; aliis Statutis prohibitum eſt, &amp; his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibemus.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:34510:67"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. XIII.</hi> Literae Teſtimoniales Practican<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium per <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſum Angliae Regnum.</head>
               <p>SCiant omnes, Nos <hi>A. B.</hi> Medecinae Doctorem &amp; Praeſidem Collegii Medicorum Londinenſium, una cum conſenſu <hi>E. P. B. H.</hi> &amp; <hi>R. M.</hi> prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicti Collegii Sociorum &amp; Electorum, Authoritate nobis à Domino Rege &amp; Parliamento conceſsâ, examinaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe &amp; approbaſſe 17 die Aug. Anno Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini 1667, probum virum <hi>T. W.</hi> ex Comitatu <hi>B.</hi> in Florentiſſimâ Acade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miâ Oxonienſi vel Cantabrigienſi, Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrum Artium &amp; in Civitate Eboracen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi benè in praxi Medica exercitatum eumque dignum judicamus, qui ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittatur ad praxin Medicinae, juxta formam Statutorum ad hoc editorum;</p>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:34510:68"/>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>in cujus rei teſtimonium Sigillum no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrum Commune appoſuimus, &amp; nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na adſcripſimus. Datum Londini in Collegio noſtro <date>die, &amp; menſe, &amp;c.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
               <argument>
                  <p>Si quis à Praeſide &amp; tribus Electo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus, modo praedicto idoneus ad praxin judicabitur, is Nomen ſuum Regiſtrario indicabit ut in Libro An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalium inſcribatur.</p>
               </argument>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. XIV.</hi> De Coercendis Empiricis.</head>
               <p>CUm magna ſit imperitorum turba qui Rempublicam affligunt, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſque ex Preſcripto Regis &amp; Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menti incumbit ut populi ſaluti &amp; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitati conſulamus; ſtatuimus &amp; or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinamus in commodiorem talium ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpationem, ut quos indoctos &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honeſtos eſſe reipsâ comprobaverimus, non ſolum mulctâ &amp; carcere puniamus,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:34510:69"/>ſed etiam Senatores &amp; Pro-Senatores cujuſlibet Urbis, Provinciae, ſive Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtodiae, ubi tales Impoſtores habitant certiores per literas noſtras faciamus, eos indignos Medicorum nomine cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſendos, proindeque tractandos ut cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teros Cives.</p>
               <p>Forma autem Literarum talis eſto ſed Lingua vernacula.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Forma Literarum ad Senatores.</head>
                  <p>VOs certiores facimus egregii viri <hi>H. M.</hi> veſtrae Provinciae, Empi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricum in vico S. Morantem, eſſe vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum indoctum &amp; imperitum Medicinae, noſtrique nequaquam eſſe Collegii, quamobrem vobis licet pro jure ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtro, eum alioſque omnes qui Literas Teſtimoniales Sigillo noſtro munitas non habent, ad omnibus urbis veſtrae idoneis Officiis fungendum, co-optare &amp; eligere, cogereque caetera agere &amp; praeſtare, quae authoritati veſtrae impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rari conceditur.</p>
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:34510:70"/>
                  <p>Haec in eum finem ſcripſimus, ne ſub Medicinae nomine &amp; praetextu, Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legia fallant, inſubidi iſti plebis Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtores.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Datum è Collegio noſtro, &amp;c.</dateline>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. XV.</hi> De Permiſſis ſive Licentiatis ad Praxin.</head>
               <floatingText xml:lang="lat" type="document">
                  <body>
                     <p>QUoniam complures, in hac Civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate Medicinam faciunt, quos inidoneos omninò cenſemus, ut in numerum Sociorum aut Candidato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum adoptentur, vel quod natione non ſint Britanni, vel Doctoratûs gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum non adepti fuerint, vel non ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis docti, aut aetate &amp; gravitate pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vecti ſint, vel alias conſimiles ob cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſas, &amp; tamen Reipublicae inſervire &amp; ſaluti hominum prodeſſe poſſint, ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem in nonnullis curationibus.</p>
                     <pb n="110" facs="tcp:34510:71"/>
                     <p>De his ordinamus &amp; ſtatuimus, Ut poſt examinationes debitas &amp; approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem Praeſidis &amp; Cenſorum permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantur ad praxin, quamdiu ſe bene geſſerint.</p>
                     <p>Volumus ut omnes qui ſolummodo permittuntur ad praxin, eâdem ſide quâ Candidati obſtringantur.</p>
                     <p>Praeſes igitur tempore admiſſionis his verbis utetur, Ego. <hi>J. C.</hi> Praeſes Collegii Medicorum Londinenſium, authoritate per Leges mihi conceſsâ, permitto te <hi>A. B.</hi> ad praxin Medici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae in Civitate Londini, &amp; per ſeptem circum circa milliaria, quamdiu te be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne geſſeris, Statuta Collegii obſervave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, &amp; folutiones debitas praeſtiteris, ita facienti precor omnia fauſta.</p>
                     <p>Volumus ut permiſſi ſive Licentiati folutiones omnes uſitatas praeſtent Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legio, Praeſidi Theſaurario, Regiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio &amp; Bedello, quas modo Candidatis praeſtandas aſſignavimus.</p>
                     <p>Volumus praeterea, ut primo Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſionis anno ſolvant Collegio ſex li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bras,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:34510:72"/>niſi ob cauſas à Praeſide &amp; Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoribus approbandas mitiùs cum iis age<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re aequum cenſebitur, ſolvent utcun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que quátuor ad minimum libras; fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentibus autem annis quam diu per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſi fuerint ſolvent in uſum Collegii quadraginta ſolidos.</p>
                     <p>Statuimus &amp; ordinamus, Ut nemo ad praxin Medicinae admittatur intra Urbem, Suburbia, ſeptem circum cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca milliaria, niſi prius ter (totidem di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ebus ad id conſtitutis) examinatus fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erit à Praeſide &amp; Cenſoribus, &amp; ab iiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem approbatus; &amp; ad Medicinae praxin permiſſus fuerit.</p>
                     <p>Quod ſi quis intra ſpatium ſive am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitum praedictum facultatem Medicinae exercuerit, nec tamen ſe examinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum Praeſidi &amp; Cenſoribus ultrò obtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerit; is primò admoneatur per Bedel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum idque Praeſidis nomine, ut omninò à Medicinae praxi abſtineat, donec Praeſidis &amp; Collegii approbationem ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuerit, utque ſtato &amp; praefixo tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore ſe coram Praeſide &amp; Cenſoribus
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:34510:73"/>ſiſtat, eorum examinationem atque ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probationem exſpectaturus.</p>
                     <p>Bedellus autem admonitionis Sche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulam vel ipſi, in manus tradat, vel domi illius relinquet, in haec verba;</p>
                     <p>NOs Praeſes &amp; Cenſores, Collegii Medicorum Londinenſium, te admonitum volumus ut 10 die Junii coram nobis in propriâ tuâ perſonâ compareas, idque poſt meridiem inter ſecundam &amp; tertiam horam ejuſdem diei, in Aedibus Collegii; ibidem re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſponſurus ad ea quae tibi de Arte Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicinae ejuſdemque praxi objicientur.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>Datum à Collegio <date>10 die Junii Anno Domiui 1647.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>Quòd ſi praedicto modo admonitus, non comparuerit pro Refractario ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bendum &amp; fecundum Regni Statuta plectendum cenſemus.</p>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:34510:74"/>
               <p>Cum autem nullo modo (niſi exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minatione prius habitâ) nobis conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re poſſit, quam ſit quilibet idoneùs ut ſecundum Regni Leges ad Medicinae praxin admittatur.</p>
               <p>Statuimus etiam &amp; ordinamus, Ut ſiquis Medicinam Londini, aut intra limites praedictos exercens, Praeſidis juſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu ad examen vocatus, comparuerit quidem, ſed ille tamen Praeſidi &amp; Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoribus reſpondere, &amp; ſcientiae ſuae in Medicinâ faciendâ experientiaeque rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem reddere recuſaverit, pro ignaro &amp; refractario habeatar; atque ob pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xin ita inſtitutam à Praeſide &amp; Cenſori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, ſecundum Regni Statuta punia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</p>
               <p>Statuimus etiam &amp; ordinamus, Ut ſiquis à Praeſide &amp; Cenſoribus exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natus, eorum judicio non ſatis peritus aut idoneus cenſebitur, qui ad Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinae praxin admittatur, is ſtatim ab iiſdem praxi interdicatur.</p>
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:34510:75"/>
               <p>Quòd ſi poſt hujuſmodi prohibitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, Medicinae tamen Facultatem ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercuerit vel cuipiam Medicamentum a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquod intra eandem Civitatem vel cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuitum praedictum exhibuerit, prout Regni Statutis cautum eſt, puniatur.</p>
               <p>Aequum autem cenſemus, Ut Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſores &amp; Socii examinatos omnes, quot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quot tam doctrinâ quàm moribus ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neos repererint, ad Medecinae praxin admittant, ne Collegium noſtrum Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopolii accuſetur; modò tamen Statu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis Collegii morem geſſerint.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. XVI.</hi> Forma Examinationum Sociorum &amp; Candidatorum eorundemque Admiſſionis.</head>
               <p>ANtequam quiſpiam vel in Socio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum vel Candidatorum Ordinem admittatur, ter examinetur in legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:34510:76"/>Comitiis, ſive majoribus ſive mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noribus, pro arbitrio Praeſidis &amp; Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorum, ut antea dictum &amp; ordinatum eſt in Capite de Comitiis.</p>
               <p>Forma autem Examinationis hujuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modi eſto,</p>
               <p>PRimò, Examinetur in Parte Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiologicâ, ipſiſque Medicinae Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dimentis; atque in hâc Examinatione proponantur Quaeſtiones ex Libris de Elementis, de Temperamentis, de U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu Partium, de Rebus Anatomicis, de Naturalibus Potentiis &amp; Facultatibus, &amp; de caeteris Naturalis Medecinae Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus.</p>
               <p>Secundò, Examinetur in Parte Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thologicâ, ſive de Cauſis Morborum, Differentiis, Symptomatibus, &amp; Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, quibus utuntur Medici ad Eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam Morborum cognoſcendam; atque in hâc Examinatione proponantur Quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiones ex Libris de Arte Medicinali, de Locis affectis, de Morborum &amp; Symptomatum Differentiis, de Febri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:34510:77"/>de Pulſibus, de Libris Prognoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corum Hyppocratis, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Tertiò, Examinetur de Uſu, Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citioque Medicinae, ſive Medendi Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione; idque fiat ex Libris de Sanitate Tuendâ, de Methodo Medendi, de Ratione Victûs in Morbis Acutis, de Simplici Medecinâ, de Criſibus, de A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoriſmis Hyppocratis &amp; id genus aliis quae ad Medendi uſum ſpectant; Ex. gr. Quae Cautio obſervanda ſit in Purgan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do? quaenam in Sectione Venae? nempè quo Tempore? quo Morbo? in quâ Perſonâ? quali Medicamine? in qua Venâ iſta fieri debeant? Similiter quis ſit uſus Narcoticorum &amp; Soporifero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum? &amp; quae Cautio in illis Obſervan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da? Quis ſit Locorum internorum po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitio? Sive ſitus &amp; quibus Viis pertin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant ad ea Medicamenta? Quis ſit Cly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterum? quis Vomitionum Uſus, peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culum, genus, &amp; menſura?</p>
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:34510:78"/>
               <p>Omnes has examinationes fieri volu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus à Praeſide &amp; Cenſoribus, licebit tamen cuilibet Socio diſputare, pro ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrio &amp; periculum facere, quantum in re Medicâ valeat.</p>
               <p>In iſtis autem Examinationibus cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pimus, ut Socii candidè ſe gerant, &amp; ſuavi quodam ſermonis temperamento utantur; nequaquam moroſos, ſe praebeant, aut difficiles in diſputando.</p>
               <p>Si Doctoris gradum in aliquâ no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrarum Academiarum ſuſceperit, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noris causâ ſedeat decenter examinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus; ne quid indignum pati à noſtrâ Examinationum formâ Mater Acade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia videatur.</p>
               <p>Qui ad hunc modum examinatus fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erit, ſi ſe virum doctum praeſtiterit, moreſque etiam honeſtos &amp; amabiles habuerit (de quibus inſignem curam haberi cupimus) admittatur per majo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem partem Sociorum praeſentium; modò non pauciores iſtis Comitiis ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuerint, quam duodecim praeter Praeſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem &amp; Pro-Praeſidem.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="126" facs="tcp:34510:79"/>
                  <head>Formula Admiſſionis talis eſto.</head>
                  <p>ADmittendus flexis genibus, manus invicem applicatas humiliter tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dat in manus Praeſidis, qui dicat, Ego J. C. Praeſes hujus Collegii admitto te A. B. in Societatem noſtri Collegii (vel in Ordinem Candidatorum, vel in nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merum Permiſſorum) quibus peractis ſi Socius fuerit, ſingulis Sociis praeſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus exhibitâ manu gratias agat.</p>
                  <p>Quod ſi conſtet eum qui examinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus eſt, in aliquâ è noſtris Academiis per triennium fuiſſe Publicum Medici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae Praelectorem Regium &amp; Doctorem Cathedrae, ut aiunt, vel ob ſingularem ſcientiae famam ad aulam vocatum, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Regis aut Reginae Medicum eſſe; non erit neceſſe ut examinetur, ſed pro arbitrio Praeſidis aut Pro-Praeſidis, &amp; majoris partis Sociorum praeſentium, poteſt admitti abſque ullâ diſputandi Ceremoniâ.</p>
                  <pb n="129" facs="tcp:34510:80"/>
                  <p>Quicunque, vel Cenſor vel Socius, Quaeſtiones proponit in examinationi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, detecto ſit capite, perinde ac Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor ille qui iſtic ut examinetur ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſit.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. XVII.</hi> De Loco &amp; Dignitate Praeſidis &amp; omnium Sociorum.</head>
               <p>PRaeſidis locus primus eſto, ut &amp; dignitas prima, non ſolum in Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legio, ſed in aliis omnibus locis.</p>
               <p>Medicorum Regiorum ordinario<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum qui aſſignatum Stipendium, Lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſque Patentes ſub Magno Regni Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gillo habuerint, locos &amp; honos proxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mè poſt Praeſidem eſto.</p>
               <p>Unicuique locus eſto, pro ſenio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate, ita ut ſeniores junioribus, non modò in Collegio, ſed &amp; extra illud ubique praeferantur.</p>
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:34510:81"/>
               <p>Senioritatem autem vocamus, non quam aetas aut dignitas, aut ubicun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ſuſcepti gradûs tempus fecere, ſed quam admiſſio in Collegium.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. XVIII.</hi> De Anatomica Adminiſtratione, &amp; ¶ De Lectura Chirurgiae.</head>
               <p>STatuimus &amp; ordinamus, Ut ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li Socii Admiſſionis tempore fidem dent, ſe Corpus Humanum publicè Collegii ſumptu Anatomicè admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraturos, eo anno quem Praeſes indix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erit, idque vel in Collegio, vel alio loco judicio Praeſidis &amp; Electorum aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignando; potiſſimum fi quis Anato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mices peritus iis videbitur.</p>
               <p>Quod ſi quis onus impoſitum recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaverit, atque ipſemet ad eam rem
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:34510:82"/>minùs idoneus illorum judicio habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atur, ſolvet quatuor libras in uſum Collegii; ſin autem munere hoc debi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to defungi pervicaciter negaverit is pro libito Praeſidis &amp; majoris partis Sociorum praeſentium mulctabitur; modò tamen poena haec Viginti libras non exceſſerit.</p>
               <p>Statuimus etiam &amp; ordinamus, Ut nullus Socius aut alius Collega, alibi quàm in Collegio aut loco à Praeſide &amp; Electoribus aſſignato publicè Corporis Humani adminiſtrationem ſuſcipiat aut profiteatur, ſub poena quatuor libra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, niſi locus ille ab Urbe ſeptem ad minimum miliaribus abfuerit.</p>
               <p>Volumus tamen, Ut integrum ſit cuilibet Collegae publicè Anatomiam exercere in Aulâ Chyrurgorum dum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo Communitatis Chyrurgorum Magiſter, &amp; Domini Guardiani ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niam illi priùs impetraverint à Praeſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de aut Pro-Praeſide; quippe aequum &amp; rationi conſentaneum arbitramur, ut qui per Collegam aliquem proſic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt, ii Collegio ipſi aliquod g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi officium praeſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt.</p>
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:34510:83"/>
               <p>Statuimus praeterea, Ut omnes So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cii &amp; Candidati ſingulis publicis Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomicis diſſectionibus in Collegio fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis interſint togâ &amp; pileo decenter ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiti, pro honore Collegii &amp; Artis.</p>
               <p>Qui contrà fecerit, tribus ſolidis &amp; quatuor denariis plectetur.</p>
               <p>¶ Ut Lectura in Chyrurgiâ, crebio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri idoneorum Auditorum turba meliùs frequentetur; idcirco volumus &amp; ſtatui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, ut omnes Candidati, omnes eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am permiſſi ad practicandum in hac Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitate Lecturam in Chirurgiâ diligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter audire teneantur. Qui ſecus fece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, &amp; in hac re negligentiùs ſe geſſerit, is toties quoties abſens fuerit, pro abſentiá ſuâ, ſingulis vicibus ſolvet Collegio duodecim denarios; quam pecuniae ſummam qui in manibus ſuis detinuerint &amp; Officiario Collegii ad cam rem deputato ſolvere recuſaverit intra octo dies poſt finem illius termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni, in quo propter abſentias ſuas prius debebatur, tunc volumus ut illa mulcta
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:34510:84"/>duodecim denariorum augeatur ad du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os ſolidos ſexque denarios, toties quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties delictum fuerit.</p>
               <p>Volumus inſuper, Ut poſtquam to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos quinque Annos hanc Lecturam at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentius audiverint, tunc Liberum ſit iis deinceps ut ſuo utantur, hac in re, arbitrio non enim à nobis requiritur ut longius illius Lecturae ſint Auditores poſt quinquennium in eo ſtudio dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genter collocatum.</p>
               <p>Concedimus praetereant liberum ſit unicuique pro arbitrio ter abeſle impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nè in unoquoque Termino, &amp; quod mulcta abſentium toties quoties cedat in uſum Praelectoris pro tempore exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtentis, &amp; quod ſtatutum ſit, ut debi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta fiat iſtorum omnium perſolutio, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tequam admitti poſſit in Collegium: iniquum enim cenſemus Praelectorem noſtrum fruſtra Auditores expectando oleum &amp; operam perdere, praeter ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norem Artis &amp; dignitatem Collegii.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <pb n="138" facs="tcp:34510:85"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. XIX.</hi> De Ornatu &amp; Veſtitu Medico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum</head>
               <p>STatuimus, juxta Hyppocratis conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium, Ut Socii omnes Veſtitu de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coro amiciantur, quoties ad Collegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um accedunt aut in publicum prodeunt ne Artis praeſtantia &amp; dignitas, ob im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munditiem, malè apud vulgus audiat &amp; contemptui habeatur.</p>
               <p>Quare ſtatuimus &amp; ordinamus, Ut Praeſes, Pro-Praeſes, Electores, Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſores, reliquique omnes Socii in omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Comitiis majoribus Collega<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>m Conviviis, Funeribus, &amp; Ana<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>s Adminiſtrationibus, Togâ re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>que Veſtitu decenti induantur ſub poena quinque ſolidorum Collegio ſolvendo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum quoties deliquerint.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:34510:86"/>
               <head>CAP. XX. <hi>De Exequiis.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SI ex Collegis quempiam mori con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigerit (niſi Peſte obierit) unuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſque Collega per Bedellum legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mè praemonitus funus ſuo Ordine ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui, &amp; Exequiis reliquiſque Divinis Officiis intereſſe tenebitur, ſub poenâ trium ſolidorum, &amp; quatuor denari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum Collegii uſibus ſolvendorum.</p>
               <p>Volumus praeterea, in honorem Collegii, ut Praeſidi ſedile in Templo, tapete ſive auleo, &amp; pulvinari decenti ornetur tantiſper dum Funebria Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia aliaeque Divinae Solennitates cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brantur.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <pb n="142" facs="tcp:34510:87"/>
               <head>CAP. XXI. <hi>De Conviviis.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>QUoniam ex honeſtis Conventibus mutuus amor alitur, atque ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi ſtudioſorum recreantur, Volumus, Ut omnes qui in Collegii Societatem admiſſi fuerint, Praeſidem &amp; Socios omnes in Urbe praeſentes, fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gali, honeſto, ac ſufficienti Convivio excipiant; idque tempore à Praeſide priùs indicto.</p>
               <p>Indicat autem ipſorum Comitiorum ordinariorum ſive majorum die aut quo die viſum fuerit ex quindecem proximè inſequentibus Feſtum Divi Michaelis, Nativitatis Domini, Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chatis, aut Nativitatis Divi Johannis Baptiſtae.</p>
               <p>Peracto Convivio licebit eodem in loco, excluſis alienis Arbitris, Comitia celebrare &amp; Collegii negotia tractare,
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:34510:88"/>ſi res id poſtulaverit, &amp; neceſſum Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes &amp; Conſiliarii judicaverint.</p>
               <p>Si autem aliquando contigerit, ut is, cujus eſt Convivium apparare, id commode praeſtare nequeat; ac prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terea ob juſtam aliquam &amp; honeſtam cauſam, à Praeſide &amp; majori Societatis parte approbatam petierit à Societate ut benignè legibus his ſolvatur, illo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que onere liberetur, rem totam Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidis &amp; Societatis prudentiâ moderan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam relinquimus.</p>
               <p>Quicunque tamen Collega gratiam hanc obtinuerit, ut à Convivio a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dornando immunis ſit, ſolvet nihilomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Collegii uſibus decem aut viginti libras, prout aequum videbitur Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidi, &amp; majori parti Sociorum.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <pb n="146" facs="tcp:34510:89"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. XXII.</hi> De Converſatione Morali &amp; Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutis Poenalibus.</head>
               <p>SI quae lis aut controverſia ex ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, gravitate, &amp; modeſtiâ (quae in Comitiis obſervari praeſcripſimus) parum obſervatis, oriatur; arbitrio Praeſidis aut Pro-Praeſidis, &amp; Cenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, quicunque deliquerit, punia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</p>
               <p>At ſi Praeſes, contra Statuta quid admiſerit, admoneatur quidem per Conſiliarios coram Sociis in Comitiis, non puniatur tamen, niſi ob grave a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquòd crimen (quale eſt peculatus, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve diſſipatio bonorum Collegii &amp; ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia) tale judicatum per majorem par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem Sociorum praeſentium; inter quos volumus ut quatuor ſint ex Electori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, qui unà cùm reliquis ſuper ea re ſententiam ferant.</p>
               <pb n="149" facs="tcp:34510:90"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tantum tribuimus Praeſidis honori &amp; authoritati.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ne quis revelet aut propalet quid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam alicujus momenti quod in Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio dictum ſit, ſub poenâ Decem ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorum.</p>
               <p>Nullus Collega alterum vel ignoran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae vel male praxis vel alicujus ſceleris, aut ignominioſi criminis nomine accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſabit, vel publicè contumeliis afficiet.</p>
               <p>Si quem contra feciſſe Praeſidi &amp; Cenſoribus innotuerit, primâ vice ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet in Collegii uſum Quatuor libras.</p>
               <p>Secundò duplicabitur Mulcta, quod ſi tertiò quis ſimiliter offenderit, expel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>letur è Collegio; nec denuo reſtitue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, priuſquam Collegio Decem libras ſolverit.</p>
               <p>Nullus Medicus, qui ſecundus ad ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grum vocabitur priorem Medicum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelli faciet, nec quicquam prius inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vabit (niſi res urgeat) quàm illum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venerit, &amp; ne quis fraudi locus ſit; quicunque ad aegrum accerſitur, ab
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:34510:91"/>illo vel aſtantibus, an quis Medicamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum aliquod praeſcripſerit, percuncta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitur: Sub poenâ Vigenti Solido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</p>
               <p>Poſtea tamen ex aegri ſententiâ, vel ſolus illi Medebitur, vel cum priori Medico, aut alio aliquo rem Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrabit.</p>
               <p>Dabit tamen operam, quantùm po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terit, ut priorem ſecum in Praxi re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineat.</p>
               <p>Quod ſi aegroti, vel Amicorum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſu id fieri nequeat priorem tamen, Medicum nullo modo vituperabit; nec Vultu, Geſtu, Suſpicioſo Silentio, vell ullo alio modo, illius Acta apud aegrum, vel aſtantes traducet ſed eum laudabit potius; neque id dolosè, Honeſtatis &amp; Probitatis Nomine, ſed (quod ad rem maximè attinet) pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riti &amp; Intelligentis Medici: Memor ſemper, ut alterius famam apud alios co loco habeat, quo ſuam mutatis vicibus eſſe cuperet. Nempe ad Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, quam Profitetur, Honorem &amp; Dignitatem.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="153" facs="tcp:34510:92"/>
                  <head>Conſultandi Formula.</head>
                  <p>SI plures, curationis gratiâ, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venerint, de Conditione aegri de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberaturi conſultandum eſt ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mâ modeſtiâ, &amp; non niſi ſecluſis Arbitris alienis, Latinè autem res tranſigatur; alioquin mulcta eſto quinque Solidorum in uſum Collegii.</p>
                  <p>Tunc Primùm ſedulò inquirendum in Morbi Speciem, Cauſam, &amp; Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptomata. Deinde Remedia propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenda, ad Morbum Profligandum, &amp; Symptomata Mitiganda maximè Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venientia.</p>
                  <p>Incipiat Junior Medicus, Concludat Senior.</p>
                  <p>At ſi Senior aliquis primò accerſitus fuerit, enarret ille primum rem totam reliquis; nempe quid egerit, &amp; quo ſucceſſu: Dein fiat ut dictum eſt.</p>
                  <pb n="154" facs="tcp:34510:93"/>
                  <p>Si ſaepius ad eundum aegrum vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſendum convenerint, nemo quidquem praeſcribat, imò ne innuat quidem quid agendum ſit, coram aegro, vel aſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus; priùſquam conjunctis Conſiliis privatim inter ipſos Medicos conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum fuerit: Ne quis ambitiosè nimium videatur praxin praeoccupare, &amp; reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis liberam praeſcribendi anſam prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ripere; niſi ſubitâ &amp; urgente aliquâ occaſione (eâque approbandâ à Praeſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de &amp; Cenſoribus) coactus fuerit ſolus praeſcribere.</p>
                  <p>Si Medici in Diverſas eant ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentias, ita ut in eandem praxin inter ſe conſentire nequeant, ſummâ tamen prudentiâ &amp; moderatione ſic ſe gerant, ut eorum diſcordia in Artis praejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium non cedat; nec aliis, ſi fieri poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit, innoteſcat.</p>
                  <p>Si duo tantum Medici fuerint; Junior cedat Seniori; vel tertiam ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocent, cui res referatur: Si plures vincat pars major: Si Diſſidentes nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mero pares fuerint concludatur cum
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:34510:94"/>majori parte Seniorum. Sic honori &amp; dignitati Artis providebitur; quae alioquin per Medicorum diſcordium facilè contemptui habebitur, qui con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trà ſecerit, mulctabitur Quadraginta Solidis.</p>
                  <p>Ne qua lis aut Controverſia inter Medicos, propter Officioſas Viſitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones, Praeoccupationes, &amp; Inſinuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones, oriatur.</p>
                  <p>Statuimus &amp; Ordinamus, ut cum ad Medicum quemlibet alii Medici conſultandi gratiâ advocati fuerint; ac ſecundùm formulam à nobis prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptam, de Morbo &amp; Remediis inter eos convenerit: Senior Medicus, aut alius aliquis, referat aegro, aut aſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, quae Approbata &amp; Praeſcripta communi conſenſu fuerint, eorundem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Executionem caeteri Ordinario Medico relinquant; nec denuo Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabunt aegrum, niſi à Medico Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio, aut ab aegro, ut id faciunt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsè rogati fuerint.</p>
                  <p>Nullus Medicus, ſive Socius, ſive
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:34510:95"/>Candidatus, ſive Permiſſus Conſilium ineat cum Empirico, aut rejecto à Collegio, &amp; à Medicinae praxi prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bito, aut alio aliquo ſine Admiſſione aut Permiſſione Medicinam exercente niſi urgente aliquâ Cauſâ, à Praeſide aut Pro-Praeſide, &amp; Cenſoribus, aut majori parte illorum approbandâ; ſub poenâ Quadraginta Solidorum.</p>
                  <p>Quilibet Medicus contentus eſto ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtâ, pro conditione aegri, &amp; laboris ſui, mercede.</p>
                  <p>Nemo paciſcetur cum aegro, ut alio quovis aegri nomine de praetio ſanita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis reſtituendae.</p>
                  <p>Verùm ſi quis aegros ſuſceperit cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randos, qui ſibi aliter ſatisfactum non putabunt niſi pactionem ineant cum Medico: Aut in eos incidat, qui fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultatum ſuarum, aut honoris nullâ habitâ ratione Parcè nimis &amp; illibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liter agunt cum Medicis; cum talli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus licebit paciſci. Reſervatâ tamen poteſtate Domino Praeſidi, &amp; Cenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus, atque in corum abſentiâ, quatuor ex Electoribus, pro ipſorum pruden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiâ
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:34510:96"/>corrigere, ſi quid iniquiùs pactum ſit, &amp; immutare.</p>
                  <p>Ne quis doceat Populum Medica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta, aut horum nomina illi indicet; (praeſertim ſi fuerint Medicamenta Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hementioria, veluti Purgantia, Opiata, vel Narcotica, abortum facientia, Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitoria, aut quidquam aliud majoris momenti ac periculi) ne abuſu eorum laedatur Populus: ſub poenâ quadra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginta ſolidorum, quoties offenderit.</p>
                  <p>Qui paciſcitur cum Pharmacopolis, de aliquâ pretii parte ex Medicamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis Praeſcribendis percipiendâ; mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctabitur quadraginta ſolidis quoties ita deliquerit.</p>
                  <p>Nullus Socius, Candidatus, aut Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſus, eorum Pharmacopolarum ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>râ utetur; qui aut ipſi Medicinam ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercent, aut iis Medicis crebro inſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt, qui Examinati &amp; Approbati non ſunt ſecundum Statuta hujus Regni: Sub poenâ Decem Solidorum quoties offenderit, Collegio ſolvendorum; modò eâ de re à Praeſide, aut Pro-Praeſide,
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:34510:97"/>&amp; Cenſoribus praemonitus fuerit.</p>
                  <p>Nemo mulctam, ſibi pro dilicto ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum Statuta inflictam, ſolvere re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cufabit; ſub poenâ violatae Fidei Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio praeſtitae.</p>
                  <p>Quoniam Pharmacopolae, &amp; Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gi, praecipuè Chyrurgi, ſaepe ad Medicos Urinas aegrotantium deferunt, petunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ut ab Urinarum Inſpectione ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid aegris ſuis preſcribant; ac deinde, ſub hoc Conſultationis praetextu, reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam Curationis telam ipſimet pro Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrio pertexunt; quicquid inde quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtûs ſive lucri eſt id omne ſibi arripien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, Medicis verò nihil praeter exilem illam &amp; jejunam Urinarum ſpectanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum mercedem afferentes.</p>
                  <p>Idcirco Statuimus &amp; Ordinamus, Ut nemo, ſive Socius, ſive Candidatus, ſive Permiſſus, Conſilii quidquam im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertiat iſtiuſmodi veteratoriis, Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoribus ſuper Urinarum nudâ Inſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctione, niſi ſimul ad aegrum vocetur; ut ibidem pro re natâ, idonea Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camenta, ab honeſto aliquo Phama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copolâ
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:34510:98"/>componenda, praeſcribat.</p>
                  <p>Volumus praeterea; ut ſingulis Schaedulis; ſive Receptis (ut vocant) diem Menſis, &amp; nomen Aegri, ſuum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que quiſque adſcribat.</p>
                  <p>Ridiculum quidem eſt &amp; inſulſum, ex Urinarum ſolummodò Inſpectione, ſive de Morbi Genere &amp; Naturâ, ſive de Aegrotantis Statu ac Conditione, Aruſpicum &amp; conjectorum more, velle quidquem certi, ſolidique divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nare.</p>
                  <p>Monemus igitur omnes Medicos, ut hâc in re Multò cautiùs in poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſe gerant, quam antehac à ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſque factitare ſolitum, &amp; hanc ob cauſam, omnibus Medicinam exercen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus interdictum volumus, ne Idiotis iſtis &amp; Mulierculis Aegrotantium ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulas circumferentibus, aliquod Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicamentum praeſcribant; niſi aut ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum aegrum priùs rectè noverint, aut ſaltem ab iis, qui conſilium petunt, de Morbo, ejuſque circumſtantiis, &amp; planè &amp; plenè inſtructi fuerint.</p>
                  <pb n="166" facs="tcp:34510:99"/>
                  <p>Quippe hac ratione, &amp; dignitatem Medicinae meliùs tuebimur, &amp; multò aptiùs certiuſque Remedia pericilitan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus profutura excogitabimus.</p>
                  <p>Denique Statuimus &amp; Ordinamus; Ut, quicunque admittuntur in Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem Collegii, ſubſcriptis nominibus polliceantur ſe Statuta omnia praedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta diligentèr obſervaturos; aut Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctas, contra facientibus inflictas, non invito animo perſoluturos.</p>
                  <p>Si ad hanc normam, Collegium prudenti conſilio Praeſidis, Electorum &amp; Cenſorum gubernetur; debito &amp; obedienti caeterorum officio honeſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur &amp; exterminatis indoctis, profli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiſque odioſis Impoſtoribus, ſcientiâ decoretur, certiſſimum eſt, &amp; floren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſſimum futurum hoc noſtrum Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legium in perpetuum, &amp; univerſae eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Reipublicae (quantum noſtra offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia attinet) rectè providèque conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum iri.</p>
                  <p>Quare per Fidem illam Collegio datam, Socios omnes hortamur, &amp; obteſtamur; ut quoquoverſum dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentèr
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:34510:100"/>proſpiciant, &amp; providentèr a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant; nec quemquam reſpectu perſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum habito, admittant in Societatem Collegii: ſed ad Laudem, Decus, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norem &amp; Perpetuitatem Societatis, om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia decernant; quoniam certum eſt, Collegium noſtrum nullâ re firmiùs ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biliri poſſe, &amp; continuari, quam bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis Legibus, Probis, Gubernatorum Moribus, &amp; Collegarum ſingulari Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute atque eruditione.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="eng" type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:34510:10"/>
            <head>THE Statutes (or By-Laws) OF THE COLLEDGE OF <hi>Phyſicians</hi> of <hi>London.</hi>
            </head>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:34510:11"/>
            <p>WHereas by the Private Grace of Our moſt Sovereign King <hi>HENRY VIII.</hi> and by the Publick Decrees of Parliament, It is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, That a Colledge of Phyſicians of <hi>London,</hi> be Eſtabliſhed for the Honour of the Kingdom and the Health of the Publick, that it be defended with Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges, enrich'd with Poſſeſſions, dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified with Electors, governed by a Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and Cenſors, and directed by Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes or By-Laws, and endowed with a Power of making them a-new; ſhould be aſſiſted with <hi>Conſiliarii</hi> or Aſſiſtants, and perpetuated by Learning, it ſeemed alſo moſt adviſable to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s, That We preſcribe firſt who are to be the Electors, and what their Office is, alſo who is to be Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, and after what manner, and of whom he is to be choſen, by what Law o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliged, and what his Office and Power is; and laſtly, what his Place and Dignity is; and then who are to be the <hi>Conſili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arii</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:34510:12"/>or Aſſiſtants, and what on their faith given, is to be performed by them; and what their Office, Place, and Power is; who are to be made Cenſors or Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of Learning, Manners, and alſo Medicines; and what Office upon Oath is to be performed by them; what is the Office of a Treaſurer, Regiſter, and Bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle; laſtly, what becomes the reſt for their own honour, and the glory of the Colledge, and by what <hi>Covenant</hi> they are obliged; if any Statutes are to be made, or if any are to be abrogated, after what manner that ought to be done; what is the Form of the <hi>Comitia,</hi> or Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, Examinations, and Admiſſions, what account to be had of an Offence with others, and what univerſally of right be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to all perſons and buſineſs of the Colledge; for nothing is durable, that wanteth Reaſon, Form, and Order.</p>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:34510:13"/>
               <head>CHAP. I. Of Creating the Electors.</head>
               <p>WE Conſtitute therefore and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain, That out of the number of the Fellows, Eight only Elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors be created, who for gravity, learning, manners, and age, excel the reſt; and that they be dignified with the Degree of Doctor, and are by birth Engliſh men, whoſe Office it ſhall be, by the Authority of the Colledge, the day after St. <hi>Michael,</hi> if conveniently it can be done, but if for ſome great impediments, that will not be lawful, then on ſome other day for that buſineſs more convenient, ſo that it be within a week from the time appointed in the greater Comitia or Meetings, to chooſe a Preſident out of the number of the Electors, if the Preſident of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going year having performed his annual Office, be remaining; but if he be want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as ſoon as that can conveniently be
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:34510:14"/>done, to ſubſtitute another, at the moſt within Twenty days after he has been wanting; but we underſtand a Preſident or an Elector to be wanting, if he be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dead, or expelled the Colledge, or departed from the City with his family, and he be wanting for a whole year, unleſs he be in the ſervice of the Prince.</p>
               <p>If one or more of the Elect have been ſo wanting, let one or more by a New Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction be ſubſtituted in his or their place, out of the reſt of the Fellows, who ſhall be of the ſame Nation, Degree, Manners, Learning, and Rank, within Thirty, or at moſt Forty days; but ſo that at thoſe Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitia or Meetings, only the Electors be preſent, to the intent that a more free Election be made, and a more juſt exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of manners, wiſdom, gravity, and learning, all which vertues are chiefly required by the Statutes of the Kingdom in an Elector.</p>
               <p>He that is to be choſen, ſhall firſt be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined by the Electors, as is provided for by the Statutes of the Kingdom, then let him be choſen by the conſent of them all if it may be, if not by the greateſt part;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:34510:15"/>but if their Votes are even, by the ſenior part.</p>
               <p>And if by reaſon of the reigning of a Plague, or ſome other cauſe, the Electors are out of Town, ſo that a certain day can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be appointed, then it ſhall be lawful for the Preſident, at what time and place conveniently may be, to call the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectors.</p>
               <p>If any of the Electors have left the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and made his aboad with his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily for the ſpace of a whole year, in any place beyond ſeven miles from the City, he, unleſs he be the Kings Phyſician, or otherwiſe detained in the ſervice of the Prince, ſhall loſe his place among the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectors, and another ſhall be ſubſtituted by the Preſident and Electors; yet we will that he keep his place and dignity in the Colledge, if in the mean time he ſhall certifie the Preſident of the cauſe of his abſence.</p>
               <p>He ſhall promiſe that he will give his Conſent or Vote for none to be created Preſident or Elector, unleſs according to the form of the Statute, and that he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly know and underſtand his gravity,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:34510:16"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:34510:17"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:34510:18"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:34510:19"/>learning, honeſt behaviour, decent age, and ſincere affection to the Colledge and the Common-wealth, and readineſs to perform his duty.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. Of the Preſident and his Office.</head>
               <p>WHo is to be Preſident ſhall be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for a year, and muſt be of the number of Electors, and whom the other Electors preſent, either all or moſt, ſhall judge fit, in reſpect of time, buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and perſon; and it ſhall be done at that time of the year which is already ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, when we treated of the Electors, to wit, the day after St. <hi>Michael,</hi> if con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniently it may be done, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as before in the Chapter of Creating the Electors.</p>
               <p>It is provided for and determined, if the Suffrages are equal, that party ſhall carry it, in which the greater number of the Seniors ſhall be; but if theſe alſo ſhall be equal, that ſhall prevail, to which the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:34510:20"/>Old Preſident, or he being dead or ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, the born Preſident inclines. We call the born Preſident, the Senior of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectors, who though he carry the name of Preſident, yet hath no power to make or change Statutes; but in adminiſtring and performing the Office of a Preſident in other things relating to the buſineſs of the Colledge, let him have a full power according to the true meaning of the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes.</p>
               <p>If any Elector refuſe the Office of a Preſident conferred on him, he ſhall be fined forty ſhillings, unleſs he be the Kings Phyſician.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Covenant or Faith given by the Preſident.</head>
                  <p>HE ſhall promiſe, That he will to his power endeavour that the honour of the Colledge be preſerved, the Statutes thereof without fraud obſerved, and that he will act all things for the health of the Publick, and the honeſt Profit of the Colledge.</p>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:34510:21"/>
                  <p>The Preſident of the former year, if he be preſent, ſhall demand the Faith from the New Preſident, or one of the Conſiliarii or Aſſiſtants, eſpecially the Senior, if he be preſent; or theſe being abſent, the Senior of the Electors then preſent.</p>
                  <p>He that ſhall demand his ſuretyſhip, let him hold forth the Enſigns of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, The Cuſhion, to wit, of Honour, the Book and Caduceus or Mace, and let him ſay, We give to thee the Authority of a Preſident, and deliver the Cuſhion of Honour, the Book of Knowledge, and the Caduceus or Mace of Government and Prudence, that your Excellency and all the other Colleagues, may underſtand our Colledge firmly to be eſtabliſh'd by Knowledge and Prudence; wherefore that you may not forget, you ſhall take care that the Book and Mace, as a ſign of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and Prudence, be carried by the Beadle before you in all ſolemn Meetings, Funeral Ceremonies, and at other times and places convenient, that what honour requires, that uſe may confirm.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:34510:22"/>
                  <head>The Manner of Laying down the Office.</head>
                  <p>THe Duty of Governing being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged, let the Preſident laying down his Office, having finiſhed what Prologue he pleaſe, ſay, I lay down the Authority of Governing, and in the name of all return it into your hands, ſome other, to wit, the Senior of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiliarii or Aſſiſtants chiefly; or theſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing abſent, the Senior Elector preſent; that it may be lawful to whom the power of Choice belongs, to elect and ſubſtitute whom they pleaſe: therefore I return to you the Cuſhion of Honour, the Book of Knowledge, and the Mace of prudent Government, and I wiſh all happineſs to the Colledge and you all.</p>
                  <p>Which done, to whom the power is conferred, let him propoſe for choice, whom they judge moſt fit for that Office, but let him be choſe after that manner which in the beginning of this Chapter is ordained, and let him with a loud voice, and by name pronounce him, who is choſen
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:34510:23"/>according to the Statutes, elected for Preſident, and command that all eſteem him for the Preſident; laſtly he ſhall demand his Suretyſhip from him in the ſame form as is before-mentioned.</p>
                  <p>Let the Office of the Preſident be to appoint Meetings, but after what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſhall be ſpoken by and by, when we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine of the Comitia or Meetings, and alſo to propoſe the cauſe of Meetings, to receive the opinion of every one, and to determine for the major part, and to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude factions and partios.</p>
                  <p>Let him, with the reſt whom that mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhall concern, chooſe the Electors, Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtants, and Cenſors, of learning, man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and medicines.</p>
                  <p>In chooſing Colleagues let him firſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Suffrages of others, afterwards give his own, and determine for the greater part.</p>
                  <p>Let him compoſe differences between the Colleagues, but that by common ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and opinion of the Electors and Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors ſeparately made uſe of, and in that manner which afterwards in the Chapter of the Conſiliarii or Aſſiſtants ſhall be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken more fully.</p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:34510:24"/>
                  <p>Moreover, let him take care that the Common Seal be ſafely kept in a Cheſt, he ſhall ſign all things to which the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Fellows according to their duty and the Statute have conſented.</p>
                  <p>If any Books are given to the Colledge, he ſhall take care that they be placed in the Library, and at the years end, let an Accompt of them be given to the New Preſident, and let them be ſhewed to him by name in the Index.</p>
                  <p>If there be any Revenue or yearly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, by the Lands of the Colledge, if any thing be given to the Colledge, if any thing come by any other names, let him take care that it be kept in the Common Cheſt, whereof let him have one Key, and likewiſe each of the Conſiliarii or Aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants one.</p>
                  <p>Let him require an A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>compt of the Receipts and Disburſements of the laſt year, from the Treaſurer and other Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of the Colledge, in preſence of the other Electors at that time in Town; all whom we would have ſummoned to be at the making up the Accompts if con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniently they can; but let him more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:34510:25"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:34510:26"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:34510:27"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:34510:28"/>take care that the Statutes be diligently obſerved, and read in the Colledge, either by him or the Regiſter, or ſome other, as it ſhall ſeem good to him; to wit, in that manner which is af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards provided and appointed in the Statutes.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. Of the Pro-Preſident.</head>
               <p>IT ſhall be lawful for the Preſident be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing detained in the ſervice of the Prince, or in the cure of ſome great No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleman, or oppreſſed by the multitude of other buſineſs, to chooſe and ſubſtitute for himſelf a Pro-Preſident; but let him be the born Preſident if conveniently by age, buſineſs, or health, it may be: If other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, one of the Electors who excels in gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, ſound judgement, experience, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, and cheerfulneſs of acting; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the will and pleaſure of the Preſident.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:34510:29"/>
               <p>His Office ſhall be to ſupply the place of the abſent Preſident, in acting and adminiſtring all buſineſs of the Colledge which cannot conveniently be performed by the Preſident.</p>
               <p>Let his Place and Dignity be accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his degree and ſeniority, unleſs when the Preſident is wanting; for then he ſhall poſſeſs the place of the Preſident, but only in the Colledge, to wit, in the ordinary place of meetings. But we un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the Preſident to be abſent, not only if he be without the City and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urbs, but alſo if detained by any diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, or more weighty buſineſs in the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, he cannot be preſent. But in theſe caſes we will that he make known his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence either by a Letter writ with his own hand, or by the Beadle of the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</p>
               <p>His Office ſhall continue according to the buſineſs. He ſhall give his faith, if the Electors think it fit, that he accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his ability will take care of the buſineſs of the Colledge committed to him, and will diligently act all things for the honour and profit of the Colledge,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:34510:30"/>and will act nothing unleſs with the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and advice of the Preſident or Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtants, and thoſe Fellows whom by the Statutes it ſhall concern.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV. Of the Conſiliarii or Aſſiſtants.</head>
               <p>THe day after St. <hi>Michael,</hi> if con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniently it can be done, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as before in the Chapter of Creating the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, in the ordinary Meetings preſently after the Election of a Preſident, let the ſame Electors chooſe two for the Conſiliarii or Aſſiſtants, out of their own Order, that ſhall be fit for this Office, with the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent either of all or the greater number of the Electors then preſent; if their ſuffrages ſhall be even, that part ſhall carry it, wherein there ſhall be more of the Seniors; if theſe alſo ſhall be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual, then that to which the Preſident ſhall incline.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:34510:31"/>
               <p>They ſhall give their faith that they will honeſtly and juſtly, as becometh good men, laying aſide all affection, perform their duty.</p>
               <p>Their duty is always to attend the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident in the greater Comitia or Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, to aſſiſt with their labour and counſel, where need ſhall be; never to be abſent, unleſs ſome extrardinary mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter compel; and leſt at that time the place ſhould be void, let him that ſhall be wanting ſubſtitute in his place ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>another Elector, till he ſhall return; but with the conſent of the Preſident, or he being abſent, of the Pro-Preſident.</p>
               <p>If any ſtrife or controverſie concerning any doubtful matter, or the genuine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of ſome Statute, or any diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord of this ſort ariſe among the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leagues, we will all that matter be qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etly and calmly compoſed by the Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, Aſſiſtants, and Cenſors, or by the greater part of them.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe, if between the Preſident and Colleagues any controverſie ſhall ariſe, we will that the whole matter be decided by the Aſſiſtants and Cenſors,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:34510:32"/>or by the greater part of them; but if it cannot be ſo compoſed, then we will that other Electors be joyned alſo to thoſe fore-mentioned Arbiters, that by the ſuffrages of all theſe, or of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er part, the whole matter in controverſie may be decided.</p>
               <p>And we will that this rule be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in decently ſuppreſſing all wran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glings of the Colleagues, for by this means we hope it will (which eſpecially is to be wiſh'd) that brawling, ſcoldings, and contentions, be avoided, and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly love with a ſweet conſent of minds and wills daily grow together, and be conſirmed for ever.</p>
               <p>If one of the Aſſiſtants either die, or be otherwiſe wanting, before he hath compleated the year, let another within fifteen days be deputed.</p>
               <p>Let none refuſe the Office of an Aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant under the penalty of Forty Shillings, unleſs he be the Kings Phyſician.</p>
               <p>As often as the Preſident ſhall ask their advice, let them be ready, or elſe let them pay each of them Three Shillings and four pence, unleſs ſome urgent mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:34510:33"/>ſhall hinder, whereof when they next return, they ſhall better certifie the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. Of the Cenſors.</head>
               <p>AFter the Preſident choſen and the Aſſiſtants, preſently in the ſame Meetings we appoint and ordain, That every year four men, learned and grave, be choſen, whether they ſhall be Electors or Fellows, whom we will have named Cenſors or Governours of the Colledge of <hi>London.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let their Election be by the Suffrages of the Preſident and whole Society, or of the greater part ſecretly received.</p>
               <p>Let their Office be to inquire after all perſons practiſing Phyſick, whether they be our Countrey-men or Foreigners, thorow the City and Suburbs, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Seven miles in circuit thereof, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine, correct, and govern them, and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:34510:34"/>if need be of a Law Suit, together with the Preſident and Treaſurer, to perſecute, to inquire their Methods of Cure, to condemn their Medicines, to ſearch the Apothecaries Shops, to judge of their Medicines, to burn, or any other ways to deſtroy the corrupt; and if the Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries withſtand or oppoſe, to refer the matter to the Preſident and the Colledge, and to perform all theſe things for the health of the Publick, and the honour of the Colledge.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Oath of the Cenſors or Governours.</head>
                  <p>THey ſhall ſwear before the Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, That they will decree none to be admitted into the Colledge, but whom, all affection laid aſide, they ſhall judge fit, both for learning and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; neither to approve any man or any medicine, for hire, intreaty, or favour; and in other things honeſtly to perform their Office, as God ſhall help them and the Holy Goſpel.</p>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:34510:35"/>
                  <p>Let no Fellow refuſe the Office of a Cenſor, under the penalty of Forty ſhillings, unleſs he be the Kings Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI. Of the Manner and Time of the Comitia or Meetings, and of the Caduceator or Beadle.</head>
               <p>THree days before the ſolemn Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings are to be, or the day before that day, if the matter be urgent, by the Authority of the Preſident all the Colleagues are to be ſummoned by the Beadle, or the ſervant of the Preſidents, that they be preſent at the Meetings, to be ſuch a day, hour, and place preſcribed.</p>
               <p>Whither, when they are come, let each ſeat themſelves in that order which ſhall afterwards be ſpoken; we call Comitia Meetings, or as King <hi>Henry</hi> in his
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:34510:36"/>Diploma nameth them Congregations of the Collegues; and we judge theſe Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings ſolemn or the greater legitimate, at which all the Collegues in the City are admoniſhed by the Beadle to be preſent, and in which twelve Fellows at the leaſt are preſent, beſide the Preſident. Let this be the manner of Summons, <hi>Mr. Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident intreateth your Excellency, worthy Doctor, that you be preſent at a Meeting held ſuch a Month, day, hour, and place, preſcribed by the Preſident.</hi> Laſtly, let him ſubſcribe it after this manner, <hi>A. V. B.</hi> that is, <hi>By your Authority Beadle.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let the Beadle be an honeſt man, and let him promiſe, that he will faithfully and diligently ſerve the Preſident and the Colledge in all buſineſs belonging to the Colledge without fraud or guile. Moreover, let him promiſe that he will neither for hire, intreaty, or favour, divulge the ſecrets of the Colledge to any one.</p>
               <p>Let his Office be to write ſcrowls of admonition to ſummon all the Collegues to the Meetings, to provide and keep all
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:34510:37"/>things clean and neat againſt their come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, not to be abſent from the Meetings, faithfully to bring and carry things re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from the Preſident for the uſe of the Colledge; to hunt out what-ſome-e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, whether Phyſicians or Empiricks and Impoſtors, and to give in their Names to the Preſident, and at the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidents or Cenſors commands, to give them a Summons; to burn bad Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, or otherwiſe to deſtroy them, to be preſent at Feaſts and Funerals, to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the Enſigns of Honour and perform o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things which lie on a ſervant as his duty.</p>
               <p>Let a ſalary of Twelve pounds yearly be paid by the Treaſurer to the Beadle.</p>
               <p>We will alſo that from every Candi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date and Permiſſive, four ſhillings year<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be beſtowed on him for a reward; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides in all admiſſions and fines, which exceed twenty ſhillings, and Anatomies, three ſhillings and four pence be paid him.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:34510:38"/>
                  <head>Of Summoning the Collegues to the Meeting.</head>
                  <p>WE appoint all the Collegues, who ſhall be in the City or Suburbs, to be preſent at all greater Meetings, whether ordinary or extraordinary, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ſome great impediment hinder. What relates to thoſe leſſer Congregations which are held every Month, and at other times, it ſhall be free for the reſt of the Collegues (except thoſe Six whom af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards we ſhall name in the Chapter of the Ordinary times of Meeting) ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be preſent or abſent, according to their pleaſure, unleſs they are bidden by the Summons of the Preſident or Pro-Preſident, to be there.</p>
                  <p>But if any fore-warned by the Beadle himſelf, or by a Note left by him at his houſe, ſhall not come, he ſhall pay Two ſhillings for the uſe of the Colledge, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he ſhall be excuſed by ſickneſs, or he be Two miles out of Town at the leaſt.</p>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:34510:39"/>
                  <p>They who ſhall be abſent from the Meetings on that day when the Preſident and Cenſors are to be choſen, unleſs up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſome weighty matter, to be approved by the Preſident or Pro-Preſident, or Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtants and Cenſors, ſhall pay for the uſe of the Colledge Three ſhillings four pence; nay he ſhall pay One ſhilling, who ſhall not come before the Clock ſtrike Three.</p>
                  <p>Becauſe very many lawfully ſummoned from the Preſident by the Beadle, either neglect or deſpiſe to be preſent at the for aid Meetings, whereby it often hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens that the Conventions are made void, and the other Fellows obeying the Summons of the Preſident, to no purpoſe neglect their own private buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; therefore we appoint and ordain, That if any Fellow, ſummoned after the manner aforeſaid, ſhall refuſe to come to the greater appointed Meetings, and ſhall four times continually fail in this manner, and in the mean time ſhall not give the reaſon of his abſence, to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved of by the Preſident or Pro-Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, with the Aſſiſtants and Cenſors,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:34510:40"/>let another Collegue (as ſoon as it ſhall ſeem good to the Colledge) be put into his place.</p>
                  <p>Let all the Statutes be divided into three parts or ſections, the firſt part comprehends all thoſe things which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the Electors, to the Preſident, and Pro-Preſident, to the Conſiliarii or Aſſiſtants, to the Cenſors or Governours, to the Comitia or Meetings, and other things, till you come to the Ninth Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which treateth of the Office of the Treaſurer.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond part comprehends thoſe Statutes which belong to the Treaſurer and Regiſter, to the number of Fellows and Candidates, to their Examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Elections, and Admiſſions, to the Order of the Permiſſives, and their Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and the other things, even to the Two and twentieth Chapter, which treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of the Penal or Moral Statutes.</p>
                  <p>The third part ſhall contain the Penal or Moral Statutes, and according to this threefold partition of Statutes, they may be read thorow in all greater Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, except on the day of the Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:34510:41"/>of St. <hi>Michael,</hi> at which time the Election of Officers are appointed.</p>
                  <p>Let the Fellows, Candidates, and Permiſſives, be preſent at the Reading of the Statutes, as many as can be there.</p>
                  <p>And theſe our Statutes ſhall be read after the aforeſaid manner, either by the Preſident himſelf, or Pro-Preſident (if they pleaſe) or by the Regiſter, if he be preſent; but if peradventure, the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, either obliged by buſineſs, or detain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by a Diſeaſe, or hindred by ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther grievous matter, ſhall not be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, then according to the pleaſure of the Preſident or Pro-Preſident, ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Fellows ſhall be appointed for that time; who may read thorow that part of the Statutes.</p>
                  <p>Yet in the mean time we will that it be taken care of and provided for, that if any more weighty matters are to be tranſacted in thoſe Meetings, it may be free for the Preſident or Pro-Preſident, at his pleaſure, either wholly to omit this reading of the Statutes for the time, or to read, or command to be read only ſome part.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:34510:42"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII. Of the Ordinary and Extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Times of Meetings, and other Things pertaining to the Reaſon of the Meetings.</head>
               <p>LEt the fix'd or ſettled Meetings be kept at four ſeaſons of the year, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually diſtant.</p>
               <p>The firſt the day after St. <hi>Michael,</hi> if conveniently it may be done, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as is ſaid before.</p>
               <p>The ſecond the day after St. <hi>Thomas,</hi> if conveniently, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The third the day after <hi>Palm Sunday,</hi> if, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The fourth the day after the Nativity of St. <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> if conveniently, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And theſe are all the ordinary or fix'd Meetings, which alſo may be called ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn or greater.</p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:34510:43"/>
               <p>And beſide the fix'd or ordinary Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, it ſhall alſo be lawful for the Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to ſummon likewiſe other ſolemn or greater extraordinary Meetings, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the neceſſity or dignity of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter happening.</p>
               <p>And in all theſe ſolemn Meetings we will that twelve Fellows at leaſt be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, beſides the Preſident and Pro-Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident.</p>
               <p>But if ſome urgent neceſſity, as the raging of a Peſtilence, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or ſome weighty affair, happen to be diſpatched at the command of the Prince; and that peradventure in ſuch a time, wherein ſo many Fellows ſhall not be preſent in the City, then indeed you muſt obey neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and in ſuch a caſe the whole matter is to be left to the prudence and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Preſident or Pro-Preſident, that as many as ſhall be in the City, he take care that all thoſe be ſummoned by the Beadle, to be preſent at the Meetings; and in thoſe greater Meetings we will that the ordinary Elections and Admiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of new Fellows, Candidates, and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſives, be made.</p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:34510:44"/>
               <p>But for what belongs to the Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Fellows, Candidates, or Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſives, thoſe may rightly be porformed, either in thoſe greater Meetings, or alſo in the other leſſer Conventions, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the pleaſure of the Preſident or Pro-Preſident.</p>
               <p>In all Meetings let the Preſident or Pro-Preſident expound the cauſe of the Convention, let him obſerve what each ſpeak in their order, and receive the Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frages: neither let any depart unleſs leave firſt obtained, before the Preſident or Pro-Preſident hath diſſolved the Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in theſe eloquent words, <hi>We diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge theſe Meetings.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There are alſo other Meetings, which are called leſſer, ſuch as are held every Month, and at other times, as ſome ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den occaſion ſhall require; according to the reaſon of things and perſons.</p>
               <p>In theſe thoſe that are admitted into the Colledge are examined, alſo the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of Quacks and Impoſtors, and of all perſons practiſing Phyſick ill, are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſed by the Preſident and Cenſors, and
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:34510:45"/>they puniſhed according to their deſerts; and other buſineſs of that kind are treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of.</p>
               <p>In theſe leſſer Meetings, we do not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire that ſo many Fellows be preſent as are required in the greater and ſolemn Meetings; it ſhall ſuffice if in theſe Mr. Preſident, the four Cenſors and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter be preſent.</p>
               <p>But it is neceſſary that all the Cenſors are preſent, according to the Statutes of the Kingdom; provided they be lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſummoned by the Beadle: wherefore leſt the reſt meet in vain, we ordain an abſent Cenſor to be fined Ten ſhillings, unleſs he certifie the Preſident before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand of the cauſe of his abſence.</p>
               <p>Leaſt any controverſie or reproach ſhould ariſe, we muſt act in all Meetings with the higheſt modeſty and the greateſt gravity; for certainly ſcolding is filthy in private, but moſt filthy in publick Meetings, eſpecially among thoſe who are judged to have acquired honeſt man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners out of good diſciplines.</p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:34510:46"/>
               <p>Therefore let none propoſe or ſpeak any thing publickly in the Colledge, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs with his hat off, and leave firſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained from the Preſident, to whom alone his ſpeech is to be directed.</p>
               <p>But if many ſhall begin to ſpeak toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, let the Junior give way to the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior. Let every one ſpeak ſhortly and gravely, without prolix babbling; and at the admonition of the Preſident be ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent.</p>
               <p>And its lawful for none to diſturb him that is ſpeaking, but the Preſident or Pro-Preſident, or the ſenior of the Cenſors then preſent; whoſe Office let it be to admoniſh every one of their duty.</p>
               <p>But let every one ſpeak his judgement to the Matter propoſed, once only and in his order, unleſs by leave again obtained from the Preſident.</p>
               <p>Let the other Fellows be attent, and not diſturb him that is ſpeaking, or the hearers, with their private diſcourſe whiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perings or noiſe; nnd let ſilence always be made at the nod of the Preſident: who
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:34510:47"/>ſhall act contrary let him be puniſhed Two ſhillings, preſently to be paid.</p>
               <p>In matters doubtful and of great mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, let the delegates be choſe at the pleaſure of the Preſident, who may diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſs the matter on every ſide, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late it to the Colledge in each Meeting, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Preſident hath opened the cauſe of the Convention.</p>
               <p>Let the Regiſter with a loud voice relate what was done in the laſt Meetings, that (thoſe things being expunged, if any things are to be mended or correct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) they may at laſt be writ in the Book of Annals.</p>
               <p>Let none propoſe to gather the Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frages, but the Preſident or Pro-Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident.</p>
               <p>In all Elections let the Votes be carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſilently and ſecretly, by peaſe or beans, in other buſineſs of the Colledge as it ſeem good to the Preſident or Pro-Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:34510:48"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII. Of Making and Abrogating of Statutes, and of Levying of Fines.</head>
               <p>LEt few Statutes be eſtabliſh'd, and thoſe confirmed either by Faith gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, or Fine.</p>
               <p>Let the Mulct be ſmall but inevita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, let the leaſt Mulct be a Shilling.</p>
               <p>To make any Statute, two Meetings ſhall ſuffice, but to abrogate not under three.</p>
               <p>We appoint and ordain that all Fines which after what manner ſoever are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, by the Preſident or Pro-Preſident and four Cenſors, or by the greater part of the Fellows, go only to the uſe of the Colledge, and not to the profit of any private perſon; yet thoſe payments of Money are excepted, which by the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes of the Colledge are otherways grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:34510:49"/>to the Officers. We will that theſe Mulcts be forthwith paid, or at leaſt a depoſite given, ſuch as the Preſident ſhall deſire, to ſecure the preſent money.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX. The Office of the Treaſurer.</head>
               <p>HE ſhall receive the Revenue and Profits which yearly accrue to the Colledge, and in his cuſtody ſafely ſhall keep for the uſe of the Colledge.</p>
               <p>He ſhall take care of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tenſils and other Neceſſaries of the Colledge, as of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten as need ſhall be.</p>
               <p>He ſhall, as well as he can, ſafely and decently keep the Goods thereof, Books, Houſhold-ſtuff, and other Ornaments ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaining to the glory thereof.</p>
               <p>If any thing be to be repaired in the Buildings of the Colledge, he ſhall take care that it be ſeaſonably done.</p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:34510:50"/>
               <p>He together with the Preſident and Cenſors, ſhall proſecute the Controverſies and Law-ſuits of the Colledge.</p>
               <p>He ſhall pay to the Officers of the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge every ones Salary or Stipend due according to the Statutes, at the four u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual Seaſons of the Year.</p>
               <p>He ſhall give in his Accompts twice every Year to the Preſident and Electors, if he be required to it and fore-warned.</p>
               <p>He ſhall give a perfect Accompt for the whole Year laſt paſt, within a Month af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Feaſt of St. <hi>Michael;</hi> to wit, on that day which the Preſident ſhall aſſign him.</p>
               <p>He ſhall reſtore to the Preſident and Electors the whole ſum of Money which at that time ſhall be over remaining, and the other Goods, Houſhold-ſtuff, and the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tenſils of the Colledge which have been in his cuſtody.</p>
               <p>He ſhall be bound in a Bond to the Preſident and Society, on the ſame day that he is admitted to his Office, that he faithfully pay the Wages due to the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of the Colledge within a Week after
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:34510:51"/>the compleat making up his Accompt for that Year.</p>
               <p>In repairing the Buildings of the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, or in buying things neceſſary for the uſe of the Colledge, he ſhall not lay out above Forty Shillings without the will and conſent of the Preſident or Pro-Preſident.</p>
               <p>To the Treaſurer for a Salary ſhall be paid yearly out of the Revenues of the Colledge the ſum of Forty Shillings.</p>
               <p>Moreover, We appoint and ordain, That from each perſon admitted into the Society of the Colledge, alſo from every one that ſhall be admitted into the Order of the Candidates, or into the number of Permiſſives, he ſhall receive Six Shillings and eight pence at the time of their Admiſſion.</p>
               <p>He ſhall give his Faith, That he will perform his Office faithfully according to the Statutes, and that he will act all things for the honour and profit of the Colledge, and that he will faithfully give up his Accompt at the Summons of the Preſident.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:34510:52"/>
               <head>CHAP. X. Of the Regiſter.</head>
               <p>LEt the Office of the Regiſter be after this manner, To be preſent at all Meetings of the Colledge, whether great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er or leſſer, being lawfully and ſeaſonably admoniſh'd by the Beadle of the Colledge, or the ſervant of the Preſident or Pro-Preſident, on the penalty of Ten Shil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings.</p>
               <p>Whatſoever ſhall be there acted, ratifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and eſtabliſh'd, by the conſent of the Preſident and the greater part of the Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows preſent (unleſs it be matter of ſmall moment, and unworthy to be taken notice of) all that he ſhall faithfully ſet down, in the beginning of the next following Meetings let him read it over, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards (it being corrected, if any things are to be amended) let him enter it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Regiſter of the Colledge.</p>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:34510:53"/>
               <p>But if he ſhall be hindred by ſickneſs or more weighty buſineſs, ſo that he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be preſent; then it ſhall be lawful for him to ſubſtitute ſome other Fellow for the time, who may ſignifie the cauſe of his abſence to the Preſident, and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently ſupply his place.</p>
               <p>The Forms of Letters writ to the Colledge or from the Colledge, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things that are acted, let him enter into the Regiſter Book.</p>
               <p>For an Annual Stipend, there ſhall be yearly paid to the Regiſter Forty Shil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, to be accompted to him from the Treaſurer, out of the Revenue of the Colledge, by equal parts, at the four uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al times of this Kingdom.</p>
               <p>From every one who are permitted to practiſe Phiſick, or received into the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Candidates, or admitted into the number of the Fellows, ſhall be paid at the very time, either of Permiſſion or Admiſſion, the ſum of Six Shillings and eight pence to the Regiſter, and Five Shillings more for writing their Names in the Regiſter Book.</p>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:34510:54"/>
               <p>As often as it ſhall happen that any one by the Sentence of the Preſident or Pro-Preſident and Cenſors, be fined in any notable ſum of money to be paid to the Colledge, by every one ſo puniſh'd Three Shillings and four pence ſhall be paid to the Regiſter.</p>
               <p>If any fined in any ſum of money to be paid for the uſe of the Colledge, ſhall not together and at once pay the whole fine, but ſhall put off the payment ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for ſome days, and ſo ſhall pay it piece-meal, for each of thoſe payments ſo made in parts, Three Shillings and four pence ſhall be paid to the Regiſter; for we judge his Office a troubleſome bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den.</p>
               <p>He ſhall give his Faith that he will duly perform his Office according to the Statutes for the honour and profit of the Colledge, and all things which have been acted either in greater or leſſer Meetings, without fraud faithfully inſert into the Regiſter Book.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:34510:55"/>
               <head>CHAP. XI. Of the Candidates.</head>
               <p>WE appoint and ordain, That the number of Candidates do not exceed Twelve; We will that none be admitted into that Order, who is not a Doctor in Phiſick, and by Nation an Engliſhman, and hath practiſed Phiſick for four years.</p>
               <p>But if he has attained the Degree of Doctor in any Foreign <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity, We will, That before he be admitted to Examination, he bring forth his Diplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma or Letters Teſtimonial true and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentick of that <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity, and ſhew them to the Colledge; and beſides that let him have and bring a Teſtimonial of his Incorporation from one of our own <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities.</p>
               <p>We will moreover and ordain, That each Candidate and Permiſſive, before
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:34510:56"/>they be admitted, viſit all the Fellows of the Colledge twice, to ask leave, to wit, the firſt time before any Examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but the ſecond the courſe of Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions being finiſh'd.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Faith required of the Candidates.</head>
                  <p>YOu ſhall give your Faith, That you will obſerve the Statutes of the Colledge, and to your power endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour that the Honour thereof be preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved intire, nor at any time ſhall you conſult, or entertain familiarity with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny one who ſtudies in word or deed to ſubvert the State of the Colledge; but in all things which belong to the honour and profit of the Colledge, you ſhall promote with your advice, aid, and aſſiſtance.</p>
                  <p>You ſhall give your Faith, That you will in all things lawful and honeſt, be obedient to Mr. Preſident or Pro-Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and Electors, that you will give place to the Senior in the Colledge (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Statutes) and reſpect him with due honour.</p>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:34510:57"/>
                  <p>You ſhall come to the Colledge at the command of Mr. Preſident or Pro-Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident and Cenſors, as often as you ſhall be admoniſh'd and ſent for by the Beadle.</p>
                  <p>You ſhall be preſent at all Anatomies, unleſs detained by ſome great impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to be approved by the Preſident and Cenſors.</p>
                  <p>Neither for intreaty, nor rewards, nor on any other cauſe, ſhall you give Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines which cauſe Abortion or Miſcarri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, nor Poiſons of any kind for deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, or to an ill uſe; neither ſhall you teach them any one, whom you ſuſpect will abuſe them.</p>
                  <p>You ſhall by name accuſe none who is admitted into the Colledge, of ignorance or ill practice, or publickly reproach them.</p>
                  <p>You ſhall perſecute by all honeſt means the unlearned, Empiricks and Impoſtors, and their names you ſhall give in to the Preſident or Cenſors; neither ſhall you keep company with Empiricks and others not licenſed by the Colledge; neither ſhall you by any means frequent their
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:34510:58"/>Meetings, to the detriment or infamy of the Colledge.</p>
                  <p>The ſecrets of the Colledge you ſhall divulge to none, that is not of the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</p>
                  <p>You ſhall give your faith that you will neither by Letters from great Men, nor by price, nor by any other unlawful means, circumvent the Society of the Colledge; and that you will to your power do all things in the Art of Phiſick for the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the Colledge and the Publick good.</p>
                  <p>We appoint and ordain, That the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſive or Licentiates, and alſo the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didates, diligently obſerve our Statutes and Decrees, be obedient to the Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, Electors, and Cenſors, and the Mulcts impoſed on them for defaults they readily pay.</p>
                  <p>Beſides, they ſhall not refuſe plainly and nakedly to reveal thoſe their Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines which they call Secrets or Arcana, and are wont to uſe in their practice, as often as they are required to do ſo by the Preſident and Cenſors; who ſhall
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:34510:59"/>obſtinately act contrary, ſhall be puniſh'd at the pleaſure of the Preſident and Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors.</p>
                  <p>Every Candidate ſhall pay at the time of his Admiſſion Four pounds to the uſe of the Colledge, and Ten ſhillings for the proper uſe of the Preſident; but to the Treaſurer Six ſhillings and eight pence; alſo to the Regiſter for his due Salary Six ſhillings and eight pence, and to him moreover Five other ſhillings, for inſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Name into the Book of Annals; and beſides to the Beadle of the Colledge Three ſhillings and four pence.</p>
                  <p>Becauſe many flock hither to practiſe, of the number of which there are very many, who coming out of their <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities before their due time, fly to places beyond the Seas, that in foreign Nations by a ſhorter ſpace and leſſer charge, they may creep to the degree of Doctor, then they could attain at home in our <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities.</p>
                  <p>We therefore appoint, That whoever ſhall be admitted either into the Society
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:34510:60"/>of the Colledge, or into the Order of the Candidates, or into the number of the Permiſſive: If he has taken the degree of Doctor abroad, he at the time of his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion ſhall pay double to the Colledge, Preſident, Treaſurer, Regiſter, and other Officers of the Colledge, then thoſe are wont to pay who are created Doctors in our own <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities. Alſo whoever is created Doctor in our <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities, yet if he anticipate, by more haſtily acquiring that Degree then is the fit time due to that dignity; that is, if he made Doctor either before he has been ſeven whole years Maſter in the Arts, or has been ſo long Batchelor in Phiſick, he ſhall pay double more to the Colledge, Preſident, and to the other aforeſaid Officers of the Colledge, then they are wont who accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the laudable Laws and Cuſtoms of our <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities, at the time prefix'd, and with more mature judgement, aſcend to the degree of Doctor.</p>
                  <p>We will, That all Candidates and Permiſſives ſummoned by the Beadle,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:34510:61"/>be preſent at every one of our Meetings; that if they know any unlawfully and ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norantly exerciſing Practice, they ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie their Names to the Preſident and Cenſors, and alſo that they hear the Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Statutes.</p>
                  <p>Let them likewiſe pay, if occaſion be, or the neceſſity of the Colledge urges, as Fellows; ſo they be required thereto.</p>
                  <p>The year compleat, let the Candidates move and ask the Preſident to be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into the number of the Fellows, if ſo be it may conveniently be done, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Statutes.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XII. Of the Fellows.</head>
               <p>WE appoint and ordain, That the number of the Fellows exceed not Thirty, and we will that above this certain and determinate number the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians in ordinary to the King, Queen,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:34510:62"/>and Prince, be admitted as Honorary, and to be reckoned Supernumeraries.</p>
               <p>We will moreover, That no body be admitted into the Society of the Colledge, who have not been firſt for a whole year of the number of the Candidates, or pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly read Phiſick in ſome <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity of <hi>England,</hi> or hath been formerly Doctor of the Chair (as they ſay) in ſome <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of this Kingdom, or has been the Kings Phiſician in Ordinary.</p>
               <p>Every Fellow at the time of his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion ſhall pay to the Colledge, Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, Treaſurer, Regiſter, and Beadle, as is appointed before concerning the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didates; but all payments ſhall be dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled on thoſe conditions which are above mentioned.</p>
               <p>We appoint alſo, That all Fellows at the time of admiſſion have Letters Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, ſigned with the Seal of the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and be obliged by this given faith.</p>
               <p>YOu ſhall endeavour to your power that the State of the Colledge be
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:34510:63"/>perpetuated; the Statutes of the Colledge you ſhall keep, you ſhall obey the Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in thoſe things which relate to the honour and perpetuity of the Colledge.</p>
               <p>You ſhall not give what may cauſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bortion, or take away or hinder concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, nor poiſon to an ill end, nay in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed you ſhall not ſo much as teach them, where there is a ſuſpicion of an ill deſign.</p>
               <p>You ſhall determine none to be choſe into the Colledge, unleſs whom, laying a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide all affection, you ſhall judge for knowledge and manners ſuitable.</p>
               <p>You ſhall read diligently within a year the five firſt Books of <hi>Galen</hi> concerning Simple Medicine, and all the Books of the uſe of the parts.</p>
               <p>You ſhall perſecute by all honeſt means the unlearned, Empericks, and Impoſtors; you ſhall give in their Names to the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident, Pro-Preſident, or Cenſors.</p>
               <p>You ſhall alſo give your faith that you have practiſed Phiſick for four years, or have read publickly in ſome <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity.</p>
               <p>Alſo you ſhall give your faith, that you will with great diligence obſerve the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:34510:64"/>concerning the publick diſſection of humane bodies, whenſoever you ſhall be ſummoned by the Preſident or Pro-Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, You ſhall truly and on good faith ſay, what is your Countrey.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Letters of Admiſſion.</head>
                  <p>KNow all men, That we <hi>A. B.</hi> Doctor of Phiſick and Preſident of the Colledge of Phiſicians of <hi>London,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the conſent of the Fellows thereof, by the Authority granted to us from our Lord the King and Parliament, have examined, approved, and into our Colledge choſe the learned and honeſt man <hi>C. D.</hi> of <hi>Kent,</hi> in the moſt Flouriſhing <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity of <hi>Oxford</hi> or <hi>Cambridge,</hi> Doctor of Phiſick, and thereby have granted the free Faculty and Licence of exerciſing the Knowledge and Art of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, according to the Form of the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes publiſh'd to that purpoſe; and more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over we have beſtowed the uſe and profit of all Advantages, Liberties, and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:34510:65"/>which by the Authority aforeſaid are already granted to our Colledge, and which for the future may be granted.</p>
                  <p>For the truth and teſtimony whereof we have cauſed our Common Seal to be ſet to theſe preſents. Given at <hi>London</hi> in our Colledge the ſeventh day of <hi>May Anno Domini 1647.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>* If any of the Collegues hath applied himſelf to Religion or the Prieſthood, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he hath been choſen into the Colledge, let him not be called to the Colledge; that we may not ſeem to recall him to the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of Phiſick, whom Religion and the Law Eccleſiaſtick has abandoned from the Office of a Phiſician.</p>
                  <p>* Neither do we think it honeſt for a Clergyman or Preacher, among other things, to meddle with Womens buſineſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and diſeaſes.</p>
                  <p>* But if any Clergyman or Preacher, deſires to be admitted into the Colledge, or permitted to Practice, let him not be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in for the ſame reaſons.</p>
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:34510:66"/>
                  <p>If any one of the Collegues ſhall addict himſelf to the Prieſthood, after he has been admitted into the Colledge, we will not that he be again ſummoned to the Colledge.</p>
                  <p>But if any Clerk, or one entred in Holy Orders, deſires to be admitted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Colledge, or to be permitted to Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, much leſs ſhall that be granted him.</p>
                  <p>We appoint and ordain, That if any one guilty of ſome more hainous and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick crime, or ſhall be infamous for ſome notable vice, he ſhall be diſcharged from the Colledge; leſt if we retain ſuch, we ſhould ſeem either to contemn vertue, or labour under the ſame diſeaſe; but leſt ſuch not being a Collegue, ſhould be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted into the Colledge, it is both by other Statutes prohibited, and we forbid it by theſe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:34510:67"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIII. Letters Teſtimonial of thoſe that Practiſe thorow the whole Kingdom of <hi>England.</hi>
               </head>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="license_to_practice_medicine">
                  <body>
                     <p>KNow all men, That we <hi>A. B</hi> Doctor of Phiſick and Preſident of the Colledge of Phiſicians of <hi>London,</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the conſent of <hi>B. H.</hi> and <hi>R. M.</hi> of the aforeſaid Colledge, Fellows and Electors, by the Authority granted to us from our Lord the King and Parliament, have examined and approved 17th day of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> in the year of our Lord <hi>1647,</hi> the honeſt man <hi>T. W.</hi> of the County of <hi>B.</hi> in the moſt Flouriſhing <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity of <hi>Oxford</hi> or <hi>Cambridge,</hi> Maſter of Arts, and in the City of <hi>York</hi> well exerciſed in the Practice of Phiſick, and we judge him worthy, who may be admitted to the Practice of Phiſick according to the form
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:34510:68"/>of the Statutes publiſh'd to this purpoſe;</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>in teſtimony whereof we have ſet our Common Seal and ſubſcribed our Names. Given at <hi>London</hi> in our Colledge <date>the day and month, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                           </date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>If any one after the aforeſaid manner ſhall be judged qualified for Practice by the Preſident and three Electors, he ſhall tell his Name to the Regiſter, that he may be inſerted into the Book of Annals.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIV. Of Suppreſſing Quacks.</head>
               <p>WHereas there is a great number of unskilful perſons who annoy the Common-wealth, and it lies on us, by the Preſcript of the King and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that we take care of the health and ſecurity of the people; we appoint and ordain for the more commodious ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpation of ſuch, that whom for certain we ſhall prove to be unlearned and diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:34510:69"/>that we puniſh not only by fine and impriſonment, but alſo that we certifie by our Letters the Magiſtrates and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours of every City, Province, or Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction, where ſuch Impoſtors dwell, that they are to be reckoned unworthy the name of Phiſicians, and therefore to be treated as other Citizens.</p>
               <p>Let this be the Form of the Letters, but in Engliſh.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>Form of the Letter to the Magiſtrates.</head>
                     <p>WOrthy Sirs, We certifie you that <hi>H. M.</hi> of your Province Quick, living in the Street <hi>S.</hi> is a man unlearn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and unskilful of Phiſick, and in no wiſe is of our Colledge; wherefore you may according to your Law elect and chuſe him and all others who have not Letters Teſtimonial, ſigned with our Seal, to ſerve all fit Offices of your City, and to compel them to act and perform o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things, which its granted to your authority to command.</p>
                     <pb n="108" facs="tcp:34510:70"/>
                     <p>Theſe we have written, to that end leſt thoſe ſilly Impoſtors of the Commonalty, ſhould under the name and pretence of Phiſick, evade your Priviledges.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>Given from our Colledge, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XV. Of the Permiſſives or Licenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates to Practice.</head>
               <p>BEcauſe very many in this City exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe Phiſick, whom we think altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unfit to be admitted into the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Fellows or Candidates, either becauſe they are Foreigners, or are not admitted Doctors, or are not ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly learned, or by reaſon of their too great youth, or ſuch like cauſes, yet may not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, be ſerviceable to the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, in taking care of the health of the Kings ſubjects, at leaſt in ſome particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Diſeaſes.</p>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:34510:71"/>
               <p>Concerning theſe we ordain and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point that after due examinations and the approbation of the Preſident and Cenſors, they be permitted to practiſe ſo long as they behave themſelves well.</p>
               <p>We will that all who are only permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to practiſe, be bound with the ſame faith wherewith the Candidates are.</p>
               <p>Therefore the Preſident at the time of admiſſion ſhall uſe theſe words, I <hi>J. C.</hi> Preſident of the Colledge of Phiſicians of <hi>London,</hi> by the authority granted me by Law, permit thee <hi>A. B.</hi> to the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of Phiſick in the City of <hi>London,</hi> and for ſeven miles round about, as long as you behave your ſelf well, and ſhall obſerve the Statute of the Colledge, and perform your due payments; and to you ſo doing I wiſh all happineſs.</p>
               <p>We will that the Permiſſive or Licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiates make all uſual payments to the Colledge, Preſident, Treaſurer, Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and Beadle, which lately we aſſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be performed by the Candidates.</p>
               <p>We will moreover that the firſt year of Permiſſion they pay to the Colledge ſix
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:34510:72"/>pounds, unleſs for reaſons to be appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of by the Preſident and Cenſors, it ſhall be thought fit to deal more gently with them; however they ſhall pay four pounds at leaſt: but for the following years, as long as they ſhall be Permiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſives, they ſhall pay to the uſe of the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge forty ſhillings.</p>
               <p>We appoint and ordain, That none be admitted to the Practice of Phiſick with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the City, Suburbs, and ſeven miles round about, unleſs he has been firſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined thrice (on ſo many days appointed for that purpoſe) by the Preſident and Cenſors, and by them approved and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the Practice of Phiſick.</p>
               <p>But if any within the ſpace, or fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid circuit, hath exerciſed the Faculty of Phiſick, and as yet has not freely of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered himſelf to the Preſident and Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, to be examined, let him firſt be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed by the Beadle, and that in the name of the Preſident, that he altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther abſtain from the Practice of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, till he hath obtained the approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Preſident and Colledge, and
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:34510:73"/>that at a ſet and prefix'd time, he appear before the Preſident and Cenſors, to wait their examination and approbation.</p>
               <p>And let the Beadle deliver a Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons either to him into his hands, or he ſhall leave it at his houſe, in theſe words;</p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="summons">
                  <body>
                     <p>WE the Preſident and Genſors of the Colledge of Phiſicians of <hi>London,</hi> ſummon you to appear on the 14th day of <hi>June</hi> before us, in your own proper perſon, and that between two or three of the clock in the afternoon of the ſame day in the Colledge, there to anſwer to thoſe things that ſhall be objected to you concerning the Art of Phiſick and the Practice thereof.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>Given from our Colledge <date>the 10th day of <hi>June Anno Domini 1647.</hi>
                           </date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>But if being ſummoned after the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid manner, he ſhall not appear, we judge him to be eſteemed for a refractory perſon, and to be puniſhed according to the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes of the Kingdom.</p>
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:34510:74"/>
               <p>But ſeeing by no means (unleſs by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination firſt had) it can be manifeſt to us, how every one is qualified to be admitted to the Practice of Phiſick ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Laws of the Kingdom.</p>
               <p>We moreover appoint and ordain, That if any exerciſing Phiſick at <hi>London,</hi> or within the aforeſaid limits, ſummoned by the commands of the Preſident to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination, ſhall appear truly, but in the mean time ſhall refuſe to anſwer the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident and Cenſors, and to give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of his knowledge and experience in the Practice of Phiſick, let him be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed for an ignorant and refractory perſon; and for Practice ſo begun, let him be puniſh'd by the Preſident and Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, according to the Statutes of the Kingdom.</p>
               <p>We alſo appoint and ordain, That if any examined by the Preſident and Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, and in their judgements ſhall be thought not ſufficiently skilful or quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, to be admitted to the Practice of Phiſick, let him preſently by them be forbid the Practice.</p>
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:34510:75"/>
               <p>But if after ſuch Prohibition, he ſhall notwithſtanding exerciſe the Faculty of Phiſick, or give any Medicine to any perſon within the ſame City, or the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference aforeſaid, let him be puniſh'd as is provided by the Statutes of the Kingdom.</p>
               <p>But we think it juſt that the Cenſors and Fellows ſhould admit to the Practice of Phiſick all examined perſous, as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as they ſhall find qualified, as well for learning as manners; leſt our Colledge ſhould be accuſed of a Monopoly; yet ſo that they obey the Statutes of the Colledge.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVI.</hi> The Form of the Examinations of the Fellows and Candi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dates, and of their Admiſſion.</head>
               <p>BEfore any one be admitted either in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Order of the Fellows or Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didates, let him be examined thrice in
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:34510:76"/>lawful Meetings, whether greater or leſſer, according to the pleaſure of the Preſident and Cenſors, as is ſaid and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained before in the Chapter of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitia or Meetings.</p>
               <p>Let the Form of Examination be after this manner,</p>
               <p>FIrſt, Let him be examined in the Phyſiologick Part, and the very Rudiments of Medicine, and in this Examination let Queſtions be propound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of Books concerning Elements, Temperaments, the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of Parts, Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomy, Natural Powers and Faculties, and the other Parts of Natural Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Let him be examined in the Pathologick Part, or concerning the Cauſes, Differences, Symptoms, and Signs of Diſeaſes, which Phiſicians make uſe of to know the Eſſence of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes; and in this Examination let Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions be propoſed out of Books concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Art of Phiſick, of the Places af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, of the Differences of Diſeaſes,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:34510:77"/>and Symptoms, of Feavers, of the Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, of the Books of the Prognoſticks of <hi>Hypocrates,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Let him be examined con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe and Exerciſe of Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine, or the Reaſon of Healing; and let that be done out of the Books concerning Preſervation of Health, of the Method of Healing, of the Reaſon of Diet in Acute Diſeaſes, of Simple Medicines, of Criſes, of the Aphoriſms of <hi>Hyppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates;</hi> and other things of that kind, which relate to the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of Healing; for Example ſake, What Caution is to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in Purging? what in Blood-let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting? at what Time? in what Diſeaſe? in what Perſon? with what Medicine? and in what Vein, thoſe things ought to be done? Likewiſe, what is the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of Narcoticks and Sleeping Medicines? and what Caution is to be obſerved in them? what is the Poſition and Site of the Internal places? and by what Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages Medicines come to them? What is the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of Clyſters, what of Vomits, the danger, kind, and meaſure?</p>
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:34510:78"/>
               <p>We will that all theſe Examinations be made by the Preſident and Cenſors, yet it ſhall be lawful for any Fellow to diſpute at his pleaſure, and make trial how able the examined is in the Phiſical Art.</p>
               <p>But in theſe Examinations, we deſire that the Fellows behave themſelves fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and uſe a pleaſant temperament of ſpeech; by no means ſhewing themſelves moroſe or difficult in diſputing.</p>
               <p>If he hath taken the Degree of Doctor in any of our <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities, let him that is to be examined, for Honours ſake be decently ſeated; leſt our Mother <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity ſhould ſeem to ſuffer ſome affront from our form of Examinations.</p>
               <p>He who bath been examined after this manner, if he ſhew himſelf a learned man, and hath honeſt and amiable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation (of which we deſire great care to be taken) let him be admitted by the greater part of the Fellows preſent; ſo there be not fewer preſent at thoſe Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings than twelve, beſides the Preſident and Pro-Preſident.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="127" facs="tcp:34510:79"/>
                  <head>Let this be the Form of Admiſſion.</head>
                  <p>HE that is to be admitted, let him on his bended knees humbly deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver his bands joyned together, into the hands of the Preſident, who ſhall ſay, I <hi>J. C.</hi> Preſident of this Colledge, admit thee <hi>A. B.</hi> into the Society of our Colledge (either into the Order of Candidates, or into the number of Permiſſives) which being done, if he be a Fellow, he ſhall with taking by the hand, give thanks to all the Fellows preſent.</p>
                  <p>But if it appear that he who is to be examined, has been for three years Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Reader of Phiſick or Regius Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor, and Doctor of the Chair (as they ſay) in any of our <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities, or for his ſingular fame of knowledge, is called to Court, and is the Kings, Queens, or Princes Phiſician, it ſhall not be neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to examine him; but at the pleaſure of the Preſident and Pro-Preſident, and greater part of the Fellows preſent, he may be admitted without any Ceremony of Diſputing.</p>
                  <pb n="128" facs="tcp:34510:80"/>
                  <p>Whoſoever, either Cenſor or Fellow, propoſeth Queſtions in Examinations, let him be with his head uncovered, as alſo that Doctor that commeth thither to be examined.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XVII. Of the Place and Dignity of the Preſident and all the Fellows.</head>
               <p>LEt the firſt place be the Preſidents, as alſo the firſt dignity, not only in the Colledge, but in all other places.</p>
               <p>Let the place and honour, next after the Preſident, be the Kings Phiſicians in ordinary, who receive a ſet Salary, and have Letters Patents under the Great Seal of the Kingdom.</p>
               <p>Let every ones place be according to his ſeniority, ſo that the juniors give place to the ſeniors, not only in the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, but alſo every where out of it.</p>
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:34510:81"/>
               <p>Now we call ſeniority, not what age or dignity, or the time of taking a degree any where, but what admiſſion into the Colledge maketh.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XVIII. Of Anatomical Adminiſtration, and ¶ The Chirurgical Lecture.</head>
               <p>WE appoint and ordain, That each Fellow at the time of Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion give his faith, that he will in publick Anatomically diſſect a Humane Body at the charge of the Colledge, in that year which the Preſident ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point, and that either in the Colledge, or ſome other place, to be aſſigned at the judgement of the Preſident and Electors; eſpecially if any ſhall ſeem to them skilful in Anatomy.</p>
               <p>But if any ſhall reſuſe the burden laid on him, and he be eſtecmed in their
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:34510:82"/>judgement leſs fit for that buſineſs, be ſhall pay four pounds to the uſe of the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: But if he ſhall obſtinately refuſe to perform this due Office, he at the pleaſure of the Preſident, and the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er part of the Fellows preſent, ſhall be fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; yet ſo that this Fine exceed not Twenty pounds.</p>
               <p>We alſo appoint and ordain, That no Fellow or any other Collegue, publickly profeſs or undertake the adminiſtration of a Humane Body, any where but in the Colledge, or place aſſigned by the Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and Electors, under the penalty of Four pounds; unleſs that place be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant from the City ſeven miles at leaſt.</p>
               <p>Yet we will, That it be free for any of the Collegues publickly to exerciſe Anato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my in Chirurgeons Hall, provided the Maſters and Wardens of the Community of Chirurgeons firſt ask leave for him of the Preſident or Pro-Preſident; for we judge it juſt and reaſonable, that they who profit by any one of the Collegues, ſhould ſhew ſome duty of reſpect to the Colledge.</p>
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:34510:83"/>
               <p>Moreover, we appoint, That all the Fellows and Candidates be preſent at each Publick Anatomical Diſſections made in the Colledge, decently clad with Gown and ap, for the honour of the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and Profeſſion.</p>
               <p>Who ſhall do otherwiſe, ſhall be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed three ſhillings and four pence.</p>
               <p>¶ That the Lecture in Chirurgery may be the better followed with a fuller com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of proper Auditors; therefore we will and appoint that all Candidates and all permitted to practiſe in this City, be obliged diligently to hear the Chirurgical Lecture; who ſhall do otherwiſe, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have himſelf more negligently in this matter, he as often as he ſhall be abſent, for that his abſence, each time, ſhall pay to the Colledge twelve pence; which ſum of money he that ſhall keep in his own bands, and ſhall refuſe to pay to the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer of the Colledge deputed for that purpoſe, within eight days after the end of that term, in which for his abſence it was formerly due; then we will that that
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:34510:84"/>fine of twelve pence be increaſed to two ſhillings and ſix pence, ſo often as it is defaulted.</p>
               <p>We will, moreover, That after they have diligently heard this Lecture for ſive whole years, then it may be free for them to uſe their own pleaſure in this matter for the future; for it is not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired by us that they ſhould be longer hearers of that Lecture, after five years diligently ſpent in that Study.</p>
               <p>We ſurther grant, That it may be free for every one at his pleaſure, to be thrice abſent in each Term without fine, and that the fine of thoſe who are abſent as often as it ſhall happen, go to the uſe of the Reader for the time being; and that it is eſtabliſh'd, that a due payment be made of all thoſe, before they can be admitted into the Colledge: for we judge it unfit, beſides the honour of the Art and the dignity of the Colledge, that our Reader expecting Auditors, ſhould to no purpoſe loſe his labour and pains.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:34510:85"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIX. Of the Ornament and Cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Phiſicians.</head>
               <p>WE appoint according to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of <hi>Hyppocrates,</hi> That all the Fellows be cloathed with a decent Garb, as often as they come to the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, or go forth in publick, leſt the excellency and dignity of our Art, by reaſon of ſlovinglineſs ſhould be reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and contemned by the Vulgar.</p>
               <p>Wherefore we appoint and ordain, That the Preſident and Pro-Preſident, Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, Cenſors, and all other Fellows, in all greater Meetings, Feaſts of the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legues, Funerals, and Anatomical Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrations, be cloathed with Gown and other decent apparel, upon penalty of five ſhillings to be paid to the Colledge, as often as they ſhall be delinquent.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:34510:86"/>
               <head>CHAP XX. Of Funeral Ceremonies.</head>
               <p>IF it happen that any one of the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legues die (unleſs he die of the Plague) every Collegue lawfully admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd by the Beadle, ſhall be obliged to be preſent at the Funeral, and to follow in his Order, and attend at the other Funeral Rites and Ceremonies, under penalty of Three ſhillings and four pence, to be paid to the uſe of the Colledge.</p>
               <p>Moreover, We will for the honour of the Colledge, that a Seat for the Preſident in the Church be adorned with Tepeſtry or Hangings, and a decent Cuſhion, for ſo long time as the Funeral Offices, and other Divine Solemnities are celebrated.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <pb n="143" facs="tcp:34510:87"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXI. Of Feaſtings.</head>
               <p>BEcauſe by honeſt Meetings mutual love is maintained, and the minds of ſtudious men recreated, We will that all who have been admitted into the Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety of the Colledge, entertain the Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and all the Fellows in Town, at a frugal, honeſt, and ſufficient Feaſt, and that at a time firſt appointed by the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident.</p>
               <p>But he appointeth it on the day of the ordinary or greater Meetings, or on what day he thinks fit of the fifteen next following the Feaſt of St. <hi>Michael,</hi> the <hi>Nativity</hi> of our Saviour, <hi>Eaſter,</hi> or the Nativity of St. <hi>John Baptiſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Feaſt over, it ſhall be lawful in the ſame place, excluding foreign Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, to call a Meeting, and treat of the
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:34510:88"/>buſineſs of the Colledge, if the matter re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire it and the Preſident and Counſellers ſhall judge it neceſſary.</p>
               <p>But if at any time it ſhall happen, that he whoſe duty it is to provide a Feaſt, cannot conveniently perform it, and therefore for ſome juſt and honeſt cauſe to be approved by the Preſident and greater part of the Society, he ſhall deſire of the Society to be kindly releaſed from this Law, and freed from that charge; we leave the whole matter to be moderated at the diſcretion of the Preſident and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety.</p>
               <p>Yet whatever Collegue ſhall obtain this favour, that he be releaſed from provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding a Feaſt, he ſhall pay to the uſe of the Colledge Ten or Twenty Pounds, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as it ſhall ſeem reaſonable to the Preſident and greater part of the Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <pb n="147" facs="tcp:34510:89"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXII. Of Moral Converſation and Penal Statutes.</head>
               <p>IF any ſtrife or controverſie ariſe from the order, gravity, and modeſty (which we preſcribe to be obſerved in our Meetings) not duly obſerved; whoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſhall offend, may be puniſhed at the pleaſure of the Preſident or Pro-Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and Cenſors.</p>
               <p>But if the Preſident ſhall commit any thing againſt the Statutes, let him be admoniſh'd by the Conſiliarii or Aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants, before the Fellows in our Meetings, but not puniſhed, unleſs for ſome grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous Crime, ſuch as is robbery or waſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the goods of the Colledge, and the like, ſo adjudged by the greater part of the Fellows, among whom we will that there be four of the Electors; who together with the reſt ſhall give their judgement on that matter.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="148" facs="tcp:34510:90"/>
                  <head>So much we attribute to the Honour and Authority of the Preſident.</head>
                  <p>Let none reveal or divulge any thing of any moment that is ſaid in the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, under the penalty of Ten ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings.</p>
                  <p>No Collegue ſhall by name accuſe ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther either of ignorance or ill practice, or any villany, or ignominious crime, or publickly reproach any of the Colledge.</p>
                  <p>If it ſhall appear to the Preſident and Cenſors that any has acted contrany, the firſt time he ſhall pay to the uſe of the Colledge Four pounds.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond the Mulct ſhall be doubled, but if any ſhall offend the third time, he ſhall be expelled the Colledge, neither ſhall he be reſtored again, before he has paid Ten pounds to the Colledge.</p>
                  <p>No Phiſician who ſhall be called ſecond to a ſick perſon, ſhall cauſe the former Phiſician to be turned away, nor ſhall he innovate any thing before (unleſs the matter be urgent) he ſhall meet him, and that there be no place for deceit, whoever
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:34510:91"/>is ſent for to a Sick Perſon, he ſhall ask of him or the By-ſtanders, whether any hath preſcribed a Medicine, under the Penalty of Twenty Shillings.</p>
                  <p>Yet afterwards at the pleaſure of the Sick, be ſhall alone Cure him, or Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter the buſineſs with the former Phyſician, or with any other.</p>
                  <p>Yet he ſhall do his endeavour, as much as in him lies, that he retain the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer with him in Practice.</p>
                  <p>But if that cannot be done with the Conſent of the Sick Perſon, or the Friends, he ſhall in no manner diſpraiſe the former Phyſician, neither by Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, Geſture, Suſpicious Silence, or by any other means blame his Actions to the Sick, or By-ſtanders; but he ſhall rather praiſe him, and that not deccit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully by the Name of Honeſty and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but (what chieſly pertains to the matter) of a Skilful and Intelligent Phyſician; always remembring, that he have the Reputation of another with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, in that eſteem, which if the Caſe were altered, he would deſire his own,
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:34510:92"/>to wit, for the Honour and Dignity of the Art he profeſſeth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The Form of Conſultation.</head>
                  <p>IF any for Cure ſake ſhall meet to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berate on the Condition of the Sick, they muſt conſult with the greateſt Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty, and not unleſs Forreign Arbiters are ſecluded: But let the buſineſs be tranſacted in Latine, otherwiſe let there be a Fine of five Shillings for the uſe of the Colledge.</p>
                  <p>Firſt of all they muſt diligently in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire into the Species or Kind, Cauſe and Symptoms of the Diſeaſe, and then Remedies moſt convenient for the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the Diſeaſe, and Mitigation of Symptoms, are to be propounded.</p>
                  <p>Let the Junior Phiſician begin, let the Senior conclude.</p>
                  <p>But if any Senior ſhall be firſt ſent ſor, let him firſt relate the whole matter to the reſt, to wit, what he hath done, and with what ſucceſs, then let them act as is Directed.</p>
                  <pb n="155" facs="tcp:34510:93"/>
                  <p>If they ſhall often meet to viſit the ſame ſick perſon, let none preſcribe any thing, nay let him not ſo much as hint what is to be done, before the ſick or by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanders, before with joyned counſels in private, it ſhall be concluded among the Phiſicians themſelves; leſt any ſhould ſeem too ambitiouſly to fore-ſtall Practice, and ſnatch the free opportunity of preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing from the reſt, unleſs upon ſome ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den and urgent occaſion (and that to be approved of by the Preſident and Cenſors) he ſhall be compelled to preſcribe alone.</p>
                  <p>If the Phiſicians are of diſſerent opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, ſo that they cannot agree among themſelves upon the ſame Practice, yet let them ſo manage themſelves with the greateſt Prudence and Moderation, that their Diſcord may not make to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice of the Art, neither if poſſible let it be known to others.</p>
                  <p>If there ſhall be only two Phyſicians, let the Junior yield to the Senior, or let them call a third, to whom the buſineſs may be referred; if many, let the greater part carry it, if the Diſſenting Phyſicians ſhall
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:34510:94"/>be equal in number, let it be concluded by greater part of the Seniors: ſo the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Dignity of the Art will be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, which would otherwiſe by the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord of Phyſicians be eaſily had in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt; he that ſhall Act contrary, ſhall be Fined Forty Shillings.</p>
                  <p>Leſt any ſtrife or controverſie ſhould ariſe among Phyſicians for Officious vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſits, fore-ſtallments and inſinuations,</p>
                  <p>We appoint and ordain, That when other Phyſicians ſhall be called to any Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician to conſult, and according to the form preſcribed by us; they are agreed of the Diſeaſe and Remedies: Let the Senior, or ſome other Phyſician, relate to the Sick, or By-ſtanders, what have been approved and preſcribed by Common Conſent, the Execution whereof the others ſhall leave to the Ordinary Phyſicians; nor ſhall they again viſit the Sick, unleſs they be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly deſired to do ſo from the Phyſician in Ordinary, or the Sick Perſon.</p>
                  <p>Let no Phyſician, whether Fellow or
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:34510:95"/>Candidate, or Permiſſive, conſult with an Empirick, or one expelled the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and forbid the Practice of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, or any other Practiſing Phyſick without Admiſſion or Permiſſion, unleſs upon ſome urgent Cauſe, to be approved of by the Preſident, or Pro-Preſident, and Cenſors, or the greateſt part of them, under the Penalty of Forty Shillings.</p>
                  <p>Let every Phyſician be content with an honeſt Reward, according to the Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Sick and his Labour.</p>
                  <p>Let none make a Bargain with the Sick, or with any other in the name of the Sick, about the Price of Cure.</p>
                  <p>But if any undertake Sick Perſons to Cure, who will not think themſelves o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe ſatisfied, unleſs they make a Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain with the Phyſician, or if he happen on thoſe, who have no regard of their Eſtate, or Honour, and act too ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringly, or illiberally, with Phyſicians, with ſuch it ſhall be lawful to make a Bargain, yet reſerving a Power for the Preſident and Cenſors, and in their ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, for Four of the Elect, at their
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:34510:96"/>prudence to correct and alter, if any thing be more unjuſtly covenanted.</p>
                  <p>Let none teach the People Medicines, or tell their Names to them (eſpecially if they are Vehement Medicines, as Purgers, Opiats, or Sleeping Medicines, or which cauſe Abortion, Vomits, or any other of greater moment or danger) leſt by the abuſe of them the People be injured; upon penalty of forty Shillings as often as they ſhall offend.</p>
                  <p>He that bargains with Apothecaries for any part of the Price ariſing from the Medicines to be preſcribed, ſhall be fined forty Shillings, as often as he ſhall ſo offend.</p>
                  <p>Let no Fellow Candidate or Permiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive, make uſe of thoſe Appothecaries, who either themſelves Practiſe Phyſick, or frequently ſerve thoſe Phyſicians, who are not Examined and Approved, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Statutes of this Kingdom, under penalty of Ten Shillings, to be paid to the Colledge, as often as he ſhall offend, provided he before-warned thereof by the
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:34510:97"/>Preſident or Pro-Preſident and Cenſors.</p>
                  <p>None ſhall refuſe to pay a Fine laid on him according to the Statutes, for a fault, under penalty of violating his Faith gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the Colledge.</p>
                  <p>Becauſe Aposhecaries and Chirurgeons, but eſpecially the Chirurgeons, often bring the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine of Sick People to Phyſicians, and deſire that from the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine they would preſcribe ſomething for their Sick; and under this pretence of Conſultation, manage the whole Courſe of Cure at their pleaſure, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever profit or gain there is; appropriating all to themſelves, but bringing to the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians nothing beſides that ſlender and hungry reward of inſpecting the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine.</p>
                  <p>Therefore, We Appoint and Ordain, That none, whether Fellow, Candidate, or Permiſſive, give any Advice to ſuch like Cheating Knaves and Impoſtors, upon the bare Inſpection of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine, unleſs he ſhall alſo be called to the Sick, and there, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as the matter ſhall require, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe proper Medicines to be Compound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:34510:98"/>by ſome honeſt Apothecary.</p>
                  <p>Moreover, We will that to each Scrowl or Receipt (as they call them) every one write the Day of the Month, Name of the Sick, and his own Name.</p>
                  <p>It is indeed ridiculous and fooliſh, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from the Inſpection of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine, after the manner of Soothſayers and Conjurers, to attempt to Divine any thing Certain and Solid, either of the Kind or Nature of the Diſeaſe, or of the State and Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Sick.</p>
                  <p>Therefore, We admoniſh all Phyſicians, that for the future, they carry themſelves much more wary in this matter, than heretofore was wont to be done of many; and for this Reaſon we forbid all Perſons Practiſing Phyſick, that they do not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe any Medicine to thoſe Idiots and Silly Women who carry the Piſpots of Sick Perſons about, unleſs they have firſt known the Sick Perſon; or at leaſt ſhall be plainly and fully inſtructed by thoſe who ask advice concerning the Diſeaſe and its circumſtances.</p>
                  <pb n="167" facs="tcp:34510:99"/>
                  <p>For by this means we ſhall both better defend the dignity of Phyſick, and alſo much more aptly and certainly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe Remedies to profit the Sick.</p>
                  <p>To conclude, We Appoint and Ordain, That, whoſoever is admitted into the Society of the Colledge, they promiſe by ſubſcribing their Names, that they will diligently obſerve all the aforeſaid Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, or willingly pay the Fines inflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on thoſe that act contrary.</p>
                  <p>If according to this Model, the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge be governed by the prudent counſel of the Preſident, Electors and Cenſors, and graced with the exact and obedient duty of the reſt, and adorned with Science, the Illiterate being rooted out, and the hateful Impoſtors exterminated, it is moſt certain that this our Colledge will be moſt flouriſhing for ever, and it will rightly and providently be conſulted for the whole Common-wealth (as much as belongs to our duties.)</p>
                  <p>Wherefore by the Faith given the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, we exhort and beſeech all the Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows that they have a diligent proſpect
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:34510:100"/>every way, and act prudently, and do not admit any for reſpect of Perſons into the Colledge; but that they determine all things for the Praiſe, Glory, Honour, and Perpetuity of the Society; becauſe it is certain our Colledge can by no means be more firmly eſtabliſhed and continued, then by good Laws, honeſt Governours, and Manners, and the ſingular Virtues and Learning of the Collegues.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div xml:lang="eng" type="notes">
            <pb n="168" facs="tcp:34510:100"/>
            <head>☞ The Statutes that are marked with theſe Characters * ¶ are ſuch that the Colledge thought good to leave out in their New Model, and theſe follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ought to be inſerted in thoſe Pages that the Numbers refer to.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag. 84.</hi> We will appoint, That no Candidate, before he be admitted into the Colledge and made Fellow, have ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Seal of our Colledge, or Letters Patents, ſuch as are granted to the Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows at their Admiſſion.</p>
            <pb n="171" facs="tcp:34510:101"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag. 87.</hi> Shall be puniſhed, either by Impriſonment, or Fine, or by both, at the pleaſure of the Preſident, Pro-Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and Cenſors, as often as they ſhall offend.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag. 91.</hi> That they give their Names to the Preſident and Cenſors, and to their power take care, that they bring with them, and have in readineſs, all thoſe Arguments and Teſtimonies which have any force or weight to accuſe them, that by this means all that race of male Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſers, be either wholly extirpated, or at leaſt more prudently reſtrained.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag. 95.</hi> You ſtall not by your ſelf or any other, in Word or Sign, declare the places of queſtions in Examinations, you ſhall be prepared for the Examination of thoſe who deſire to be examined and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted.</p>
            <p>To your Knowledge you ſhall not ſpeak nor act againſt the Colledge; the more choice Medicines you ſhall not write to an Apothecary, that you may gain his favour in procuring Patients.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="notes">
            <pb n="169" facs="tcp:34510:100"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 85. Volumus &amp; Statuimus, Ut nullus Candidatus antequam admitta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur in Collegium &amp; fiat Socius habeat aut Collegii noſtri Sigillum, aut Lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras Patentes, quales Sociis in admiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one conceduntur.</p>
            <pb n="170" facs="tcp:34510:101"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 86. Poenas luet, ſive per Carcerem, ſive per Mulctam, ſive per utrumque pro Praeſidis &amp; Pro-Praeſidis atque Cenſorum arbitrio toties quoties offenderit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 90. Eorum nomina Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidi &amp; Cenſoribus ſignificent curentque quantum in ſe eſt, ut omnia illa argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta &amp; teſtimonia, quae vim aliquam habent atque pondus ad eos accuſandos, unà ſecum adducant &amp; habeant in promptu, ut hâc ratione, tota illa ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leficorum progenies aut penitus extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petur, aut ſaltem paulo providentius coerceatur.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 94. Non indicabis verbo aut ſigno per te, aut alium loca quaeſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem in examinationibus, paratus eris ad examinationem eorum, qui petunt examinari &amp; admitti.</p>
            <p>Sciens non loqueris nec ages contra Collegium, pretioſiora Medicamenta, non ſcribes Pharmacopolae, quo favo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem ejus in procurandis aegris de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merearis.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="eng" type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:34510:102"/>
            <head>INDEX.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 1.</hi> OF the Electors. <hi>Page 7.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Their Office. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Oath. <hi>p. 11.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap 2.</hi> Of the Preſident. <hi>p. 12.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>His Oath. <hi>p. 15.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>His Office. <hi>p. 20.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 3.</hi> Of the Pro-Preſident. <hi>p. 24.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>His Office. <hi>p. 27.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 4.</hi> Of the Aſſiſtants. <hi>p. 28.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Their Oath. <hi>p. 31.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Duty. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 5.</hi> Of the Cenſors. <hi>p. 35.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Their Office. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Oath. <hi>p. 36.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 6.</hi> Of the Meetings and of the Beadle. <hi>p. 39.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>His Oath. <hi>p. 40.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>His Office. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Summoning the Collegues to the Meetings. <hi>p. 44.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 7.</hi> Of the Ordinary and Extraordinary times of Meetings, <hi>&amp;c. p. 52.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Examinations of Fellows, Candi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dates, and Permiſſives. <hi>p. 56.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 8.</hi> Of Making and Abrogating Statutes, and Levying Fines. <hi>p. 64.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:34510:103"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 9.</hi> The Office of the Treaſurer. <hi>p. 67.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>His Oath. <hi>p. 71.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 10.</hi> Of the Regiſter. <hi>p. 72.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>His Oath. <hi>p. 76.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 11.</hi> Of the Candidates. <hi>p. 79.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Their Oath. <hi>p. 80.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Secret Medicines. <hi>p. 85.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of their Payments. <hi>p. 87.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 12.</hi> Of the Fellows. <hi>p. 91.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Their Oath. <hi>p. 92.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Letters of Admiſſion. <hi>p. 96.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 13.</hi> Letters Teſtimenial of thoſe that Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe thorow <hi>England. p. 103.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 14.</hi> Of Suppreſſing Quacks. <hi>p. 104.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Form of Letters to Magiſtrates. <hi>p. 107.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 15.</hi> Of Licentiates. <hi>p. 108.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 16.</hi> The Form of the Examinations <hi>p. 119.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Form of Admiſſion. <hi>p. 127.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 17.</hi> Of the Place and Dignity of the Preſident and Fellows. <hi>p. 128.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 18.</hi> Of Anatomical Adminiſtration, and the Chirurgical Lecture. <hi>p. 131.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 19.</hi> Of the Ornament and Cloathing of Phiſicians. <hi>p. 139.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 20.</hi> Of Funeral Ceremenies. <hi>p. 140.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 21.</hi> Of Feaſtings. <hi>p. 143.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 22.</hi> Of Moral Converſation and Penal Statutes. <hi>p. 147.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Form of Conſultation. <hi>p. 152.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:34510:102"/>
            <head>INDEX.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 1. DE Electoribus. <hi>Page</hi> 6.</item>
               <item>Officium. Ibid.</item>
               <item>Fides data. <hi>p.</hi> 10.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 2. De Praeſide. <hi>p.</hi> 13.</item>
               <item>Sponſio ſeu Fides data. <hi>p.</hi> 14.</item>
               <item>Officium. <hi>p.</hi> 22.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 3. De Pro-Praeſide. <hi>p.</hi> 25.</item>
               <item>Officium. <hi>p.</hi> 26.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 4. De Conſiliariis. <hi>p.</hi> 29.</item>
               <item>Data Fides. <hi>p.</hi> 30.</item>
               <item>Officium. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cap. 5.</hi> De Cenſoribus. <hi>p.</hi> 34.</item>
               <item>Officium. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Juramentum. <hi>p.</hi> 37.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 6. De Comitiis &amp; de Bedello. <hi>p.</hi> 38.</item>
               <item>Data Fides. <hi>p.</hi> 41.</item>
               <item>Officium. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>De Collegis Admonendis ad Comitia. <hi>p.</hi> 45.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 7. De Temporibus Ordinariis &amp; Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinariis, <hi>&amp;c. p.</hi> 53.</item>
               <item>Examinatio Sociorum, Candidato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, &amp; Permiſſorum. <hi>p.</hi> 57.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 8. De Statutis Condendis &amp; Abrogandis, &amp; de Mulctis. <hi>p.</hi> 65.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:34510:103"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 9. De Officio Theſaurarn. <hi>p.</hi> 66.</item>
               <item>Data Fides. <hi>p.</hi> 70.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 10. De Regiſtrario. <hi>p.</hi> 73.</item>
               <item>Data Fides. <hi>p.</hi> 77.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 11. De Candidatis. <hi>p.</hi> 78.</item>
               <item>Data Fides. <hi>p.</hi> 81.</item>
               <item>De Arcanis. <hi>p.</hi> 85.</item>
               <item>De Solutionibus. <hi>p.</hi> 86.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 12. De Sociis. <hi>p.</hi> 90.</item>
               <item>Data Fides. <hi>p.</hi> 93.</item>
               <item>Literae Admiſſionis. <hi>p.</hi> 97.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 13. Literae Teſtimoniales Practicantium per Regnum. <hi>p.</hi> 102.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 14. De Coercendis Empiricis. <hi>p.</hi> 105.</item>
               <item>Forma Literarum ad Senatores. <hi>p.</hi> 106.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 15. De Permiſſis. <hi>p.</hi> 109.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 16. Forma Examinationum. <hi>p.</hi> 118.</item>
               <item>Formula Admiſſionis. <hi>p.</hi> 126.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 17. De Loco &amp; Dignitate Praeſidis &amp; Sociorum. <hi>p.</hi> 129.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 18. De Anatomica Adminiſtratione &amp; Lectura Chirurgiae. <hi>p.</hi> 130.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 19. De Ornatu &amp; Veſtitu Medicorum. <hi>p.</hi> 138.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 20. De Exequiis. <hi>p.</hi> 141.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 21. De Conviviis. <hi>p.</hi> 142.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cap</hi> 22. De Converſatione Morali &amp; Statutis Poenalibus. <hi>p.</hi> 146.</item>
               <item>Conſultandi Formula. <hi>p.</hi> 153.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="eng" type="statutes">
            <pb n="176" facs="tcp:34510:104"/>
            <head>THE <hi>NEW STAT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TES</hi> OF The Preſident of the Colledge, or Commonalty of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of <hi>PHISICK</hi> of <hi>LONDON,</hi> Made by the Preſident of the Colledge, or Commonalty aforeſaid, with the conſent of the Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of the Colledge, or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monalty aforeſaid, in the year 1687. and that they may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main eſtabliſh'd, fix'd, and certain, ſigned with the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Seal of the ſame Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, or Commonalty afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, the 28th of <hi>September,</hi> in the year 1687.</head>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> THat none, to any but the abſent Fellows, reveal or divulge the Secrets of the Colledge, or
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:34510:105"/>any thing of any moment, that is ſaid in the Aſſemblies, whether greater or leſſer, under the penalty of Forty ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings the firſt time, Five pounds the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, and the third Expulſion from the Colledge: We will have all that eſteemed for a ſecret or matter of moment, whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſhall be pronounced in the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies or Meetings by the Preſident or the two Senior Cenſors preſent, fit to becon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> Let no Phiſician, whether Fellow or Candidate, or Licentiate, conſult with an Empirick, or who is rejected by the Colledge, or forbidden the Practice of Phiſick, or any other practiſing Phiſick without Admiſſion or Permiſſion, who is not Phiſician to the King or the Royal Family, and to whom a Salary hath been aſſigned, or who by chance ſhall come out of the Countrey, with no deſign of ſtaying in the City, under the penalty of Ten pounds.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="180" facs="tcp:34510:106"/>
               <hi>3.</hi> Let no Phiſician who ſhall be called ſecond to a ſick perſon, cauſe the former Phiſician to be repelled or put by, nor ſhall he alter any thing, unleſs the matter be urgent, before he meet his Collegue; and that there be no place for deceit, whoever is ſent for to a ſick perſon, ſhall inquire of him or the by-ſtanders, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any one hath preſcribed any Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine, under the penalty of Forty ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings the firſt time, the ſecond Five pounds; but if any ſhall in like manner offend the third time, he ſhall be expelled the Colledge.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4.</hi> If to viſit the ſame ſick perſon, two or more Phiſicians ſhall meet together, let none preſcribe any thing, nay let him not ſo much as hint what is to be done, in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the ſick or by-ſtanders, before with joynt counſel in private, it ſhall he concluded betwixt them; leſt he ſeem too ambitiouſly to fore-ſtall Practice, and ſnatch the free opportunity of preſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing from all the reſt, unleſs by ſome ſudden and urgent occaſion, and that to
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:34510:107"/>be approved by the Preſident and Cenſors, he ſhall be compelled to preſcribe alone; under the penalty of Five pounds, as of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten as he is delinquent: but if any ſhall be found often to offend in this matter or part, let him be removed from the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge with ignominy.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5.</hi> Leſt any ſtrife or controverſie ſhould ariſe between Phiſicians for offici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous viſitings, foreſtallments, and inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuations, we appoint and ordain, that when other Phiſicians ſhall be called to any Phiſician to conſult, that the elder Phiſician, or ſame other, relate to the ſick, or by-ſtanders, what by common conſent have been approved and preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, and let the reſt leave the execution thereof to the ordinary Phiſician; nor ſhall they again viſit the ſick, unleſs ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly deſired to do ſo by the ordinary Phiſician, or from the ſick perſon, on the penalty of Five pounds as often as they ſhall be found delinquent.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="184" facs="tcp:34510:108"/>
               <hi>6.</hi> None ſhall refuſe to pay Subſcriptions or Payments due, or laſtly Fines inflicted on them for default, according to the Statutes, under penalty of expulſion from the Colledge.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <hi>7.</hi> Seeing by the wandering Diſcourſe of men there is a report that ſome Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians of our Community, after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Empericks, diſperſe Bills among the common People, whereby they may hawk out a ſordid and mean practice among the ordinary ſort of people, and in the mean time bring no ſmall diſhonour to the faculty of Phyſick, We Appoint and Ordain, that no Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legue Print, Divulge, or by any means Publiſh any Book, Treatiſe, Table, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, or Pamphlet whatſoever, wherein is contained any thing that relates to the Art of Phiſick or Chirurgery, or the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of them, without leave and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of the Preſident and Cenſors, or the greater part of them, under the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty of four pounds the firſt time, eight pounds the ſecond, but the third Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion from the Colledge.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <pb n="187" facs="tcp:34510:109"/>
               <hi>8.</hi> If by chance any Chirurgeon or A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothecary ſhall offer himſelf to the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident and Cenſors to be examined, that he may be received into the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Candidates, or Licentiates; We will that he before Examination, or at leaſt before Admiſſion, be wholly diſcharged from all Tie and Obligation, wherewith he was formerly oblidged to his Community; for we do not think it juſt or convenient, to admit any into our Society, who hath his Faith oblidged to another.</p>
            <p n="9">
               <hi>9.</hi> Becauſe it is found by Experience that the Apothecaries from the Preſcripts of Phyſicians, attain ſome pretence or ſhadow of falſe Knowledge (every where boaſting themſelves to Sick Perſons) which they abuſe, not without the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of others, to their own profit; We Determine and Ordain, that no Collegue for the future, either Fellow, Candidate, or Licentiate, add Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as they call them, to their Preſcripts or Phyſical Scrowls (ſave only in Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals)
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:34510:110"/>but he ſhall leave them with the Sick, or at leaſt take care that they be firſt ſigned and carried to his houſe; in the mean time let him command, that the Medicines preſcribed in the Scrowls be only ſigned with ſome agreeable titles or apt notes for their diſtinction, to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent that as much as in us lies, nothing at all be ſmelt out by this ſort of Medica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, with what deſign, intention, or for what uſes the Remedies are preſcribed: let every one be fined Twenty Shillings for the uſe of the Colledge as often as they ſhall fail in this part.</p>
            <p n="10">
               <hi>10.</hi> Let no Fellow, Candidate, or Permiſſive, make uſe of an Apothecary whom in the greater Meetings (at which all Collegues of all ranks are fore-warned that they be preſent) the Preſident hath renounced, or declared to practice Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, or has been twice about that matter ſummoned to appear before the Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and Cenſors, and has not appeared, on the penalty of Forty ſhillings the firſt
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:34510:111"/>time, the ſecond five pounds, and the third Expulſion from the Colledge. Let the Office of the Preſident and Cenſors be to inquire into ſuch like cauſes, weigh the matters, and define who is guilty of Practice; and whom they or the greater part of them, ſhall judge ſo, we deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine and will, that he be called, and is, a Practiſing Apothecary. Laſtly, We charge and command the Fellows, with all the reſt of the Collegues, that laying aſide all affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and reſpest of perſons, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomever Apothecaries of that ſort they find to have practiſed, they bring their names to the Preſident and Cenſors, and that under the penalty of breach of Faith given to the Colledge.</p>
            <p n="11">
               <hi>11.</hi> Whereas ſome of our Statutes ſeem more ſeverely to have conſtituted the penalty of Expulſion to Delinquents, ſo that all hope and expectation of return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into the Colledge being precluded, and no place is left for repentance, it hath ſeemed good ſo to moderate this ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity of Laws, with ſome mixture of
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:34510:112"/>clemency, that if any expelled out of the Colledge, openly, ingenuouſly, and ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively, confeſs his Crime in the greater Meetings, and withal preſently pay whatever Fines have been formerly laid on him for defaults, and ten pounds be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides for the uſe of the Colledge; on theſe Conditions it may be lawful for the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident and greater part of the Fellows, to reſtore him to his former Place, State, and Dignity.</p>
            <p n="12">
               <hi>12.</hi> We appoint that every year on the ſame day, and with the ſame ſuffrages wherewith the Cenſors are wont to be crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that ten men be choſe out of the Fellows, that are more fit then, the reſt to expedite and diſpatch buſineſs; in the number of which we will always have the Preſident, who for the following year are the ſtated Delegates or Committee men, and it may be lawful for them at any time, according to their pleaſure to meet, diſcourſe and handle matters of any ſort, relating to the Profit, or Honour of the Colledge, to relate their Opinions
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:34510:113"/>and Conſults to the Society in the greater Meetings: Laſtly, to execute and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form all other things that our moſt Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Prince <hi>James</hi> the Second, in Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Patents lately given us, hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to our charge.</p>
            <p n="13">
               <hi>13.</hi> In the Election of a Treaſurer, we will that altogether the ſame form be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, which is before appointed by us in creating the Cenſors, to wit, that he be choſe after the ſame manner, at the ſame time, and by the ſame Suffrages; and moreover we appoint that the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer now Elect, before he be admitted to his Office, be oblidged by a Bond ſigned with his own Seal, to the Preſident and our Society, that at the ſummons of the ſame Preſident and Electors, he, to them, and four other Fellows appointed to this purpoſe, by the Colledge, ſhall faithfully give an account of what is received and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burſt: and laſtly, the Accounts made up, whatſomever the ſum of the Remainder due to the Colledge ſhall be, he will pay it to the ſaid Colledge, within twenty
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:34510:114"/>days after the Account is made up. Let the Witneſſes made uſe of to this Bond be three Foreigners, who are joyned with us by no right of Community.</p>
            <p n="14">
               <hi>14.</hi> We will that the Seal of the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge for the future be ſet to no Letters Teſtimonial, ſave to thoſe Fellows to whom at the time of their Admiſſion by the Statutes, it is granted to have, that is to thoſe who have a right of Voting in greater Meetings: But let them pay the Beadle ten Shillings for theſe Letters, as for others by which a Licence to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice without the City is granted, us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſigned by the Hands and Seals of the Preſident only and three of the Elect, let the Licentiates pay ſix ſhillings and eight pence.</p>
            <p n="15">
               <hi>15.</hi> Whereas formerly there was no convenient place within the Colledge, wherein our Writings might be kept, we have thought good for theſe uſes in the Study of <hi>Henry Guy <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
               </hi> to build a Desk or Paper-Treaſury, whereof let
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:34510:115"/>there be Four Keys; one of them let the Preſident have, another the Treaſurer, and both the two Senior Cenſors likewiſe one: in this Place and Cuſtody we will that the Diplomata of Princes, Bonds, and other Inſtruments of the Colledge, and laſtly, all Papers whatſomever of that ſort, and Parchments which are of greater moment, be contained and kept; but we forbid that any thing be brought out thence without the conſent of the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, unleſs by chance or ſome urgent neceſſity, it ſhall otherwiſe ſeem good to the Committee, or Preſident, and Cenſors; beſides we appoint that in the ſame place be laid up the Common Seal of the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in a ſmall Cabinet made for this purpoſe, whoſe Key let the Preſident have, and as often as need ſhall be, let him open it in the greater Meetings: neither will we that our Common Seal be affixed to any Inſtrument elſewhere, then in the aforeſaid Aſſemblies.</p>
            <p n="16">
               <pb n="200" facs="tcp:34510:116"/>
               <hi>16.</hi> We appoint and ordain, That no Chirurgeen, Apothecary, or any ſuch Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificer, be admitted into the Order of Candidates, on Fellows, whoever hath exerciſed, any leſs liberal Art, or bound to Servitude, hath laid his beginning in a Shop, leſt peradventure if we ſhould ſo chooſe ſuch into the Colledge, we might ſeem not ſufficiently to have conſulted either our own Dignity or the Honour of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities of <hi>England,</hi> which not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding we ought and always will Honour with the higheſt Veneration.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="statutes">
            <pb n="177" facs="tcp:34510:104"/>
            <head>
               <hi>STATUTA NOVA</hi> Praeſidis Collegii, ſeu Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatis Facultatis <hi>MEDI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CINAE LONDINI,</hi> per Praeſidem Collegii, ſeu Communitatem praedictam, per conſenſum Praeſidis, Collegii, ſeu Communitatis praedictae, Anno <hi>1687</hi> facta, &amp; ut rata firma ac certa permaneant Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gillo Communi ejuſdem Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gii, ſeu Communitatis praedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctae <hi>28</hi> die Septembris <hi>1687,</hi> munita.</head>
            <p n="1">1. UT nè quis cuiquam praeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam Sociis abſentibns revelet, aut propalet Secreta Collegii,
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:34510:105"/>aut quidquam alicujus momenti quod in Comitiis (ſive majoribus ſive mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noribus) dictum ſit, ſub poenâ Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draginta ſolidorum primâ vice, Quin que librarum ſecundâ vice, &amp; tertiâ Expulſionis à Collegio, id autem omne pro ſecreto, &amp; re momenti haberi vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumus, quicquid à Praeſide, vel Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorum praeſentium duobus Senioribus celandum eſſe in Comitiis pronuntia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum fuerit.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Nullus Medicus, ſive Socius, ſive Candidatus, ſive Permiſſus, Conſili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um ineat cum Empirico, aut Rejecto à Collegio, aut à Medicinae praxi pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibito, aut aliô aliquô, ſine Admiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one, aut Permiſſione Medicinam ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercente, qui non ſit Medicus Regius, aut Regiae Familiae, cui Stipendium aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignatum fuerit, vel qui fortè è Rure advenerit nullô in Urbe commoran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di Conſiliô ſub poena Decem libra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="181" facs="tcp:34510:106"/>3. Nullus Medicus qui ſecundus ad aegrum vocabitur, priorem Medicum repelli ſaciat, nec quidquam priùs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novabit, niſi res urgeat, quàm Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legam convenerit, &amp; ne quis fraudi locus ſit; quicunque ad aegrum accer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitur, ab illo, vel aſtantibus percun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctabitur, an quis Medicamentum ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quod praeſcripſerit ſub poenâ Quadra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginta ſolidorum primâ vice, ſecundâ Quinque librarum, ſi quis autem ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiâ vice pariter offenderit, expelletur à Collegio.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Si ad eundem aegrum viſendum, duo, vel plures Medici ſimul convene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rint nemo quidquam praeſcribat immò ne innuat quidem, quid agendum ſit, coram aegro, vel adſtantibus priuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quàm conjunctis Conſiliis, privatim inter ipſos concluſum fuerit nè ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiosè nimiùm videatur praxin praeoccu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare &amp; reliquis liberam praeſcribendi anſam praeripere, niſi ſubita &amp; urgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te aliquâ occaſione eàque approbandâ
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:34510:107"/>à Praeſide &amp; Cenſoribus coactus fuerit ſolus praeſcribere ſub poenâ quinque librarum, quoties deliquerit: quod ſi quis in hac parte ſaepius offendiſſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendetur à Collegio cum ignominiâ amoveatur.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Ne qua lis, aut Controverſia inter Medicos propter officioſas viſitationes, praeoccupationes, &amp; inſinuationes ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atur; ſtatuimus &amp; ordinamus, ut quum ad Medicum quemlibet, alii Medici, conſultandi gratiâ advocati fuerint, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior Medicus, vel alius aliquis referat aegro, aut adſtantibus, quae approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, &amp; praeſcripta communi conſenſu fuerint, eorundemque executionem caeteri ordinario Medico relinquant, nec denuò viſitabunt aegrum niſi à Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dico ordinario, aut ab aegro, ut id fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciant expreſsè rogati fuerint, ſub poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nâ quinque librarum toties quoties deliquerint.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="185" facs="tcp:34510:108"/>6. Nemo ſubſcriptiones, aut ſolutiones debitas, aut denique Mulctas ſibi pro delicto, ſecundùm Statuta inflictas, ſolvere recuſabit, ſub poenâ expulſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis è Collegio.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Quoniam pervagato hominnm ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mone fama percrebuit, quoſdam noſtrae Communitatis Medicos, Empericorum more Schedulas in vulgus ſpargere, quibus ut inter plebeios ſordidam, &amp; illiberalem praxin aucupentur, facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tati interim Medicinae haud le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vem ignominiae labem aſpergunt, Statuimus &amp; Ordinamus, nè quis Collega Typis Mandet, divulget, aut quoquô modô in Publicum emittat li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brum aliquem, Tractatum. Tabellam, Chartam, Schedulamve aliquam, in quibus contineatur quicquam quod ad Artem Medicinae, vel Chirurgiae, earumve praxin ſpectet, ſine permiſſu, &amp; approbatione Praeſidis, &amp; Cenſorum, vel eorum majore parte, ſub poenâ quatuor librarum primâ vice, octo librarum ſecundâ, tertiâ autem Expul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionis è Collegio.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <pb n="186" facs="tcp:34510:109"/>8. Si quis fortè Chirurgus, aut Pharmacopola, ſe Praeſidi, &amp; Cenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus Examinandum obtulerit, quò in Candidatorum, Permiſſorumve Numerum recipiatur; eum, ante ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aminationem, aut ſaltem ante Admiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem, omni Jure &amp; Obligatione pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitùs exui volumus, quibus ſuae Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munitati prius obſtringebatur; neque enim aequum; aut commodum cenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus quemquam in Societatem noſtram admittere qui Fidem alteri addictam habet.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Quoniam Experientiâ compertum eſt, Pharmacopolas ex Medicorum praeſcriptis, ſpeciem quandam, &amp; umbram falſae Scientiae conſectari, quâ ſe paſſim aegris venditantes, non ſine aliorum periculô, ad ſuum compendium abutuntur; Statui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, &amp; Ordinamus, nè quis in poſterum Collega, ſive Socius, ſive Candidatus, ſive Praemiſſus, praeſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis ſuis, ſeu Schedulis Medicinalibus, directiones (quas vocant) adjiciant
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:34510:110"/>(praeterquam in Noſocomiis) ſed eas apud aegrum ipſe relinquet, aut ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem priùs obſignatas ad ejus domum transferendas curabit; Medicamenta interim in Schedulis praeſcripta, jubeat ſolummodò ut titulis quibuſdam con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruentibus, aut notis ad eorum diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionem aptis ſignentur, nempè ut quantum in nobis eſt, nihil quicquam hujuſmodi Medicaſtris Suboleat, quô conſilio, quâ ve intentione, aut in quos uſus Remedia praeſcribantur: mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctentur autem ſinguli viginti ſolidis in uſum Collegii quoties in hâc parte deliquerit.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Nullus Socius, Candidatus, aut Permiſſus, Pharmacopolae operâ uta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, quem in Comitiis majoribus (quibus ut interſint omnes omnium ordinum Collegae praemoniti ſunt) Praeſes renunciaverit, aut Medicinae praxin exercere, aut eâ de causâ bis citatum, ut ſe ſiſteret coram Praeſide, &amp; Cenſoribus, nondum comparuiſſe, ſub poenâ quadraginta ſolidorum pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mâ
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:34510:111"/>vice, ſecundâ quinque librarum, &amp; tertiâ Expulſionis è Colegio. Praeſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis autem &amp; Cenſorum eſto hujus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modi cauſas cognoſcere, momenta ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendere, &amp; definire, quis praxeos te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neatur, &amp; quem illi, aut major pars eorum judicaverit, eum nos Pharmacopolam Practicantem eſſe, ſtatuimus &amp; appellari volumus. Denique Sociis, caeteriſque Collegis omnibus, precipimus, &amp; mandamus, ut ſepoſitô omni affectu, &amp; reſpectu Perſonarum, ejuſmodi Pharmacopoeos quoſcunque praxin exercuiſle depre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henderint, eorum nomina Praeſidi, &amp; Cenſoribus deferant, idque ſub poenâ violatae Fidei Collegio Praeſtitae.</p>
            <p n="11">11. Cum Statuta quaedam noſtra graviùs Delinquentibus poenam Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſionis ita conſtituiſſe videantur, ut praecluſâ omni ſpe, &amp; expectatione re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deundi in Collegium, nihil quicquam loci relictum eſt penitentiae, viſum eſt hanc legum ſeveritatem Clementiae temperatione aliquâ ſic moderari, ut
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:34510:112"/>ſi quis è Collegio Expulſus, culpam ſuam in majoribus Comitiis apertè, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuè, &amp; demiſsè confiteatur, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulque mulctas quaſcunque ob de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licta priùs irrogata, &amp; praeterea decem libras in uſum Collegii ſtatim ſolvat, illum his Conditionibus li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceat Praeſidi, &amp; majori parti Socio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum in priſtinum Locum, Statum, &amp; Dignitatem reſtituere.</p>
            <p n="12">12. Statuimus, ut ſingulis annis eôdem die, iiſdemque Suffragiis qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Cenſores creaii ſolent, è Sociis decem eligantur viri, ad expedien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da &amp; tranſigenda negotia prae caeteris maximè idonei (quô in numero Praeſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem, ſemper haberi volumus) qui in annum ſequentem, ſtati ſint deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gati, iiſque liceat quoquô tempore pro ſuô Arbitrio convenire res qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litercunque ad utilitatem, aut hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem Collegii ſpectantes diſcutere, &amp; tractare, ſuaſque ſententias, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulta ad Societatem in Comitiis ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joribus
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:34510:113"/>referre: Denique caetera ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equi, &amp; praeſtare quaecunque ipſis Sereniſſimus Princeps <hi>Jacobus</hi> Secun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus in Literis Patentibus nuper ad nos datis procuranda commiſit.</p>
            <p n="13">13. In Theſaurarii Electione, ean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem prorſus formam, obſervari vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumus quae à nobis anteà in Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoribus creandis conſtituta eſt, nem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe ut eodem modo, eôdem tempore, &amp; per eadem Suffragia eligatur, tùnc praetereà ſtatuimus, ut Theſaurarius jam electus, priuſquàm admittatur ad Officium ſuum, Chirographô Sigillô ſuô ſignatô obligetur Praeſidi, &amp; Societati noſtrae, ſe monitu ejuſdem Praeſidis &amp; Electorum, ipſis quatuorque aliis Sociis ad hanc rem à Collegio deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatis, accepti, &amp; expenſi rationem fidelitèr redditurum, &amp; denique cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culis ſubductis, quaecunque reliqui ſumma fuerit, Collegio debiti, eam ſe intra dies viginti à peracto com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puto eidem Collegio praeſtiturum,
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:34510:114"/>teſtes autem adhibeantur huic obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gationi tres extranei, qui nullô com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munitatis jure nobiſcum conjuncti ſunt.</p>
            <p n="14">14. Nullis in poſterum Literis Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonialibus, apponi volumus figil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum Collegii, preterquam iſtis, quas tempore Admiſſionis ſuae, per Statuta Sociis habere conceditur, iis nempe qui jus habent Suffragii in majoribus Comitiis; ſolvantur autom Bedello pro hujuſmodi Literis decem ſolidos, pro aliis vero quibus extra Urbem practicandi Licentia conceditur ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potè Chirographis, &amp; Sigillis Praeſidis ſolummodò, &amp; trium Electorum mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niendis, ſolvant permiſſi ſex ſolidos octò denarios.</p>
            <p n="15">15. Cum nullus olim intra Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legium locus extiterit idoneus in quô Scripta noſtra conſervarentur, placuit ad hos uſus in Muſaeo <hi>Henr. Guii.</hi> Armigeri Scriniam, vel Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to-phylaceum extrui, cujus quatuor
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:34510:115"/>ſint Claves eorumque unam Praeſes, alteram Theſaurarius, duorum au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem Cenſorum Seniorum, uterque itidem unam habeant, hic loci atque hâc Cuſtodiâ contineri volumus, &amp; ſervari, Principum Diplomata, Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rographa, caeteraque Inſtrumenta Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legii; denique alias id genus Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulas quaſcunque, &amp; membranas, quae ſunt majoris momenti: Prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bemus autem indè proferri quid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam injuſſû Collegii, niſi fortè ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gente aliquâ neceſſitate alitèr viſum fuerit deligatis, aut Praeſidi, &amp; Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoribus, Praeterea ſtatuimus ut eôdem locô reponatur Sigillum Commune Collegii, in Arculâ in hunc finem fabricatâ, cujus Clavem Praeſes ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beat, &amp; quoties opus fuerit in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joribus Comitiis ipſe aperiat, neque alibi quam in Comitiis praedictis cuicunque Inſtrumento Sigillum no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrum Commune apponi volumus.</p>
            <p n="16">
               <pb n="201" facs="tcp:34510:116"/>16. Statuimus &amp; Ordinamus, Ut in Candidatorum vel Sociorum Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem nullus admittatur Chirurgus, Pharmacopaeus, aliuſve aliquis ejuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modi Artifex, qui aut artem quam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque minùs liberalem unquam ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercuerit, aut ad ſervitutem adſtrictus in Officina Tyrocinium poſuit, nè forte ſi tales in Collegium ita co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>optentur, non ſatis conſuluiſſe videa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur, aut Dignitati noſtrae, aut Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri Academiarum noſtratium quas ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſummâ veneratione proſequi debemus, &amp; ſemper volumus.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
